<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4242734</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1470-7330-14-S1-S5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1470-7330-14-S1-S5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Scientific Session Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Robot-assisted navigation system for CT-guided percutaneous lung tumour procedures: our initial experience in Hong Kong</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>charmantchu@gmail.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>SCH</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Imaging and Interventional Radiology The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Prince of Wales Hospital, Shatin, N.T., Hong Kong</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">Proceedings of the International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication charges for this supplement were funded through the International Cancer Imaging Society by support received from Siemens AG, Healthcare Sector, Imaging and Therapy Division.</named-content></supplement><fpage>S5</fpage><lpage>S5</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Chu and Yu; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chu and Yu; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cancerimagingjournal.com/content/14/S1/S5"/><conference><conf-date>9-11 October 2014</conf-date><conf-name>International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</conf-name><conf-loc>Heidelberg, Germany</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>To evaluate the new robot-assisted navigation system for CT-guided lung tumour procedures</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>Imaging-guided lung procedures are usually challenging due to patient breathing. This is an ongoing prospective study with 50 patients targeted in a university-based hospital. This was an initial assessment of efficacy involving 10 patients with lung tumours who underwent CT-guided lung interventions utilizing the robot-assisted Navigation system (Maxio, Perfint Healthcare, USA). The targeted needle pathway was planned on Maxio Robotic system based on pre-procedural CT-scans. The primary endpoint was satisfactory instrument position for intended intervention. Lesion size and depth from skin were noted. Performance level was documented on a five-point scale (5-1: excellent-poor). Total radiation doses were recorded and compared against 20 patients with conventional CT-guidance and CT-fluoroscopy lung procedures (ratio 1:1).</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>There were 7 male and 3 female patients in the robotic group. Average age was 72.1 years (range 67-78). 8 patients underwent lung biopsy while the rest had thermal ablation or fiducial marker insertion. Average lesion size was 2.8cm (range 1.9-4.1cm). Average lesion depth was 6.2cm (range 3.7-8.6cm). All interventions met the primary endpoint of satisfactory instrument positioning. Average performance levels were 4.5. Average radiation dose (Dose Linear Product) was 480.4 (range 196.5-959.8) whereas conventional CT-guidance was 645.4 (range 285.1-1043.5) and CT-fluoroscopy was 460.1 (range 214.2-1157.0).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our initial experience demonstrated effectiveness of the robot-assisted navigation system for CT-guided lung tumour interventions with lower radiation dose compared with conventional CT-guided procedures. Radiation doses were similar to CT-fluoroscopy without radiation exposure to interventional radiologists. Targeting success rate for satisfactory intervention was 100%.</p></sec></body></article>