<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Biol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CBM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Biology &#x00026; Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-3941</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Chinese Anti-Cancer Association</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009754</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4069797</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">cbm-11-02-123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7497/j.issn.2095-3941.2014.02.007</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of postmastectomy radiotherapy on prognosis in different tumor stages of breast cancer patients with positive axillary lymph nodes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Miao-Miao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Zhi-Jie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="afn1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Ling-Mei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>Xu-Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff><target id="aff1" target-type="aff"><sup>1</sup></target>The First Department of Breast Cancer, Tianjin Medical University Cancer Institute and Hospital, Key Laboratory of Breast Cancer Prevention and Therapy, Tianjin Medical University, Ministry of Education, Tianjin 300060, <country>China</country>; <target id="aff2" target-type="aff"><sup>2</sup></target>Department of Pathology, Tianjin Medical University Cancer Institute and Hospital, National Clinical Research Center of Cancer, Tianjin 300060, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn id="afn1"><label>*</label><p>These authors equally contributed to this work.</p></fn><fn id="afn2"><p>Correspondence to: Xu-Chen Cao</p></fn><fn id="afn3"><p>E-mail: <email xlink:href="CXC@medmail.com.cn">CXC@medmail.com.cn</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><!--Fake ppub date generated by PMC from publisher
							pub-date/@pub-type='epub-ppub' --><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>2014 Cancer Biology &#x00026; Medicine</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cancer Biology &#x00026; Medicine</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Objective</title><p>To explore the effects of postmastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT) on the locoregional failure-free survival (LRFFS) and overall survival (OS) of breast cancer patients under different tumor stages and with one to three positive axillary lymph nodes (ALNs).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We conducted a retrospective review of 527 patients with one to three positive lymph nodes who underwent modified radical or partial mastectomy and axillary dissection from January 2000 to December 2002. The patients were divided into the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> groups. The effects of PMRT on the LRFFS and OS of these two patient groups were analyzed using SPSS 19.0, Pearson&#x02019;s &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test, Kaplan-Meier method, and Cox proportional hazard model.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>For T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients, no statistical significance was observed in the effects of PMRT on LRFFS [hazard ratio (HR)=0.726; 95% confidence interval (CI): 0.233-2.265; <italic>P</italic>=0.582] and OS (HR=0.914; 95% CI: 0.478-1.745; <italic>P</italic>=0.784) of the general patients. Extracapsular extension (ECE) and high histological grade were the risk factors for LRFFS and OS with statistical significance in multivariate analysis. Stratification analysis showed that PMRT statistically improved the clinical outcomes in high-risk patients [ECE (+), LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>=0.026, OS: <italic>P</italic>=0.007; histological grade III, LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, OS: <italic>P</italic>=0.007] but not in low-risk patients [ECE (&#x02013;), LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>=0.987, OS: <italic>P</italic>=0.502; histological grade I-II, LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>=0.816, OS: <italic>P</italic>=0.296]. For T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients, PMRT effectively improved the local control (HR=0.089; 95% CI: 0.210-0.378; <italic>P</italic>=0.001) of the general patients, whereas no statistical effect was observed on OS (HR=1.251; 95% CI: 0.597-2.622; <italic>P</italic>=0.552). Absence of estrogen receptors and progesterone receptors (ER/PR) (&#x02013;) was an independent risk factor. Further stratification analysis indicated a statistical difference in LRFFS and OS between the high-risk patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;) receiving PMRT and not receiving PMRT [ER/PR (&#x02013;), LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>=0.046, OS: <italic>P</italic>=0.039]. However, PMRT had a beneficial effect on the reduction of locoregional recurrence (LRR) but not in total mortality [ER/PR (+), LRFFS: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, OS: <italic>P</italic>= 0.695] in T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (+) who received endocrine therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>PMRT could reduce ECE (+), histological grade III-related LRR, and total mortality of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;) could benefit from PMRT by improving LRFFS and OS. However, PMRT could only reduce LRR but failed to improve OS for T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (+) who received endocrine therapy.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS </title><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd><kwd>positive lymph nodes</kwd><kwd>postmastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT)</kwd><kwd>locoregional failure-free survival (LRFFS)</kwd><kwd>overall survival (OS)</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Postmastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT), as a treatment modality for postoperative patients with breast cancer, is primarily used to reduce locoregional recurrence (LRR) and improve survival, although modestly, in patients with high-risk factors<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>.</p><p>According to the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) guidelines<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>, PMRT should be considered for patients with T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> breast cancer with more than three positive lymph nodes or with T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> breast cancer with one to three positive lymph nodes. Given that several clinical and pathological factors may affect prognosis of patients with intermediate-risk breast cancer, using T/N classification only is an imprecise method in determining whether a patient should be considered for PMRT<xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. Several researchers have attempted to identify the risk factors for LRR and mortality after mastectomy to select patients who are most likely to benefit from PMRT<xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>. However, these patient subgroups have not been clearly defined, and the contribution of PMRT to locoregional control and survival remains unclear.</p><p>The function of PMRT is not clearly defined in breast cancer patients with one to three positive lymph nodes. In this retrospective study, we identified prognostic factors for LRR and mortality of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> breast cancer patients. In addition, we compared the locoregional failure-free survival (LRFFS) and overall survival (OS) of the high-risk patients with and without PMRT to define a subgroup of patients who might benefit from PMRT.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Clinical data</title><p>From January 2000 to December 2002, breast cancer patients with pathologically proven one to three positive axillary lymph nodes (ALNs) were treated with modified radical mastectomy plus axillary dissection at the Tianjin Cancer Hospital. Of the 527 patients with one to three positive lymph nodes, the median age was 48.73 years (range, 26 to 79 years). The median number of involved ALNs was 1.93 (range, 1 to 3). A total of 432 patients with T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> disease and 95 patients with T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> disease were included in the study, 75.7% (327/432) and 70.5% (67/95) of whom received PMRT, respectively. The study was approved by the institutional ethics committee.</p></sec><sec><title>Systemic treatment</title><p>All patients received TEC-based (docetaxel, epirubicin, cyclophosphamide) or docetaxel-containing regimens as adjuvant chemotherapy. Adjuvant endocrine therapy was performed for 5 years in all patients who had positive hormone receptors. Among 527 patients, 74.8% (394/527) underwent PMRT, which was delivered to the breast, chest wall, internal mammary, supraclavicular, and axillary fossa drawing region by medial and lateral-tangential fields with external-beam irradiation (4 or 6 MV photons/60 Co). The standard dose to the entire chest wall was 50 Gy (range, 46 to 54 Gy), 1.8 to 2 Gy/d, and five times weekly. The supraclavicular region and the full axilla were treated with a dose of 50 Gy using an anterior field. An additional external boost with electrons (2 Gy/10 Gy to 14 Gy) was performed in patients who had locally advanced disease.</p></sec><sec><title>Follow-up</title><p>The median time of follow-up was 127.82 months (range, 15 to 155 months). All intervals were calculated from the date of completion of surgery, and the endpoint was defined as the last follow-up or death. Evaluation of tumor control was performed for patients in 4-month intervals for the first 2 years and in 6-month intervals for the next 3 years. Subsequently, these patients were observed on a yearly basis. Clinical examinations, which included blood sampling, routine chest radiograph, mammograph, and ultrasound, were performed as evaluation during the follow-up. Further evaluations were conducted only if the clinical findings indicated a disease progression. Survival period was calculated from the date of surgical resection to the date of last follow-up. The endpoints of interest included LRFFS and OS.</p></sec><sec><title>Recurrence</title><p>LRR was identified as local recurrence (chest wall alone) or regional recurrence (axillary, supraclavicular, and internal mammary lymph nodes alone). Any recurrence outside these areas was defined as distant metastasis (DM).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All analyses were performed using SPSS 19.0. Pearson&#x02019;s &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-test was used to compare the proportions of categorical covariates among the groups of patients with different T stages. OS and LRFFS were analyzed with Kaplan-Meier method. Univariate and multivariate hazard ratios (HR) and their 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were calculated using Cox&#x02019;s proportional hazard model. A probability level of &#x02264;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Basic information</title><p>With a median follow up of 127.82 months (range, 15 to 155 months), 3.7% (16/432) and 14.7% (14/95) of patients developed LRR in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patient groups, respectively. OS was 93.5% (404/432) and 45.3% (43/95) in the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> groups, respectively. The Kaplan-Meier curves of LRFFS and OS in different T stages confirmed the statistically significant difference in LRFFS and OS between the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1"><bold>Figure 1A,B</bold></xref>). The distribution patterns of clinico-pathologic characteristics for the PMRT and non-PMRT groups are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1"><bold>Table 1</bold></xref>. A statistically significant difference was observed between the two groups regarding the status of extracapsular extension (ECE) and the number of involved ALNs (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p><fig id="f1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(A) Kaplan-Meier curve of LRFFS in different T stages; (B) Kaplan-Meier curve of OS in different T stages; (C) Kaplan-Meier curve of OS in patients with different ECE in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+E&#x02013; <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;E&#x02013;: <italic>P</italic>=0.502; PMRT+E+ <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;E+: <italic>P</italic>=0.007 (PMRT&#x02013;, non-PMRT; PMRT+, PMRT; E&#x02013;, ECE&#x02013;; E+, ECE+); (D) Kaplan-Meier curve of LRFFS in patients with different ECE in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+E&#x02013; <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;E&#x02013;: <italic>P</italic>=0.987; PMRT+E+ <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT-E+: <italic>P</italic>=0.026; (E) Kaplan-Meier curve of OS in patients with different histological grades in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+ GI-II <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013; GI-II: <italic>P</italic>=0.296; PMRT&#x02013; GIII <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT+ GIII: <italic>P</italic>=0.007. (GI-II, grade I-II; GIII, grade III); (F) Kaplan-Meier curve of LRFFS in patients with different histological grades in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+ GI-II <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013; GI-II: <italic>P</italic>=0.816; PMRT&#x02013; GIII <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT+ GIII: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001; (G) Kaplan-Meier curve of OS in patients with different hormone receptor status in T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+ER/PR&#x02013; <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;ER/PR&#x02013;: <italic>P</italic>=0.039; PMRT+ER/PR+ <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;ER/PR+: <italic>P</italic>=0.695; (H) Kaplan-Meier curve of LRFFS in patients with different hormone receptor status in T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. PMRT+ER/PR&#x02013; <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;ER/PR&#x02013;: <italic>P</italic>=0.046; PMRT+ER/PR+ <italic>vs</italic>. PMRT&#x02013;ER/PR+: <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cbm-11-02-123-f1"/></fig><table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Clinicopathologic features of patients in the study</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="39.88%" span="1"/><col width="22.37%" span="1"/><col width="20.89%" span="1"/><col width="16.86%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1">Characteristics</th><th colspan="2" valign="top" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">No. of patients<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;<italic>P</italic></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">PMRT</th><th valign="top" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No-PMRT</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, yrs</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.841</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x02264;50</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x0003e;50</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ER/PR</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.052</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Negative</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Postmenopausal</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.133</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;No</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Yes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECE</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Negative</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">324</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Positive</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological grade</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;I-II</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">364</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">118</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;III</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T stage</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.299</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">327</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub></td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Endocrine therapy</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="3" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">0.131</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;No</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Yes</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">337</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ALN</td><td colspan="2" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td rowspan="4" valign="top" align="char" char="." colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;1</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;2</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;3</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td valign="top" align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>ER, estrogen receptor; PR, progesterone; ER/PR, estrogen receptor and progesterone receptor; ECE, extracapsular extension; ALN, axillary lymph nodes; PMRT, postmastectomy radiotherapy.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Univariate and multivariate analyses</title><p>The univariate and multivariate factors for LRR in the different T stages were analyzed using Cox&#x02019;s proportional hazard model. The risk and protective factors in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> patients were different. ECE (HR=2.867; 95% CI: 1.035-7.939; <italic>P</italic>=0.043) and histological grade III (HR=9.219; 95% CI: 2.956-28.747; <italic>P</italic>=0.000) were the risk factors in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> patients. For the T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> patients, the risk factor was estrogen receptor and progesterone receptor (ER/PR) (&#x02013;) tumors, whereas the protective factors were ER/PR (+) tumors (HR=0.098; 95% CI: 0.025-0.389; <italic>P</italic>=0.001) and PMRT (HR=0.089; 95% CI: 0.210-0.378; <italic>P</italic>=0.001) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2"><bold>Tables 2</bold></xref><bold>,</bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="t3"><bold>3</bold></xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Multivariate analysis with Cox proportional hazards model for OS and LRFFS of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="21.94%" span="1"/><col width="11.61%" span="1"/><col width="14.79%" span="1"/><col width="10.68%" span="1"/><col width="0.97%" span="1"/><col width="12.12%" span="1"/><col width="16.29%" span="1"/><col width="11.6%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">OS<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">LRFFS<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">HR</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">HR</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological grade</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.365</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.332-8.602</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.219</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.956-28.747</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ER/PR</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.716</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.679-4.333</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.375</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.390-4.849</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMRT</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.914</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478-1.745</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.784</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.726</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233-2.265</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.582</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECE</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.086</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.012-1.164</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.867</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.035-7.939</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OS, overall survival; LRFFS, locoregional failure-free survival; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; ER/PR, estrogen receptor and progesterone receptor; PMRT, postmastectomy radiotherapy; ECE, extracapsular extension.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="t3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Multivariate analysis with cox proportional hazards model for OS and LRFFS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col width="22.04%" span="1"/><col width="11.7%" span="1"/><col width="14.6%" span="1"/><col width="9.27%" span="1"/><col width="2.1%" span="1"/><col width="11.93%" span="1"/><col width="16.57%" span="1"/><col width="11.79%" span="1"/><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1">Variable</th><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">OS<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" valign="middle" align="left" scope="col" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" colspan="1"/><th valign="middle" colspan="3" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-bottom: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">LRFFS<hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">HR</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th><th valign="middle" colspan="1" align="center" scope="colgroup" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1">HR</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th valign="middle" align="center" scope="col" style="border-top: solid 0.75pt" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histological grade</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.845</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.957-3.556</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.337</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063-1.795</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.202</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ER/PR</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.307</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.154-0.610</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.098</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.025-0.389</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMRT</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.251</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.597-2.622</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.552</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210-0.378</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="middle" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECE</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.533-1.801</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.947</td><td valign="middle" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.702</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.633-11.529</td><td valign="middle" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OS, overall survival; LRFFS, locoregional failure-free survival; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; PMRT, postmastectomy radiotherapy; ECE, extracapsular extension.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The factors affecting OS varied between the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. ECE (HR=1.086; 95% CI: 1.012-1.164; <italic>P</italic>=0.022) and histological grade III (HR=3.365; 95% CI: 1.332-8.602; <italic>P</italic>=0.010) were the risk factors in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> patients. However, the risk factor in T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> patients was ER/PR (&#x02013;) tumors. ER/PR (+) tumors (HR=0.307; 95% CI: 0.154-0.610; <italic>P</italic>=0.001) had a significant effect in improving OS (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t2"><bold>Tables 2</bold></xref><bold> and </bold><xref ref-type="table" rid="t3"><bold>3</bold></xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Effects of PMRT on LRFFS and OS of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients based on ECE status and histological grade</title><p>The OS and LRFFS were analyzed by Kaplan-Meier, and survival curves were plotted for the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patient subgroups: ECE (&#x02013;) /PMRT (&#x02013;), ECE (&#x02013;) /PMRT (+), ECE (+) /PMRT (&#x02013;), and ECE (+) /PMRT (+). The log-rank test results showed that PMRT had statistically positive effects on improving LRFFS (<italic>P</italic>=0.026) and OS (<italic>P</italic>=0.007) of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ECE (+) but not ECE (&#x02013;). We also performed a subgroup analysis according to the histological grade, and the results showed that PMRT could improve the LRFFS (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) and OS (<italic>P</italic>=0.007) of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with histological grade III (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1"><bold>Figure 1C-F</bold></xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Effects of PMRT on LRFFS and OS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients based on hormone receptor status</title><p>With regard to LRFFS and OS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients, ER/PR (+) was a statistically significant factor on multivariate analysis. PMRT was beneficial on LRFFS of all patients regardless of the hormone receptor status. The effects of PMRT on LRFFS and OS of the patients with different ER/PR statuses were examined. All T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients were first stratified into subgroups of ER/PR (+) and ER/PR (&#x02013;). We observed that PMRT was useful for the reduction of LRR (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001) of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (+) but failed to improve OS (<italic>P</italic>=0.695). However, patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;) could benefit from PMRT on improving LRFFS (<italic>P</italic>=0.046) and OS (<italic>P</italic>=0.039) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1"><bold>Figure 1G,H</bold></xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The significance of PMRT to reduce LRR and total mortality in the subgroup of patients with one to three positive lymph nodes remains unclear<xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>-</sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref>. Currently, the indication of PMRT is mainly determined by the number of positive lymph nodes and the T stage. However, some studies<xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> have reported the comparatively more effective prognostic predictors other than T and N stage that guide the PMRT treatment. These predictors include age, hormone receptor status, ECE status, histological grade, lymphovascular invasion, menstrual status, and lymph node ratio.</p><p>Huang <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> highly recommends the PMRT to breast cancer patients with T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> and one to three positive lymph nodes for reducing LRR and improving disease-free survival. Tendulkar <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> suggested that PMRT provides excellent locoregional control for patients with one to three positive lymph nodes, regardless of PMRT patients in more advanced stage (about 40% had stage T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> disease) and a greater number of risk factors, such as pathological grade III and ECE. However, Geng <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> suggested that PMRT does not significantly improve the LRFFS for patients with one to three positive axillary nodes, regardless of the ECE status. Kong <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> found that PMRT does not improve LRR, DM-free survival, or OS in T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> breast cancer patients. However, PMRT might be beneficial in a subgroup of patients with histological grade III disease, ECE, or triple-negative subtype. PMRT is important in identifying the risk factors associated with increased risk of LRR and total mortality in patients with one to three positive axillary lymph nodes to establish its indications.</p><p>According to the American Society of Clinical Oncology<xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>, insufficient evidence exists to formulate recommendations or suggestions for the routine use of PMRT in patients with T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> breast cancer and one to three positive lymph nodes. However, PMRT has been considered for T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients based on the NCCN guidelines<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Our retrospective study provided some new information with regard to patients with one to three positive axillary lymph nodes, who may benefit from PMRT.</p><p>Based on our study, different effects of PMRT on improving LRFFS or OS were found between the T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. Previous studies have reported<xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> that the LRFFS and OS of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> breast cancer patients treated with radical mastectomy are dependent on several prognostic factors other than T and N stage. Our analysis revealed that ECE (+) and histological grade III were the high-risk factors for LRR and mortality of T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients. The stratification analysis results revealed that PMRT had a positive effect in reducing ECE (+) or histological grade III-related LRR and mortality. However, the remaining patients with ECE (&#x02013;) or histological grade I-II experienced extremely low LRR and mortality rates after mastectomy treatment, and the benefit from PMRT was minimal. Although PMRT had no protective function in improving LRFFS and OS of the general T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients, high-risk patients with ECE (+) and histological grade III could benefit from PMRT.</p><p>Contrary to T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients, the general T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients could benefit from PMRT in terms of LRFFS but not in OS. Stage T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> is a high-risk factor in breast cancer patients, who are more likely to develop DM than patients with early T stage disease. Breast cancer tends to be a systemic disease with potential sub-clinical DM in Fisher&#x02019;s theory<xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>. Our analysis revealed that PMRT could improve the LRR control in T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> patients, but no statistically significant effect on OS was observed among these patients. In addition, patients with ER/PR (+) benefited from endocrine therapy. All patients with ER/PR (+) who were included in our study received endocrine therapy. Endocrine therapy was a protective factor to improve LRFFS and OS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients according to the multivariate analysis results. Thus, the risks of LRR and mortality were positively associated with ER/PR (&#x02013;). NCCN guidelines<xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> suggested that T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> patients should receive PMRT. Rangan <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> reported that LRR rate of patients with one to three positive lymph nodes who received chemotherapy and endocrine therapy is approximately 10% under the condition of non-PMRT. To further determine whether PMRT is essential for patients receiving endocrine therapy and whether ER/PR (&#x02013;) patients could benefit from it, we analyzed its effects on LRFFS and OS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;) and who received endocrine therapy, respectively. The results of stratification analysis indicated that PMRT caused a statistically significant improvement in LRFFS and OS of T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;). For T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients who received endocrine therapy, PMRT could improve local control but no statistical change in OS was observed compared with non-PMRT.</p><p>PMRT alleviates local symptoms but often results in significant pathological damage to the heart, lungs, and skin. A meta-analysis by Taghian <italic>et al</italic>.<xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> revealed a significant increase in non-breast cancer mortality in irradiated women. The mortality is mainly because of heart disease and lung cancer. Given the complications of PMRT, its necessity for T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients receiving endocrine therapy should be reconsidered because no statistical effect on OS was observed in this study despite the improvement in local control.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>According to our results, PMRT is highly recommended to improve LRFFS and OS for T<sub>1</sub>-T<sub>2</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ECE (+) or pathological grade III as well as for T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (&#x02013;). However, PMRT has to be reconsidered for T<sub>3</sub>-T<sub>4</sub> N<sub>1</sub> patients with ER/PR (+) who benefited from endocrine therapy on improving LRFFS and OS. Other prognostic factors should be considered, and the decision has to be made individually on the basis of endocrine therapy and request of the patient because PMRT could control LRR but not total mortality.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Tianjin Natural Science Foundation of China (Grant No.11JCZDJC28000).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p>No potential conflicts of interest are disclosed.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="r1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bach</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postoperative radiotherapy in high-risk premenopausal women with breast cancer who receive adjuvant chemotherapy. Danish Breast Cancer Cooperative Group 82b Trial.</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1997</year>;<volume>337</volume>:<fpage>949</fpage>-<lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9395428</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postoperative radiotherapy in high-risk postmenopausal breast-cancer patients given adjuvant tamoxifen: Danish Breast Cancer Cooperative Group DBCG 82c randomised trial.</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1999</year>;<volume>353</volume>:<fpage>1641</fpage>-<lpage>1648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10335782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragaz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spinelli</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Locoregional radiation therapy in patients with high-risk breast cancer receiving adjuvant chemotherapy: 20-year results of the British Columbia randomized trial.</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>97</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>-<lpage>126</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whelan</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Julian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Does locoregional radiation therapy improve survival in breast cancer? A meta-analysis.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1220</fpage>-<lpage>1229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10715291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">National Comprehensive Cancer Network. NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology (NCCN Guidelines&#x02122;) (National Comprehensive Cancer Network ed., vol. 2012, v1. 2012 edition. Fort Washington, PA: National Comprehensive Cancer Network; 2012. Breast cancer. Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/breast.pdf">http://www.nccn.org/professionals/physician_gls/pdf/breast.pdf</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Postmastectomy radiation therapy: who needs it?</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>4237</fpage>-<lpage>4239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452185</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Panades</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Speers</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthelet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Selecting breast cancer patients with T1-T2 tumors and one to three positive axillary nodes at high postmastectomy locoregional recurrence risk for adjuvant radiotherapy.</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>1337</fpage>-<lpage>1347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Is the benefit of postmastectomy irradiation limited to patients with four or more positive nodes, as recommended in international consensus reports? A subgroup analysis of the DBCG 82 b&#x00026;c randomized trials.</article-title><source>Radiother Oncol</source><year>2007</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<fpage>247</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17306393</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsou</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic index score and clinical prediction model of local regional recurrence after mastectomy in breast cancer patients.</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>1401</fpage>-<lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16472935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrelli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roviello</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Stefano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guarnieri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallucca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of extracapsular extension of axillary lymph node metastases in T1 to T3 breast cancer.</article-title><source>Ann Surg Oncol</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15827817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamamoto</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohsumi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aogi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Are there high-risk subgroups for isolated locoregional failure in patients who had T1/2 breast cancer with one to three positive lymph nodes and received mastectomy without radiotherapy?</article-title><source>Breast Cancer</source><year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>177</fpage>-<lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22569681</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lian</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of clinical outcome of breast cancer patients with T1-2 tumor and one to three positive nodes with or without postmastectomy radiation therapy.</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>711</fpage>-<lpage>720</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22645150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The clinical value of adjuvant radiotherapy in patients with early stage breast cancer with 1 to 3 positive lymph nodes after mastectomy.</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>668</fpage>-<lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20591219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Horng</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Radiotherapy can decrease locoregional recurrence and increase survival in mastectomy patients with T1 to T2 breast cancer and one to three positive nodes with negative estrogen receptor and positive lymphovascular invasion status.</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>77</volume>:<fpage>516</fpage>-<lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19577858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Berthelet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kader</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivotto</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The prognostic significance of the percentage of positive/dissected axillary lymph nodes in breast cancer recurrence and survival in patients with one to three positive axillary lymph nodes.</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2005</year>;<volume>103</volume>:<fpage>2006</fpage>-<lpage>2014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15812825</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tendulkar</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of postmastectomy radiation on locoregional recurrence in breast cancer patients with 1-3 positive lymph nodes treated with modern systemic therapy.</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2012</year>;<volume>83</volume>:<fpage>e577</fpage>-<lpage>581</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22560546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of ECE on the benefits of PMRT for breast cancer patients with positive axillary nodes.</article-title><source>J Radiat Res</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>712</fpage>-<lpage>718</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23392824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Which patients might benefit from postmastectomy radiotherapy in breast cancer patients with T1-2 tumor and 1-3 axillary lymph nodes metastasis?</article-title><source>Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2013</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>-<lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23864843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taghian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamounas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Deutsch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patterns of locoregional failure in patients with operable breast cancer treated by mastectomy and adjuvant chemotherapy with or without tamoxifen and without radiotherapy: results from five National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project randomized clinical trials.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2004</year>;<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>4247</fpage>-<lpage>4254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15452182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Overgaard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Loco-regional recurrence after mastectomy in high-risk breast cancer--risk and prognosis. An analysis of patients from the DBCG 82 b&#x00026;c randomization trials.</article-title><source>Radiother Oncol</source><year>2006</year>;<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>147</fpage>-<lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16647152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Recht</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Edge</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Solin</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Estabrook</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Postmastectomy radiotherapy: clinical practice guidelines of the American Society of Clinical Oncology.</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2001</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>1539</fpage>-<lpage>1569</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11230499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="r22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rangan</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahern</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyages</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Local recurrence after mastectomy and adjuvant CMF: implications for adjuvant radiation therapy.</article-title><source>Aust N Z J Surg</source><year>2000</year>;<volume>70</volume>:<fpage>649</fpage>-<lpage>655</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10976894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>