<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1805070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.i2.pg32</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069096</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diagnostic performance of spectroscopic and perfusion MRI for distinction of brain tumors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>M A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zoubaa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">&#x000a7; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlieter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">&#x000b6; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000fc;ttler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">&#x02016; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huttner</surname><given-names>H B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">&#x02016; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Geletneky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">** </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ittrich</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">&#x02021; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lichy</surname><given-names>M P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">&#x02020; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Debus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giesel</surname><given-names>F L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">&#x000b6; </xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Essig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">* Department of Radiology, German Cancer Research Center, Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff2">&#x02020; Department of Physics in Radiology, German Cancer Research Center, Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff3">&#x02021; Department of Central Unit Biostatistics, German Cancer Research Center, Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff4">&#x000a7; Department of Pathology, University of Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff5">&#x000b6; Department of Neuroradiology, University of Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff6">&#x02016; Department of Neurology, University of Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><aff id="aff7">** Department of Neurosurgery, University of Heidelberg, Germany.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding address: Dr Marc-Andr&#x000e9; Weber, Department of Radiology, German Cancer Research Center, Im Neuenheimer Feld 280, D-69120 Heidelberg, Germany. Email: <email>m.a.weber@dkfz.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S32</fpage><lpage>S41</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Objective:</bold> To assess the value of spectroscopic and perfusion MRI for glioma grading and for distinguishing glioblastomas from metastases and from CNS lymphomas.
<bold>
Methods:</bold> The authors examined 79 consecutive patients with first detection of a brain neoplasm on nonenhanced CT scans and no therapy prior to evaluation. Spectroscopic MRI; arterial spin-labeling MRI for measuring cerebral blood flow (CBF); first-pass dynamic, susceptibility-weighted, contrast-enhanced MRI for measuring cerebral blood volume; and T1-weighted dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI were performed. Receiver operating characteristic analysis was performed, and optimum thresholds for tumor classification and glioma grading were determined.
<bold>
Results:</bold> Perfusion MRI had a higher diagnostic performance than spectroscopic MRI. Because of a significantly higher tumor blood flow in glioblastomas compared with CNS lymphomas, a threshold value of 1.2 for CBF provided sensitivity of 97&#x00025;, specificity of 80&#x00025;, positive predictive value (PPV) of 94&#x00025;, and negative predictive value (NPV) of 89&#x00025;. Because CBF was significantly higher in peritumoral nonenhancing T2-hyperintense regions of glioblastomas compared with metastases, a threshold value of 0.5 for CBF provided sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV of 100&#x00025;, 71&#x00025;, 94&#x00025;, and 100&#x00025;. Glioblastomas had the highest tumor blood flow values among all other glioma grades. For discrimination of glioblastomas from grade 3 gliomas, sensitivity was 97&#x00025;, specificity was 50&#x00025;, PPV was 84&#x00025;, and NPV was 86&#x00025; (CBF threshold value of 1.4), and for discrimination of glioblastomas from grade 2 gliomas, sensitivity was 94&#x00025;, specificity was 78&#x00025;, PPV was 94&#x00025;, and NPV was 78&#x00025; (CBF threshold value of 1.6).
<bold>
Conclusion:</bold> Perfusion MRI is predictive in distinguishing glioblastomas from metastases, CNS lymphomas and other gliomas vs. MRI and magnetic resonance spectroscopy. 
</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Brain tumor</kwd><kwd>MRI</kwd><kwd>grading gliomas</kwd><kwd>glioblastoma</kwd><kwd>metastasis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>MRI is the modality of choice for depiction and delineation of intracerebral neoplasms. However, tumor specification is limited and sometimes conventional MRI cannot discriminate glioblastomas from solitary metastases, CNS lymphomas, or other glioma grades. Because their management and prognosis are different, early differentiation is important. For this, functional MRI techniques are beneficial.</p><p>First-pass dynamic susceptibility-weighted, contrast-enhanced (DSC) magnetic resonance (MR) echo-planar imaging (EPI) is well established for determining relative regional cerebral blood volume (rrCBV) in brain tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. Perfusion can also be measured by arterial spin-labeling techniques (ASL) that measure relative regional cerebral blood flow (rrCBF) without using extrinsic contrast agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>]. Dynamic contrast-enhanced (DCE) MRI measures a composite of tumor perfusion, vessel permeability, and extravascular-extracellular space volume. It bases on the acquisition of serial T1-weighted MR images before, during, and after administration of an IV contrast agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. Proton MR spectroscopic imaging (<sup>1</sup>H MRSI) displays the
distribution of metabolites within tumor tissue as a molecular image. It shows benefits for the differentiation of neoplastic and non-neoplastic lesions and for glioma grading [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>].</p><p>Although each functional MRI technique is beneficial for tumor grading, differentiation, and treatment monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>], a comprehensive analysis of all these techniques with respect to intermodality correlation and predictive power in discriminating glioblastomas from other entities is lacking.</p><p>Thus, we present a comprehensive investigation of the functional MRI methods DSC and ASL perfusion MRI, DCE MRI, and MRSI. We assess correlations between histology and functional MRI and evaluate their value to differentiate between a glioblastoma, solitary metastasis, or CNS lymphoma and to correctly grade gliomas.
</p><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Patient enrollment</title><p>Seventy-nine consecutive patients (36 women, 43 men; mean age 57&#x000b1;14 years [SD]) with suspected intra-axial brain tumor were included prospectively in the study over 2
years. Suspicion was raised based on unenhanced CT scans that were routinely performed when the patients presented with a new neurologic deficit at the casualty ward of our university&#x02019;s neurology department. Exclusion criteria were any antiedematous or immunosuppressive treatment, surgery, radiation therapy, or chemotherapy of a brain tumor before inclusion in the study. For all patients, it was the first diagnosis of a brain lesion. The patients were then referred for MRI.</p><p>The study was approved by the institutional review board and conducted according to the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from all patients after the nature of the examination had been fully explained.
</p></sec><sec><title>MRI protocol and data post-processing</title><p>Two MRI examinations were performed within 1 week prior to surgery prospectively in two imaging centers with 1.5-T MR units using standard circular-polarized head coils within a minimum time interval of 1 day and a maximum interval of 3 days. Two MRI examinations were necessary because of the long imaging time needed for the functional MRI methods under test and the fact that both DCE and DSC MRI require specific contrast medium administration. In all patients, there were no substantial changes in tumor morphology (e.g. caused by intratumoral bleeding) between both MR examinations that would have meant exclusion of the study. With the first MR unit (Edge whole body system, Marconi Medical Systems, Cleveland, OH), standard anatomic MRI and DSC MRI were performed. With the second MR unit (Magnetom Vision Plus, Siemens, Erlangen, Germany), MRSI, ASL, and DCE MRI were performed. The main features of the functional MRI techniques used in our study are given in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>. 
<table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Functional MRI techniques used for brain tumor imaging 
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRI technique</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abbreviation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters measured</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurement time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynamic susceptibility-weighted</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">contrast-enhanced MRI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DSC MRI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative regional cerebral blood volume</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arterial spin-labeling MRI (Q2TIPS sequence)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASL MRI (Q2TIPS)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative regional cerebral blood flow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 min, 42 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arterial spin-labeling MRI (ITS-FAIR sequence)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASL MRI (ITS-FAIR)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative regional cerebral blood flow,</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 min, 3 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">arterial transit time</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnetic resonance spectroscopic imaging</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MRSI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Choline, creatine, <italic>N</italic>-acetyl aspartate,</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 min, 17 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lactate, lipids</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynamic contrast-enhanced MRI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DCE MRI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude, exchange rate constant <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 min, 56 s</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Q2TIPS sequence = second version of quantitative imaging of perfusion by using a single subtraction with addition of thin-section periodic saturation after inversion
and a time delay sequence; ITS-FAIR sequence = inflow turbo-sampling, echo-planar, flow-sensitive, alternating inversion recovery
sequence.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><sec><title>DSC MRI</title><p>Standard MRI and DSC MRI were performed during the same session. Standard T2- (repetition time [TR]/echo time [TE], 2600 ms /100 ms) and T1-weighted (550 ms
/25 ms) images were obtained before DSC MRI, and then contrast-enhanced T1-weighted images were acquired. DSC MRI was performed using a gradient-echo EPI sequence (1300 ms
/26 ms). With this sequence, 40 data sets were acquired with a time resolution of 1.3 s per data set. The sequence and the contrast agent injection were started simultaneously. As contrast agent, we used 0.1 mmol
/kg body weight of gadolinium-diethylene-triamine-pentaacetic acid (Gd-DTPA) (Magnevist, Schering, Berlin, Germany), which was injected by a pneumatically driven injection pump at an injection rate of 5 mL
/s. DSC MRI was analyzed on a workstation (Vistar, Marconi Medical Systems, Cleveland, OH). From the DSC MRI data, we calculated rrCBV values by using contralateral white matter as internal
reference [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>].
</p></sec><sec><title>Spectroscopic imaging</title><p>An axial and coronal fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (FLAIR) sequence (9000 ms /105 ms) was used to position the
<sup>1</sup>H two-dimensional MRSI sequence (point-resolved spectroscopy, 1500 ms
/135 ms, voxel size
9&#x000d7;9&#x000d7;15mm<sup>3</sup>). Relative signal intensity ratios of choline-containing compounds (Cho), the creatine-phosphocreatine complex (Cr), and
<italic>N</italic>-acetyl aspartate (NAA) and metabolic images were calculated using the software SiTools (VA Medical Center, San Francisco, CA). MRSI was performed before contrast-enhanced
MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>].
</p></sec><sec><title>ASL MRI</title><p>After MRSI, two pulsed ASL sequences were performed. We used the Q2TIPS sequence (second version of quantitative imaging of perfusion by using a single subtraction with addition of thin-section periodic saturation after inversion and a time delay sequence) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>] that is capable of multislice imaging, such as DSC MRI, but gives no dynamic information about blood inflow. Hence, another ASL sequence was performed after the Q2TIPS sequence. The inflow turbo-sampling, echo-planar FAIR sequence (ITS-FAIR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>] allows for sampling the inflow of labeled blood into the read-out slice with a temporal resolution of 100 ms and thus yields dynamic information about inflow characteristics and enables quantification of the arterial transit time (ATT). The ITS-FAIR sequence parameters were as follows: TE = 17.7 ms,
measurement interval (TR) = 2700 ms,
128&#x000d7;128 matrix, slice thickness 10 mm, 220-mm field of view (FOV), acquisition time of 5 min 3 s for 55 interleaved averages of selective and global inversion series. A time series of 27 CBF-weighted images was acquired with a time delay of 100 ms between two successive images. The first image was acquired at an inflow time of 150 ms. Sequence parameters of Q2TIPS were as follows: TE
= 30.5 ms; measurement interval (TR)
= 2500 ms; TI
= 1200 ms (inversion time); TI2
= 200 ms (time delay between saturation pulse and image acquisition); slice thickness, 8 mm; five slices obtained in one acquisition; acquisition time, 4 min 42 s; matrix,
128&#x000d7;128; FOV, 240 mm; 50
averages.
</p></sec><sec><title>DCE MRI</title><p>After ASL MRI, T1-weighted DCE MRI was performed using the following parameters: TR /TE, 82.6 ms
/3.63 ms; 10 slices; slice thickness, 6 mm; measurement interval, 9.54 s; matrix,
96&#x000d7;256; FOV, 310 mm; 75 measurements; contrast media (0.1 mmol
/kg body weight of Gd-DTPA, Magnevist, Schering, Berlin, Germany); infusion time 30 s starting with the fifth measurement. With a pharmacokinetic two-compartment model, the parameter amplitude, reflecting the degree of MRI signal enhancement, and the exchange rate constant
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> that reflects microvascular permeability were calculated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>]. Typical criteria for malignancy in enhancement kinetics of DCE MRI are rapid and high-amplitude wash-in followed by a relatively rapid wash-out. Thus, malignant lesions tend to have high rate constants or transfer constants of exchange reflected as bright colors on parametric images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. Benign lesions enhance and wash out slowly and show only minimal change
in color on parametric images [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. Regarding enhancement kinetics, amplitude reflects the magnitude of the enhancement curve and a small <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> reflects a
more delayed enhancement than a high <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>].</p><p>After DCE MRI, the imaging protocol on the Magnetom Vision Plus MR unit was finished by an axial T1-weighted spin-echo sequence (600 ms /20
ms).
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Data analysis</title><sec><title>Region-of-interest (ROI) analysis</title><p>Analysis of perfusion and DCE MRI was performed using ROI analysis according to the recommendations of earlier studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>]. ROIs were placed after consensus of two radiologists with 6 and 12 years of experience in the field of CNS MRI. To avoid the risk of calculating maps from normal vessels, the serial T2 <sup>*</sup>-weighted images from the arterial to venous phases as well as the standard MR images were scrutinized before placing the ROIs. The ROIs placed within the tumor or perifocally had a size of at least 20 pixels. The perfusion values were calculated in four regions of interest within both areas of the peritumoral region and within the
enhancing tumor. In order to readily appreciate the inherent heterogeneity of brain tumors, the four ROIs were defined as follows: ROI 1, &#x02018;Tumor&#x02019;, includes all non-necrosis-enhancing tumor tissue, or, if the lesion did not show enhancement, the whole non-necrotic T2-hyperintense, T1-hypointense tumor tissue avoiding perifocal edema. ROI 2, &#x02018;Max Tumor&#x02019;, was placed on the tumor area with maximum CBF or CBV values on parameter images by identifying regions of maximal tumor blood flow or volume from color maps [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. For DCE MRI, the ROI &#x02018;Max Tumor&#x02019; was placed on the tumor area with the highest amplitude and <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> on
parameter images. ROI 3, &#x02018;Perifocal (T2high)&#x02019;, was placed within a 1-cm distance from the outer enhancing tumor margin in T2-hyperintense regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>]. The ROI 4, &#x02018;Perifocal (T2normal)&#x02019;, was placed next to the T2-hyperintense perifocal area in the normal-appearing ipsilateral brain tissue.</p><p>Additionally, in order to average distribution of flow values in the different regions of the brain, both the contralateral gray and white matter, which appeared normal on conventional MRI, were evaluated by six ROIs of 6 pixels in size each [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>].
</p></sec><sec><title>DSC MRI intensity&#x02013;time curve analysis</title><p>Besides calculation of CBV maps, we determined the intensity&#x02013;time curve within the ROI with the highest rrCBV value. By this, differentiation between CNS lymphoma and glioblastoma has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>] because CNS lymphomas showed a significant undershoot below baseline after the first pass of contrast medium resulting from T1 effects, whereas no or only a slight undershoot below baseline was observed in glioblastomas. The two radiologists assessed, in consensus, in a dichotomous fashion whether there was undershoot.
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Perfusion analysis using ASL MRI</title><p>For each ASL measurement, rrCBF ratios of gray to white matter (GM/WM) and ROIs 1 to 4/GM were calculated as major parameters of interest because of underestimation of white matter perfusion using ASL and other methodological considerations that are in favor of GM as internal reference as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>]. Additionally, ATT was determined in all ROIs.
</p><sec><title>Analysis of spectroscopic imaging data</title><p>At a TE of 135 ms, signal intensities of Cho (3.2 ppm), Cr (3.0 ppm), and NAA (2.0 ppm) were calculated by fit and integration of the resonances in postprocessed Fourier spectra. In addition, all <sup>1</sup>H spectra were inspected for the presence of resonances of
lactate (inverted lactate doublet at 1.32 ppm) and lipid resonances (CH <sub>3</sub>: 0.9 ppm, &#x02013;CH
<sub>2</sub>&#x02013;: 1.3 ppm) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>]. Two readers with 6 years of experience in the field of MR spectroscopy assessed, in consensus, in a dichotomous fashion, whether there were lipids or lactate present. The metabolite ratios Cho/Cr, Cho/NAA, and NAA/Cr [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>] were calculated in voxels corresponding
to the ROIs defined for perfusion and DCE analysis, i.e. &#x02018;Tumor&#x02019;, &#x02018;Max Tumor Perfusion&#x02019;, and &#x02018;Perifocal (T2high)&#x02019; for the different lesions. To ensure quality control and acceptable quality of spectroscopic data, control spectra were obtained from the normal-appearing white matter in the contralateral hemisphere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. Additionally, the maximum metabolite tumor ratios on the Cho/NAA and Cho/Cr parameter maps and the minimum metabolite tumor ratios on the NAA/Cr parameter maps were identified. MRI and MRSI analysis was performed without knowledge of the final histologic tumor diagnosis.
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Histology</title><p>Gross total resection was obtained in 56 of all 79 brain tumors. Stereotactic biopsy was performed in the other 23 tumors because in toto resection was either not surgically possible or not indicated. Stereotactic biopsies were guided by imaging findings, including findings of functional MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. This means that in cases of tumors with heterogeneous perfusion, stereotactic biopsies were directed to the area with highest perfusion. Surgical specimens were paraffin embedded after 4&#x00025; formalin fixation (buffered in phosphate-buffered saline), and 1- &#x003bc;m slices were prepared for hematoxylin-eosin (HE) staining. The tumor types were histopathologically classified according to World Health Organization criteria and afterward were divided into the following groups in accordance with previous
studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>]: well-differentiated or low-grade gliomas (grade 2), anaplastic gliomas (grade 3), glioblastoma multiforme (grade 4), CNS lymphomas, metastases, meningiomas, and miscellaneous nonglial circumscribed tumors. Grading of gliomas was based on histologic examination of the most aggressive neoplastic tissue area present in specimens obtained by surgical resection or biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>]. In addition to histologic grading, tumor proliferation activity was assessed morphometrically by a senior neuropathologist after immunohistologic staining with the monoclonal antibody against Ki-67 antigen MIB-1 (Dako, Glostrup, Denmark). To visualize microvessels in the tumor specimens, immunoperoxidase staining for CD31 and factor VIII (Dako) were performed on 1- &#x003bc;m
sections. All sections were then counterstained with hematoxylin. Immunohistochemically stained slides were examined field by field at a magnification of &#x000d7;200 to
identify the area revealing the most intense vascularization, i.e. the &#x02018;hot spot&#x02019;. The magnification was then changed to &#x000d7;400 to determine the number of vessels per
square millimeter within the hot spot. According to established proceedings, any stained endothelial cell or endothelial cell cluster, with or without a lumen that was clearly separated from adjacent microvessels, as well as any glomeruloid vascular proliferation, was considered as a single countable microvessel.
</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The statistical analysis was carried out using the software package R, version 2.1.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>]. Vessel density, proliferation index, rrCBF and rrCBV ratios, parameters arising from DCE MRI and MRSI, and ATT were correlated with each other by calculating Pearson&#x02019;s correlation coefficients and the 95&#x00025; confidence intervals (CIs) (coefficients &#x0003e;0.5 indicate a moderately
positive correlation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>]. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analysis was performed for tumor classification and glioma grading. Nonparametric estimates and 95&#x00025; CIs for the area under the ROC curves (AUCs) were calculated with AUC = 1, indicating perfect discrimination, and AUC
= 0.5, indicating no or random discrimination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>]. Optimal thresholds for tumor classification and glioma grading were determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>]. Sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV), and negative predictive value (NPV) together with the 95&#x00025; CIs for correct tumor classification of glioblastoma vs. lymphoma, metastasis, anaplastic glioma, or low-grade glioma were calculated using these threshold values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>]. The association of the different variables/parameters with glioma grading and tumor classification was evaluated by analysis of variance (ANOVA). If the global F test was significant
<inline-formula><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} 
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath} 
\usepackage{amsfonts,amssymb,amsbsy} 
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal} 
\usepackage{mathrsfs} 
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{} 
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}{&#x0003c;-&#x0003e; linotext}{} 
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} 
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext} 
\begin{document} 
$(p \le 0.05)$ 
\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> , Tukey&#x02019;s all-pairwise comparisons and Dunnett&#x02019;s contrasts (R library multcomp) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>] were used to assess differences between single groups and to compute the corresponding multiplicity-adjusted <italic>p</italic> values for glioma
grading and tumor classification. A <italic>p</italic> value of
&#x0003c;0.05 was considered
significant.
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Results</title><sec><title>Histology</title><p>In our patient population with a total of 79 brain tumors, 75 were localized intra-axially and four were extra-axial. Thirty-five were classified as glioblastomas (diagnosis based on stereotactic biopsy samples [SB], 12), 11 as anaplastic gliomas (SB, 6), nine as grade 2 gliomas (SB, 1), 10 as CNS lymphomas (all high-grade diffuse large cell non-Hodgkin lymphomas of B-cell type and periventricularly localized; SB, 3), seven as adenocarcinoma metastases (SB, 1), four as grade 1 meningiomas (secretory, 2; meningothelial, 1; microcystic, 1), and two as other nonglial tumors. Except for the meningiomas, none of the other tumors had dural localization. The one low-grade glioma included in our study that was diagnosed based on stereotactic biopsy had a homogeneous appearance both on conventional MRI and functional MRI and lacked focal malignant transformation at histology, assuming that the specimen was representative. Vessel density was higher in glioblastomas than grade 3 (<italic>p</italic>=0.004) and
grade 2 gliomas (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001), CNS lymphomas
(<italic>p</italic>=0.01), and metastases
(<italic>p</italic>=0.01), but not higher than in meningiomas
(<italic>p</italic>=0.1). Proliferation index was higher in glioblastomas than grade 2 gliomas
(<italic>p</italic>=0.01), but proliferation activity was not higher compared to grade 3 gliomas
(<italic>p</italic>=0.2) and metastases
(<italic>p</italic>=0.4). CNS lymphomas had a higher proliferation index than glioblastomas (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 (see Table E-1 on the <italic>Neurology</italic> web site at
<uri xlink:type="simple">http://www.neurology.org</uri>).
</p></sec><sec><title>DSC MRI</title><p>In tumor tissue of glioblastomas, rrCBV was higher than grade 3 (<italic>p</italic>=0.04) and grade 2 gliomas
(<italic>p</italic>=0.04), but not in the peritumoral T2-weighted hyperintense area (Table E-1). In all CNS lymphomas, there was a significant undershoot below the baseline after the first pass of contrast medium that was observed in 6&#x00025; of glioblastomas and 50&#x00025; of meningiomas, but was absent in grades 2 and 3 gliomas (Fig. E-1). ROC
analysis yielded AUC values of 0.98 (95&#x00025; CI: 0.98&#x02013;0.98) using the ROI &#x02018;Max Tumor&#x02019; and 0.93 (95&#x00025; CI: 0.93&#x02013;0.94) for the ROI &#x02018;Perifocal (T2high)&#x02019; for discrimination of glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas or metastases.
</p></sec><sec><title>ASL MRI</title><p>Detailed results are given for the Q2TIPS (Table E-2) and for the ITS-FAIR sequence (Tables E-3 and E-4). rrCBF was higher in tumor tissue of glioblastomas than grade 3 (Q2TIPS: <italic>p</italic>=0.01, ITS-FAIR:
<italic>p</italic>=0.03) and grade 2 gliomas (Q2TIPS:
<italic>p</italic>=0.003, ITS-FAIR:
<italic>p</italic>=0.002). rrCBF was higher in tumor tissue of glioblastomas than CNS lymphomas (Q2TIPS:
<italic>p</italic>=0.003, ITS-FAIR:
<italic>p</italic>=0.03,
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>), but not when compared with metastases (Q2TIPS: <italic>p</italic>=0.9, ITS-FAIR:
<italic>p</italic>=0.7) and meningiomas (Q2TIPS:
<italic>p</italic>=0.4, ITS-FAIR:
<italic>p</italic>=0.3). rrCBF was higher in the peritumoral T2-weighted hyperintense region of glioblastomas when compared with meningiomas, metastases, and CNS lymphomas (<italic>p</italic>=0.001 for all entities and both ASL sequences
(<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, Fig. E-2). In all tumor entities, both rrCBF and ATT of the peritumoral T2-weighted normal brain parenchyma and the contralateral normal brain tissue were not significantly different. In tumors with high perfusion, such as glioblastomas and meningiomas, ATT was reduced compared with normal brain parenchyma (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001, Table E-4). ATT was shorter both in tumor
(<italic>p</italic>=0.001) and peritumoral T2-hyperintense regions
(<italic>p</italic>=0.002) of glioblastomas when compared with CNS lymphomas. ROC analysis yielded AUC values for the ROI &#x02018;Perifocal (T2high)&#x02019; of 0.96 (Q2TIPS, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.95&#x02013;0.96), 0.95 (ITS-FAIR, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.95&#x02013;0.95), and 0.85 (ATT, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.84&#x02013;0.86) for discrimination of glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas or metastases.
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A 63-year-old woman with anaplastic glioma of the splenium (a, b) and 66-year-old woman with CNS lymphoma (c, d). (a, c) Contrast-enhanced T1-weighted MRI; (b, d) relative regional CBF perfusion maps obtained by Q2TIPS arterial spin labeling MRI. Tumor blood flow normalized on gray matter is higher in anaplastic glioma than in CNS lymphoma (5.4 vs. 0.6, arrows). 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06003201"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>A 34-year-old man with glioblastoma. Fluid-attenuated inversion recovery MRI (a), contrast-enhanced T1-weighted MRI (b), relative regional cerebral blood flow perfusion map obtained by Q2TIPS arterial spin labeling MRI (c), and proton MR spectroscopic imaging superimposed on a T2-weighted MR image showing choline/creatine metabolite ratios (d). The contrast-enhancing areas of the glioblastoma show elevated tumor blood flow normalized on gray matter (8.2). The peritumoral T2-weighted hyperintense nonenhancing area (arrows) also has a high blood flow normalized on gray matter (1.7) and shows elevated choline/creatine metabolite ratios, suggesting tumor infiltration. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06003202"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Spectroscopic imaging</title><p>Detailed results for MRSI are given (Table E-5). In the different glioma grades, signal intensity ratios of Cho/Cr, NAA/Cr, and Cho/NAA were not significantly altered both for tumor and perifocal regions. Also, signal intensity ratios of Cho/Cr, NAA/Cr, and Cho/ NAA within tumor tissue were not significantly different between glioblastomas, CNS lymphomas, and metastases. However, MRSI demonstrated pathologic spectra with elevated Cho levels and thus increased Cho/NAA ratios in the perifocal T2-weighted hyperintense region in all cases of gliomas and CNS lymphomas but not in metastases, meningiomas, and contralateral normal brain tissue (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>; Fig. E-2). Lactate and lipid signals were found in all tumors except in low-grade gliomas. The maximum metabolite tumor ratios on the Cho/NAA and Cho/Cr parameter maps and the minimum metabolite tumor ratios on the NAA/Cr parameter maps were not colocalized with maximum tumor perfusion. ROC analysis yielded AUC values of 0.81 (Cho/NAA, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.80&#x02013;0.83) and 0.77 (Cho/Cr, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.74&#x02013;0.80) using tumor ROIs for discrimination of glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas. AUC values were 0.96 (Cho/Cr, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.96&#x02013;0.97) and 0.95 (Cho/NAA, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.95&#x02013;0.96) using perifocal T2-hyperintense regions for discrimination of glioblastomas from metastases.
</p></sec><sec><title>DCE MRI</title><p>Meningiomas had the highest amplitude values, higher than glioblastomas (<italic>p</italic>=0.02), whereas
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> values were not different
(<italic>p</italic>=0.9). Amplitude and
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> values were higher in glioblastomas (amplitude:
<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c;0.001,
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub>:
<italic>p</italic>=0.003) and grade 3 gliomas (amplitude:
<italic>p</italic>=0.001,
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub>:
<italic>p</italic>=0.03) than in grade 2 gliomas. Amplitude and
<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub> values were not significantly different between glioblastomas, grade 3 gliomas, CNS lymphomas, and metastases (Table E-6). ROC analysis yielded AUC values of 0.68 (amplitude, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.66&#x02013;0.69) and 0.53 (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>e</italic><italic>p</italic></sub>, 95&#x00025; CI: 0.51&#x02013;0.55) using the ROI &#x02018;Max Tumor&#x02019; for discrimination of glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas or
metastases.
</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation analysis</title><p>Results of correlation analysis are given in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>. Tumor blood volume and vessel density were correlated (<italic>r</italic>=0.51). When comparing other intratumoral functional MRI parameters with proliferation index or vessel density, correlation coefficients did not reach a value of
&#x000b1;0.5 that would indicate a moderate correlation. In tumor tissue, the parameter amplitude was correlated with rrCBF and rrCBV. When tumor blood flow measured by the Q2TIPS ASL sequence was high, the ITS-FAIR ASL sequence also measured a high tumor blood flow
(<italic>r</italic>=0.64). The higher the tumor blood flow was with either ASL sequence, the shorter was the arterial transit time (ITS-FAIR,
<italic>r</italic>=&#x02212;0.56; Q2TIPS,
<italic>r</italic>=&#x02212;0.57). Although no substantial correlation was observed between Cho/NAA and Cho/Cr in tumor tissue, both metabolite ratios were correlated in healthy brain tissue
(<italic>r</italic>=0.64) and perifocal T2-hyperintense regions
(<italic>r</italic>=0.74).
<table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Correlation coefficients for tumor regions of interest 
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBF (Q2TIPS)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBF (ITS-FAIR)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cho/NAA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cho/Cr</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBV</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 <sup>*</sup> (0.15&#x02013;0.69)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212; 0.32&#x02013;0.53)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 <sup>*&#x02020; </sup> (0.45&#x02013;0.89)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212; 0.26&#x02013;0.59)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 <sup>*&#x02020; </sup> (0.26&#x02013;0.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBF (Q2TIPS)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (0.0&#x02013;0.63)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 <sup>*&#x02020; </sup> (0.46&#x02013;0.77)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 <sup>* </sup> (0.13&#x02013;0.67)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212; 0.22&#x02013;0.44)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61 <sup>*&#x02020; </sup> (0.43&#x02013;0.73)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBF (ITS-FAIR)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11 (&#x02212;0.44&#x02013;0.58)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 <sup>&#x02020;</sup> (0.57&#x02013;0.86)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212;0.29&#x02013;0.66)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 <sup>*&#x02020; </sup> (0.49&#x02013;0.91)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 <sup>*&#x02020;</sup> (0.31&#x02013;0.70)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cho/NAA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 <sup>&#x02020;</sup> (0.38&#x02013;0.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 <sup>&#x02020;</sup> (0.26&#x02013;0.79)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (&#x02212; 0.22&#x02013;0.70)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212; 0.13&#x02013;0.54)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19 <sup>* </sup> (&#x02212; 0.17&#x02013;0.51)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cho/Cr</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (&#x02212;0.22&#x02013;0.70)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21 (&#x02212; 0.19&#x02013;0.55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (&#x02212; 0.05&#x02013;0.79)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 (&#x02212; 0.24&#x02013;0.56)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 <sup>*</sup> (&#x02212; 0.13&#x02013;0.55)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amplitude</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 (0.0&#x02013;0.73)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 <sup>&#x02020;</sup> (0.35&#x02013;0.74)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 <sup>&#x02020; </sup> (0.46&#x02013;0.82)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (&#x02212; 0.20&#x02013;0.59)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 (&#x02212;0.09&#x02013;0.67)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><p> <sup>*</sup>Data
represent results for all brain tumors. Other data represent the results only for all glioma patients.
<sup>&#x02020;</sup> Correlation coefficients indicating at least a moderate correlation. 95&#x00025; confidence intervals are presented in
parentheses.
CBV = cerebral blood volume; CBF
= cerebral blood volume; Q2TIPS
= second version of quantitative imaging of perfusion by using a single subtraction with addition of thin-section periodic saturation after inversion and a time delay sequence; ITS-FAIR
= inflow turbo-sampling, echo-planar, flow-sensitive, alternating inversion recovery sequence; Cho
= choline; NAA
=
<italic>N</italic>-acetyl aspartate; Cr
=
creatine.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec><title>Differential diagnosis</title><p>For the discrimination of glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas, both DSC and ASL perfusion MRI had higher predictive values than MRSI (Table E-7). Sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV for DSC and ASL perfusion MRI were comparable when using ROIs within tumor tissue or perifocal T2-hyperintense regions. The Q2TIPS ASL perfusion technique yielded slightly higher predictive values than the ITS-FAIR technique. For Q2TIPS ASL MRI, sensitivity was 97&#x00025;, specificity was 80&#x00025;, PPV was 94&#x00025;, and NPV was 89&#x00025;, with a threshold value of 1.2 for rrCBF within tumor tissue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>); for ITS-FAIR ASL MRI, sensitivity was 89&#x00025;, specificity was 83&#x00025;, PPV was 96&#x00025;, and NPV was 63&#x00025;, with a threshold value of 1.1 for rrCBF; and for DSC MRI, sensitivity was 100&#x00025;, specificity was 50&#x00025;, PPV was 90&#x00025;, and NPV was 100&#x00025;, with a threshold value of 1.4 for rrCBV. 
<table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Sensitivity, specificity, and predictive values for differentiation of glioblastoma from CNS lymphoma or metastasis and for glioma grading using arterial spin-labeling MRI 
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Threshold value</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity (&#x00025;)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PPV (&#x00025;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NPV (&#x00025;)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma vs. CNS lymphoma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrCBF of 1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (87&#x02013;99)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 (66&#x02013;89)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (83&#x02013;98)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (76&#x02013;95)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma vs. metastasis <sup>*</sup></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrCBF of 0.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (91&#x02013;100)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (56&#x02013;83)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (83&#x02013;98)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (91&#x02013;100)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma vs. grade 3 glioma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrCBF of 1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (87&#x02013;99)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (36&#x02013;64)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84 (71&#x02013;92)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (73&#x02013;93)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glioblastoma vs. grade 2 glioma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrCBF of 1.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (82&#x02013;98)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (63&#x02013;88)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94 (82&#x02013;98)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (63&#x02013;88)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade 3 vs. grade 2 glioma</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rrCBF of 1.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (73&#x02013;98)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (17&#x02013;55)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (44&#x02013;81)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (54&#x02013;89)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></table><table-wrap-foot><p> <sup>*</sup>Results for
differentiation between glioblastoma and metastasis are given for peritumoral T2-hyperintense regions.
Results are given for tumor regions of interest using the second version of quantitative imaging of perfusion by using a single subtraction with addition of thin-section periodic saturation after inversion and a time delay arterial spin-labeling sequence. All values presented are significant; 95&#x00025; CIs are presented in parentheses.
PPV = positive predictive value; NPV
= negative predictive value; rrCBF
= relative regional cerebral blood
flow.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>For the discrimination of glioblastomas from metastases by analyzing perifocal T2-hyperintense regions, perfusion MRI had higher predictive values than MRSI (Table E-8). For Q2TIPS ASL MRI, sensitivity was 100&#x00025;, specificity was 71&#x00025;, PPV was 94&#x00025;, and NPV was 100&#x00025;, with a threshold value of 0.5 for rrCBF in perifocal T2-hyperintense regions (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>). Results of the Q2TIPS ASL sequence were slightly better than results of the ITS-FAIR ASL sequence (Table E-8).</p><p>Results for glioma grading are given in
<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table 3</xref>. Among the 11 nonenhancing tumors of our study, two had areas of distinctly higher perfusion than gray matter, underwent gross total resection, and were classified as grade 3 gliomas at histology. The other nine nonenhancing tumors had a homogeneous appearance both on conventional and functional MRI with no evidence of increased tumor vascularity on perfusion maps and were classified as grade 2 gliomas at histology. Threshold values of rrCBF = 1.4 and
1.6 provided minimum errors for determining a glioblastoma from a grade 3 or 2 glioma. DSC and ASL perfusion MRI had comparable predictive values for glioma grading. DSC MRI obtained higher AUC values than both ASL sequences and other MRI techniques, such as MRSI, for the ROI &#x02018;Max Tumor&#x02019; (Table E-9).
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we compared different functional MRI techniques, such as DSC and ASL perfusion MRI, DCE MRI, and MRSI with histologic findings in untreated brain tumors, such as vessel density and proliferation index. We presented characteristic MRI findings of various brain neoplasms in perfusion and spectroscopic imaging and assessed their value for specific tumor diagnosis. Additionally, sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV for discriminating brain tumors based on these MR-derived functional parameters were presented.</p><p>The results of ASL perfusion MRI in tumor and normal brain tissue were in accordance with those of previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>]. Highest signal intensities on ASL images in meningiomas and lowest rrCBF values in CNS lymphomas and low-grade gliomas have been reported before in a small patient population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>]. We observed a significantly higher tumor blood flow in high-grade than in low-grade gliomas in accordance with previous observations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>]. Moreover, we could prove by using the ITS-FAIR ASL approach that a high brain tumor perfusion is related to a short arterial transit time, as previously hypothesized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>]. As reported in healthy brain tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>], rrCBF values obtained by the Q2TIPS and ITS-FAIR ASL sequence were also correlated in tumor tissue.</p><p>In all tumor entities, the parameter amplitude was correlated with rrCBF and rrCBV, reflecting the fact that all these parameters measure tumor vascularity. However, in our study, no strong correlation between rrCBF and rrCBV was observed. The reason for this may be that the two parameters were measured in two separate MRI examinations. For gliomas, MRI- and MRSI-derived parameters were associated with vascularity, proliferation index, and tumor type. Correlation analysis of MR-derived parameters and histologic findings only showed a moderate correlation of rrCBV and vessel density. This may be due to several reasons. rrCBV measurements by DSC MRI are falsified by contrast agent leakage in case of blood-barrier-disruption or absence, such as in extra-axial lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. Blood flow is underestimated by ASL sequences at low flow rates, i.e. hypovascularized lesions or white matter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>]. Attempts to correlate DCE MRI results with vessel density have met with mixed success [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. This is not entirely unexpected because vessel density is an anatomic index, whereas DCE MRI is an <italic>in vivo</italic> assay dependent on vascular characteristics in living tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>]. Moreover, histopathologic assessment is limited by inherent sampling error associated with stereotactic biopsy, particularly regarding microvessel density. Tumors may be very heterogeneous, and in our study, we included both homogeneous- and heterogeneous-appearing tumors. This may explain why strong correlations between Cho and proliferation activity have only been described in homogeneous gliomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>]. The Cho/NAA ratios in tumor and normal brain tissue observed in our study are in good agreement with other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>]. Areas of highest Cho signal and perfusion did not always correspond [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. This may be due to the fact that MRS and perfusion MRI are measuring different pathophysiologic aspects of tumoral activity.</p><p>Although contrast-enhancing lesions in contact with the CSF system and without necrosis are characteristic of CNS lymphoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>], it can be difficult, sometimes even impossible, to distinguish high-grade gliomas from CNS lymphomas on conventional MRI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>]. We examined a homogeneous group of high-grade diffuse large cell non-Hodgkin lymphomas of the B-cell type and demonstrated that perfusion MRI enabled the discrimination of glioblastomas from this CNS lymphoma group with high predictive values. Tumor blood flow and volume were significantly higher in glioblastomas than in CNS lymphomas, as also reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>]. The reason why we were not able to discriminate glioblastomas from CNS lymphomas by the increased lipid signal of CNS lymphomas as reported before with a TE of 20 ms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>] might be our use of a TE of 135 ms because lipid peaks are more readily appreciated at short echo times [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. A TE of 135 ms has the advantage of a better detection of lactate and is thus often used for evaluation of intracranial neoplasms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. Because of extensive necrotic areas observed in some glioblastomas and metastases, the Cho signal may be influenced in such lesions by partial volume effects, although in our study necrotic areas were avoided in analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. This may be another reason why metabolite ratios of different tumor entities were not significantly different in our study.</p><p>Correct grading of gliomas has significant clinical impact because adjuvant therapy after surgery is usually administered to high-grade but not low-grade gliomas. Histopathology as gold standard based on biopsy samples is limited due to the inherent sampling error in these heterogeneous tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. In accordance with previous observations, high-grade gliomas had higher rrCBV [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>], rrCBF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>], and Cho levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>] than low-grade gliomas. However, we observed a significant overlap of metabolite ratios and tumor perfusion between high- and low-grade gliomas, which may be explained by the inherent glioma heterogeneity and the sampling error of biopsy samples, as observed previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>], although all low-grade gliomas in our study had a homogeneous appearance both on conventional MRI and functional MRI with no focal areas of contrast enhancement, elevated perfusion, or increased MRSI metabolites and even lacked focal malignant transformation in histology. Nevertheless, the use of perfusion measurements and metabolite ratios increased the sensitivity, specificity, PPV, and NPV compared with conventional MRI (sensitivity, 73&#x00025;; specificity, 65&#x00025;; PPV, 86&#x00025;; and NPV, 44&#x00025;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>] for discriminating high- from low-grade gliomas. The threshold values presented in our study can be used in a clinical setting to evaluate tumors preoperatively for histologic grade and provide a means for guiding treatment and predicting postoperative patient outcome. In comparison with a previous study that only distinguished between low- and high-grade gliomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>], we could demonstrate that MR perfusion and spectroscopic imaging provide better prospective grading of gliomas than conventional MRI, even when discriminating glioblastomas from grade 3 gliomas and grade 3 from grade 2 gliomas. However, because of the low specificity, especially when differentiating grade 3 from grade 2 gliomas, these functional MRI techniques have limited utility for an individual patient in making a specific diagnosis, but they may be of great clinical value for biopsy guidance because of the potential glioma heterogeneity with high-grade components that might be interspersed among low-grade components. Thus, it may become possible to reduce potential errors due to sampling bias from a stereotactic biopsy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>].</p><p>Although conventional MRI characteristics of solitary metastases and primary high-grade gliomas may sometimes be similar, MR perfusion and spectroscopic imaging enable distinction between the two [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>]. Although both intratumoral metabolite ratios [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>], rrCBV or rrCBF values did not allow for discrimination between the two entities, analyzing the peritumoral T2-weighted hyperintense region allows discrimination between high-grade gliomas and metastases or, as indicated by our initial results, grade 1 meningiomas. High Cho and reduced NAA signals as well as elevated perfusion in the peritumoral region of the lesion represent with high specificity glioma in differentiation of glioma from metastasis or grade 1 meningioma. The decrease in NAA is a marker of neuronal or axonal injury and loss, while the elevated Cho concentration suggested an increase of cell membrane synthesis and turnover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>] and an increased number of cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>]. Gliomas are known to infiltrate along vascular channels, whereas peritumoral regions in metastases or grade 1 meningiomas contain no tumor cells or vascular endothelial proliferation but almost purely vasogenic edema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>]. Hence, MR perfusion and spectroscopic imaging allow us to readily appreciate tumor extension past obvious gross anatomic boundaries on conventional MRI.</p><p>In our study, perfusion MRI measurements had the superior diagnostic performance in predicting glioma grade and in differentiating glioblastoma from other tumor entities. Because of the shorter acquisition time and the better predictive values in differential diagnosis, we would favor the use of perfusion over spectroscopic imaging on a 1.5-T MR unit. This may be the case in patients with reduced physical condition and compliance, which results in a limited imaging time. DCE MRI offered little information for differential diagnosis of enhancing brain tumors. This technique may be rather used for treatment monitoring of brain tumors, especially of extraaxial lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>], because the technique is not as susceptible to susceptibility artifacts arising from bone and air as DSC MRI. For intra-axial lesions, the value of DSC MRI for treatment monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>] and biopsy targeting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>] has already been reported. Although functional MRI techniques have a better diagnostic performance than conventional MRI techniques in distinguishing different tumor entities, functional MRI cannot eliminate the need for a biopsy and histologic confirmation.
</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors thank Marco Meissner, Department of Radiology, German Cancer Research Center, for help with data analysis.
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Reprinted with permission from Neurology volume 66 Weber <italic>et al.</italic> Diagnostic performance of spectroscopic and perfusion MRI for distinction of brain tumors, pp. 1899&#x02013;1906, copyright 2006, with permission from AAN Enterprises Inc. Corresponds to presentation titled &#x02018;MRI for grading, therapy guidance and follow-up of gliomas&#x02019;.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Litt</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagzag</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracranial mass lesions: dynamic contrast-enhanced susceptibility-weighted echo-planar perfusion MR imaging</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>223</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11930044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamalle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Decorps</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodology of brain perfusion imaging</article-title><source>J Magn Reson Imaging</source><year>2001</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11276094</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Warach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thangaraj</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wielopolski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelman</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noninvasive perfusion imaging of human brain tumors with EPISTAR</article-title><source>Eur Radiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8798035</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warmuth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantification of blood flow in brain tumors: comparison of arterial spin labeling and dynamic susceptibility-weighted contrast-enhanced MR imaging</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>228</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12819338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choyke</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional tumor imaging with dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>J Magn Reson Imaging</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12720260</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MR spectroscopy of brain tumors</article-title><source>Top Magn Reson Imaging</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15627004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluml</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamelak</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy in clinical decision making for patients with suspected malignant brain tumors</article-title><source>J Neurooncol</source><year>1999</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10728912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schlemmer</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bachert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Herfarth</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuna</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Debus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Kaick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton MR spectroscopic evaluation of suspicious brain lesions after stereotactic radiotherapy</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1316</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11498420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heiland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harting</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinguishing of primary cerebral lymphoma from high-grade glioma with perfusion-weighted magnetic resonance imaging</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2003</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12566167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijens</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Bent</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dijk</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudkerk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>1H chemical shift imaging reveals loss of brain tumor choline signal after administration of Gd-contrast</article-title><source>Magn Reson Med</source><year>1997</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9001146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luh</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandettini</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyde</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QUIPPS II with thin-slice TI1 periodic saturation: a method for improving accuracy of quantitative perfusion imaging using pulsed arterial spin labeling</article-title><source>Magn Reson Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1246</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10371458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Arterial spin labeling in combination with a look-locker sampling strategy: inflow turbo-sampling EPI-FAIR (ITS-FAIR)</article-title><source>Magn Reson Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>974</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawighorst</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Debus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic MRI for assessment of malignant glioma response to stereotactic radiotherapy: initial results</article-title><source>J Magn Reson Imaging</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9702878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hawighorst</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Engenhart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intracranial meningiomas: time- and dose-dependent effects of irradiation on tumor microcirculation monitored by dynamic MR imaging</article-title><source>Magn Reson Imaging</source><year>1997</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9223043</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Litt</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-grade gliomas and solitary metastases: differentiation by using perfusion and proton spectroscopic MR imaging</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>222</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11867790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thilmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of irradiated brain metastases by means of arterial spin-labeling and dynamic susceptibility-weighted contrast-enhanced perfusion MRI: initial results</article-title><source>Invest Radiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15087722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relative cerebral blood volume measurements in intracranial mass lesions: interobserver and intraobserver reproducibility study</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glioma grading: sensitivity, specificity, and predictive values of perfusion MR imaging and proton MR spectroscopic imaging compared with conventional MR imaging</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1989</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;nther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of arterial spin-labeling techniques and dynamic susceptibility-weighted contrast-enhanced MRI in perfusion imaging of normal brain tissue</article-title><source>Invest Radiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>712</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harting</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jost</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differentiating primary central nervous system lymphoma from glioma in humans using localised proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy</article-title><source>Neurosci Lett</source><year>2003</year><volume>342</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12757890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lev</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozsunar</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Henson</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glial tumor grading and outcome prediction using dynamic spin-echo MR susceptibility mapping compared with conventional contrast-enhanced MR: confounding effect of elevated rCBV of oligodendroglimoas</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calvar</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meli</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterization of brain tumors by MRS, DWI and Ki-67 labeling index</article-title><source>J Neurooncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>du Plessis</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fildes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation of molecular genetics with molecular and morphological imaging in gliomas with an oligodendroglial component</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>7182</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R Development Core Team R</surname><given-names/></name></person-group><article-title>A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</article-title><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuncali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation and simple linear regression</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12773666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bamber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The area above the ordinal dominance graph and the area below the receiver operating characteristic graph</article-title><source>J Math Psychol</source><year>1975</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>415</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halpern</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Minimally selected p and other tests for a single abrupt changepoint in a binary sequence</article-title><source>Biometrics</source><year>1999</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1044</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11315046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agresti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caffo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simple and effective confidence intervals for proportions and differences of proportions result from adding two successes and two failures</article-title><source>Am Stat</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bretz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Genz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hothorn</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>On the numerical availability of multiple comparison procedures</article-title><source>Biomet J</source><year>2001</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlation between choline level measured by proton MR spectroscopy and Ki-67 labeling index in gliomas</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10782774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000fc;hring</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrlinger</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Krings</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiex</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000fc;ker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MRI features of primary central nervous system lymphomas at presentation</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2001</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11515505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aronen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazit</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cerebral blood volume maps of gliomas: comparison with tumor grade and histologic findings</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1994</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8134596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugahara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Korogi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kochi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Correlation of MR imaging-determined cerebral blood volume maps with histologic and angiographic determination of vascularity of gliomas</article-title><source>Am J Roentgenol</source><year>1998</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>1479</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9843274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Glial neoplasms: dynamic contrast-enhanced T2*-weighted MR imaging</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>211</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10352608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwun</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using relative cerebral blood flow and volume to evaluate the histopathologic grade of cerebral gliomas: preliminary results</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2002</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12185064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinction between high-grade gliomas and solitary metastases using peritumoral 3-T magnetic resonance spectroscopy, diffusion, and perfusion imagings</article-title><source>Neuroradiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>619</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15243726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowling</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollen</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Noworolski</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preoperative proton MR spectroscopic imaging of brain tumors: correlation with histopathologic analysis of resection specimens</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>604</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11290466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burtscher</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Skagerberg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Geijer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahlberg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Holtas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proton MR spectroscopy and preoperative diagnostic accuracy: an evaluation of intracranial mass lesions characterized by stereotactic biopsy findings</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10669230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopp</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic contrast-enhanced T2 <sup>*</sup>-weighted MR imaging of recurrent malignant gliomas treated with
thalidomide and carboplatin</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10815664</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>