<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="meeting-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1805063</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Workshops</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>WORKSHOPS 4&#x02013;6</article-title><subtitle>Tuesday 17 October 2006, 16:00&#x02013;17:30</subtitle></title-group><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S122</fpage><lpage>S125</lpage></article-meta></front><sub-article id="d31e43" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069019</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Prostate cancer&#x02014;current status and new developments</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barentsz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.1"><label>*</label>Department of Radiology, Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre, Nijmegen, The Netherlands</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.1">Corresponding address: Jelle Barentsz, Professor of Radiology, Chair for Research, Department of Radiology, UMC St. Radboud Nijmegen, PO Box 9101, 6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands. Email: <email>j.barentsz@rad.umcn.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S122</fpage><lpage>S122</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>The objectives of this presentation are to discuss the clinical role of magnetic resonance (MR) in local and nodal staging of prostate cancer, and to show new developments. The clinical questions are how can we improve with new MR imaging (MRI) techniques: localization, local staging, targeted radiotherapy planning, and nodal staging? Accurate tumour localisation is important for detection of prostate cancer in patients with clinical suspicion (e.g. elevated prostate-specific antigen (PSA)) and a negative trans-rectal ultrasound biopsy. When combining anatomical (T2-weighted) high resolution techniques by applying either 1.5 T with an endorectal coil, or 3 T without an endorectal coil, with contrast enhanced dynamic MRI and MR spectroscopy, localization accuracy is &#x0223c;90&#x00025;. The additional use of this technique has been shown to increase the rate of positive biopsies. In addition, when the tumour is accurately localised, local staging by inexperienced radiologists improves. These localisation techniques allow targeted radiotherapy planning (e.g. by giving 90 Gy to the dominant intraprostatic lesion), as fusion with these &#x02018;functional&#x02019; MR images and computed tomography (CT) is feasible. Local staging at 1.5 T without using an endorectal coil results in a sensitivity of 64&#x00025; and a specificity of 72&#x00025;. When using an endorectal coil, specificity can improve to 98&#x00025; with equal sensitivity. Advanced MRI at 3 T using an endorectal coil has resulted in a sensitivity of 88&#x00025; and a specificity of 96&#x00025;. When a high specificity reading is performed in patients with intermediate to high risk for extracapsular disease (PSA &#x0003e; 10 or Gleason &#x0003e; 6 or T3 at digital rectal examination (DRE)), and if prostatectomy is not performed in a stage T3 on such an MRI, the use of MRI results in a cost-saving of 2500 euros per patient. As current cross sectional imaging techniques and positron emission tomography (PET)-CT have limited sensitivity in detecting nodal metastases (CT 35&#x00025;, and [<sup>18</sup>F]FDG-PET 65&#x00025;), in patients with intermediate to high risk for nodal metastases (PSA &#x0003e; 10 or Gleason &#x0003e; 6 or T3 at DRE) routinely a pelvic lymph node dissection is performed. However, it has been showed that with this (obturator) dissection not all positive nodes are detected. The combination of a new MRI (lymph node specific) contrast agent (MRL) has been shown to have a sensitivity and specificity &#x0003e;90&#x00025; and a negative predictive value of 97&#x00025; in detecting even small nodes. In patients with a negative MRL a diagnostic pelvic lymph node dissection can be safely avoided. This results in a cost saving of approximately 2000 euros per patient. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e122" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9020</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS122</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069020</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MR imaging of the cervix</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reinhold</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.2">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.2"><label>*</label>McGill University Health Centre, 1650 Cedar Avenue, Montreal, Quebec, H3G 1A4, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.2">Corresponding address: Caroline Reinhold, Associate Professor of Radiology, Gynaecology &#x00026; Gastroenterology, McGill University Health Centre, 1650 Cedar Avenue, Montreal, Quebec, H3G 1A4, Canada. Email: <email>caroline.reinhold@muhc.mcgill.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S122</fpage><lpage>S122</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>This course will enable the attendee to review the FIGO staging system of cervical carcinoma and understand how the various stages impact on patient management, thereby allowing the radiologist to tailor the report according to what the clinician wants to know. The magnetic resonance (MR) imaging findings as well as potential pitfalls of the FIGO staging system will be illustrated. The attendee will take home clear guidelines on the MR staging criteria and will understand the relative accuracy of MR and computed tomography (CT) for the various stages. Ways of optimising MR imaging of cervical carcinoma will also be presented. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e198" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69021</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9021</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069021</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MR imaging of the ovary</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>J A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.3">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.3"><label>*</label>Department of Radiology, St James&#x02019;s University Hospital, Leeds, LS9 7TF, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.3">Corresponding address: J A Spencer, Department of Radiology, St James&#x02019;s University Hospital, Leeds, LS9 7TF, UK. Email: <email>johnaspencer50@hotmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S123</fpage><lpage>S123</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Magnetic resonance (MR) imaging has a vital role in problem solving for the adnexal mass which is indeterminate between benign and malignant after ultrasound and clinical assessment. This is a vital distinction because lesions considered malignant should be referred to cancer centres for extensive cytoreductive surgery in the hands of skilled gynaecological surgeons whilst benign lesions can be simply resected by unit general gynaecologists or watched on the basis of symptoms. Common benign lesions such as dermoid cysts, haemorrhagic lesions and pedunculated fibroids may confound ultrasound. MR imaging allows recognition of key tissue characteristics of fat, blood, fibrous tissue and vascularised soft tissue although it may fail to detect calcifications. It uses fat suppression sequences to define the presence of fat; it recognises blood products and their age. Oblique planar imaging allows demonstration of connection to the uterus of fibroids and separation from it in the case of ovarian fibroma. Selective use of intravenous gadolinium defines enhancement patterns of solid lesions. MR imaging is most valuable when CA125 is normal or only minimally elevated. A significant minority of women with endometriosis and inflammatory disease may have elevated CA125. Conversely women with confined cancer may have normal levels. Even with the application of MR imaging radiologists may overcall some complex benign lesions as malignant. Even surgeons and pathologists are uncertain until lesions are opened and sectioned. However, this can be reduced with meticulous technique following a simple algorithm and recognition of common variants and pitfalls in diagnosis. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e274" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9022</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS123</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069022</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CT/MRI of the peritoneum</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reznek</surname><given-names>Rodney H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.4">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.4"><label>*</label>St Bartholomew&#x02019;s Hospital, London, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.4">Corresponding address: Rodney H Reznek, FRCP, FRCR, Professor of Diagnostic Imaging, Cancer Imaging, St Bartholomew&#x02019;s Hospital, London, UK. Email: <email>r.h.reznek@qmul.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S123</fpage><lpage>S123</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Prior to the advent of computed tomography (CT), peritoneal metastases were not radiographically detectable until late in the disease, when they displaced adjacent organs, caused intestinal obstruction, or produced radiological signs due to massive ascites on plain films. CT can identify peritoneal metastases as small as a few millimetres in size and also identify very small volumes of ascites. This information is essential in staging tumours, assessing resectability, monitoring response, and identifying recurrence. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e350" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9023</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069023</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Diagnosis and staging small bowel tumours</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>R M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.5">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.5"><label>*</label>Department of Radiology, Northwestern University Medical School, Evanston, IL, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.5">Corresponding address: Richard M Gore, MD, Gastrointestinal Imaging, Department of Diagnostic Radiology, Evanston Northwestern Healthcare, 2650 Ridge Ave, Evanston, IL 60201, USA. Email: <email>rmgore1953@aol.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S124</fpage><lpage>S124</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Small bowel tumours are uncommon and their detection is illusive. Indeed, there is typically a delay in diagnosis of up to three to five years with many small bowel neoplasms, so that they often have an advanced stage at the time of operation. As a result, there has been no significant change in survival of these patients in the last five decades despite significant progress in surgical intervention and chemotherapy. In this presentation, recent advances in multidetector computed tomography (MDCT), breath hold magnetic resonance (MR), computed tomography (CT)-enterography, CT-enteroclysis, MR-enteroclysis, and the video capsule are highlighted. The potential of these new imaging techniques to provide earlier diagnosis and more accurate preoperative staging of adenocarcinomas, carcinoids, and gastrointestinal stromal tumours is featured. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e426" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9024</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS124</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069024</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nasal and paranasal tumours</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.6">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.6"><label>*</label>Department of Radiology, University Hospitals Leuven, Leuven, Belgium</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.6">Corresponding address: Robert Hermans, MD, PhD, Department of Radiology, University Hospitals Leuven, Herestraat 49, B-3000 Leuven, Belgium. Email: <email>robert.hermans@uz.kuleuven.ac.be</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S124</fpage><lpage>S124</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Many different types of malignant tumors arise within the sinonasal cavities, constituting less than one percent of all malignant neoplasms. Sinonasal carcinoma is a disease mainly occurring in the age range of 50&#x02013;70 years, although some tumor types also occur in younger patients. The risk for developing sinonasal carcinoma is associated with exposure to certain exogenous factors. Tumors arising in the paranasal sinuses have abundant place to grow, and are usually diagnosed in an advanced stage. They may present with nasal obstruction, facial deformity, orbital symptoms, trismus, pain or other neurological symptoms. Sometimes associated inflammatory disease overshadows the tumor. Imaging is necessary for evaluating paranasal extension and possible intracranial spread, orbital involvement, infratemporal extension, spread to the nasopharynx, oropharynx or oral cavity and spread along neurovascular bundles. When there is extension into the skin, oral cavity or pharynx, or when a recurrent tumor is present, the facial lymph nodes and the upper neck nodes should be included in the imaging study. Although contrast-enhanced computed tomography (CT) will often adequately show the tumor extension, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is indicated when the tumor is close to the intracranial compartment, to evaluate possible dural involvement or transdural extension. MRI is also best to evaluate subtle orbital involvement, as well as subtle perineural spread. A major advantage of MRI over CT is the better differentiation of tumor from accompanying inflammatory changes. The imaging findings influence therapeutic management. Many patients with malignant sinonasal neoplasms are managed surgically. In advanced sinonasal cancer, surgery is often combined with radiation therapy; the radiation fields are individualized based on disease extent. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article><sub-article id="d31e502" article-type="abstract"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69025</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9025</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.iSpec No A.pgS125</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069025</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Abstract</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cervical lymphadenopathy: what radiologists should know</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1.7">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1.7"><label>*</label>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, National University Hospital, Singapore</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1.7">Corresponding address: Department of Diagnostic Radiology, National University Hospital, 5 Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore 119074. Email: <email>dnrcfhv@nus.edu.sg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S125</fpage><lpage>S125</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>Most head and neck tumours spread to the cervical nodes as part of their natural history. Up to 80&#x00025; of patients with upper aerodigestive mucosal malignancies will have cervical nodal metastasis at presentation. The occurrence of nodal metastasis has a profound effect on the surgical management and prognosis of these patients. In general, it decreases the overall survival by half. The presence of extracapsular spread, level of nodal metastasis, the number and size of nodes correlate with distant metastasis. Apart from nodal staging, imaging contributes to the follow up of patients. Following surgery or radiation therapy or both, the indurated soft tissues often make neck palpation difficult. PET has a useful role in detecting disease recurrence at the primary site, nodal relapse or distant metastasis. To facilitate communication, radiologists should be familiar with the anatomical distribution of cervical nodes and their relationship with the numerical level classification system used by their surgical colleagues. The pathologists also use the same level system when they document cervical nodes in radical neck dissection specimens. This presentation correlates the anatomical and the simplified level classification systems of cervical lymph nodes and examines the clinical significance of nodal metastasis. The criteria used to diagnose nodal metastasis and their limitations are also evaluated. </p></abstract></article-meta></front></sub-article></article>
