<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4601851</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1470-7330-15-S1-P22</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1470-7330-15-S1-P22</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CT characteristic of early local recurrence after resection of the squamous cell carcinoma: comparison with CT characteristics of granulation tissue at stump site</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>Hye Jeon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mimowdr@naver.com</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Ki</surname><given-names>Mi Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>Chang-Min</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Radiology, Hallym University College of Medicine, Hallym University Sacred Heart Hospital, Korea</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology and Research Institute of Radiology, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, Seoul 138-736, Korea, 86 Asanbyeongwon-Gil, Songpa-Gu, Seoul 138-735, Korea</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, Seoul 138-736, Korea, 86 Asanbyeongwon-Gil, Songpa-Gu, Seoul 138-735, Korea</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Oncology, University of Ulsan College of Medicine, Asan Medical Center, Seoul 138-736, Korea, 86 Asanbyeongwon-Gil, Songpa-Gu, Seoul 138-735, Korea</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">Proceedings of the International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 15th Annual Teaching Course</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication charges for this supplement were funded through the International Cancer Imaging Society by support received from Siemens Healthcare GmbH.</named-content></supplement><fpage>P22</fpage><lpage>P22</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Hwang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hwang et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cancerimagingjournal.com/content/15/S1/P22"/><conference><conf-date>5-7 October 2015</conf-date><conf-name>International Cancer Imaging Society Meeting and 15th Annual Teaching Course (ICIS 2015)</conf-name><conf-loc>London, UK</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Aim</title><p>To compare thin section CT characteristics of the early local tumour recurrence after the resection of squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) with those of the stump deformity or granulation tissue.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Twenty nine consecutive patients with local recurrence after definitive SCC operation from April 2006 to September 2012 were included. Pre- and post-operative CT from these patients were retrospectively reviewed and compared with those in age- and gender-matched 29 patients with stump deformity or granulation tissue at stump site after the definitive SCC operation, by two chest radiologists.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>Local recurrence were commonly observed as round/oval shape, peripheral eccentric lesion or central contour bulging lesion on CT, while the stump deformity or granulation tissue were commonly demonstrated as irregular or flat shape, focal wall thickening. The size of suspected soft tissue and the distance between stump staples and suspected soft tissue were significantly different between two groups (median; 19mm and 3mm; 18mm and 0mm, respectively, <italic>p</italic>&#x0003c; 0.001). The univariate analysis showed that the size of soft tissue and the distance between soft tissue and stump site were associated with the predictive factors of local recurrence (<italic>p</italic>&#x0003c; 0.001). On the receiver operating characteristic analysis, the optimal cut-offs of the size of soft tissue and the distance between soft tissue and stump staples were 6mm and 5mm, respectively.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The proper knowledge of stump recurrence regarding the size and the distance around the stump on CT imaging will help us achieve an early and higher diagnostic rate of recurred SCC.</p></sec></body></article>