<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cncr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0008-543X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1097-0142</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23625540</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3700651</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.28087</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Which Strategies Reduce Breast Cancer Mortality Most?</article-title><subtitle>Collaborative Modeling of Optimal Screening, Treatment, and Obesity Prevention</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelblatt</surname><given-names>Jeanne</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>Nicolien</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>Clyde</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MA</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Yaojen</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>An-Tsun</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Near</surname><given-names>Aimee M</given-names></name><degrees>MPH</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>Ahmedin</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Oncology, Georgetown University, Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center</institution><addr-line>Washington, DC</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Public Health, Erasmus MC</institution><addr-line>Rotterdam, the Netherlands</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Departments of Family and Social Medicine and Epidemiology/Population Health, Albert Einstein School of Medicine</institution><addr-line>Bronx, New York</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>American Cancer Society</institution><addr-line>Atlanta, Georgia</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Corresponding authors:</bold> Jeanne Mandelblatt, MD, MPH, Lombardi Comprehensive Cancer Center, 3300 Whitehaven Street NW, Suite 4100, Washington, DC 20007; Fax: (202) 687-0305; <email>mandelbj@georgetown.edu</email></corresp><fn><p>Prepared under contract from the American Cancer Society Project #NHSURVGDO.</p></fn><fn><p>We thank the Breast Cancer Surveillance Consortium (BCSC) for data provided for this study. BCSC data collection was supported by NCI cooperative agreements U01CA63740, U01CA86076, U01CA86082, U01CA63736, U01CA70013, U01CA69976, U01CA63731, U01CA70040, and HHSN261201100031C. The collection of cancer data was also supported by public health departments and cancer registries. For a full description of these sources, please see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.breastscreening.cancer.gov/work/acknowledgement.html">http://www.breastscreening.cancer.gov/work/acknowledgement.html</ext-link>. A list of the BCSC investigators and procedures for requesting data are provided at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/">http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn><p>Model results are the sole responsibility of the authors and do not reflect the views of the funding agencies.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>119</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2541</fpage><lpage>2548</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 American Cancer Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial exploitation.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>BACKGROUND</title><p>US breast cancer mortality is declining, but thousands of women still die each year.</p></sec><sec><title>METHODS</title><p>Two established simulation models examine 6 strategies that include increased screening and/or treatment or elimination of obesity versus continuation of current patterns. The models use common national data on incidence and obesity prevalence, competing causes of death, mammography characteristics, treatment effects, and survival/cure. Parameters are modified based on obesity (defined as BMI &#x02265; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Outcomes are presented for the year 2025 among women aged 25+ and include numbers of cases, deaths, mammograms and false-positives; age-adjusted incidence and mortality; breast cancer mortality reduction and deaths averted; and probability of dying of breast cancer.</p></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>If current patterns continue, the models project that there would be about 50,100-57,400 (range across models) annual breast cancer deaths in 2025. If 90% of women were screened annually from ages 40 to 54 and biennially from ages 55 to 99 (or death), then 5100-6100 fewer deaths would occur versus current patterns, but incidence, mammograms, and false-positives would increase. If all women received the indicated systemic treatment (with no screening change), then 11,400-14,500 more deaths would be averted versus current patterns, but increased toxicity could occur. If 100% received screening plus indicated therapy, there would be 18,100-20,400 fewer deaths. Eliminating obesity yields 3300-5700 fewer breast cancer deaths versus continuation of current obesity levels.</p></sec><sec><title>CONCLUSIONS</title><p>Maximal reductions in breast cancer deaths could be achieved through optimizing treatment use, followed by increasing screening use and obesity prevention. <bold><italic>Cancer</italic> 2013;119:2541&#x02013;2548</bold>. &#x000a9; <italic>2013 American Cancer Society</italic>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>simulation</kwd><kwd>modeling</kwd><kwd>breast cancer</kwd><kwd>treatment</kwd><kwd>mammography</kwd><kwd>obesity</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Breast cancer mortality continues to decrease in the United States, largely because of improved treatment and screening,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref> but it remains the most commonly diagnosed nonskin cancer and the second-leading female cause of cancer death, with about 40,000 dying each year.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref> Reasons for the continuing burden of breast cancer are multifactorial and include the &#x0201c;graying of America,&#x0201d; high rates of obesity that affect incidence and complicate treatment, suboptimal access to screening and timely diagnostic follow-up, nonstandard and/or delayed treatment, limits in existing screening and therapeutic paradigms, socioeconomic factors that diminish survival, and unknown aspects of this disease.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref> Evaluating the impact of these factors on breast cancer mortality across the population separately and jointly is not feasible through empirical research.</p><p>Modeling can be used as a population laboratory to estimate the impact of changing a number of these contributing factors alone or in combination.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref> In this article, we use 2 well-established models<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> to evaluate combinations of screening and treatment strategies<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref> or elimination of obesity to decrease breast cancer deaths beyond what would be expected if current patterns persist.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><p>The 2 models (MISCAN-Fadia and SPECTRUM) were developed independently within the Cancer Intervention and Surveillance Modeling Network<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref> and were exempt from institutional review board approval. The models estimate the impact of applying 6 strategies in the US female population from 2012 to 2025 versus maintaining current patterns: 1) 90% of women screen annually from ages 40 to 54 and biennially from ages 55 to 99 (or death) and the remaining 10% do not screen at all; women receive treatment based on current patterns; 2) current screening, but 100% receive treatment indicated by age, stage, and ER/HER2 status<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>; 3) 90% screening and 100% receipt of indicated treatment; 4) 100% screening and current patterns of treatment; 5) 100% screening and 100% indicated treatment; and 6) eliminate obesity but maintain current screening and treatment. Although we will never achieve 100% compliance or eliminate obesity, these strategies demonstrate upper bounds of possible known approaches. We examined a hybrid strategy of more frequent screening intervals at younger ages than at older ages because there are shorter age-dependent sojourn times before versus after menopause. We did not impose an upper age limit to provide an estimate of the impact of screening and treatment over the entire life course.</p><sec><title>Model Overview</title><p>Both models begin with estimates of incidence and mortality trends without screening and systemic treatment and then overlay screening use and improvements in survival associated with systemic therapy.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref> We overlay actual dissemination of screening and systemic treatments as our &#x0201c;base case,&#x0201d; carrying these rates forward into the future. We superimpose the 6 strategies beginning in 2012 through 2025. Women are followed until death, even if that date is after 2025.</p><p>Breast cancer is depicted as having a preclinical screening-detectable period and a clinical detection point. On the basis of mammography sensitivity (or thresholds of detection), screening identifies disease in the preclinical period and results in the identification of earlier-stage or smaller tumors than occurs via clinical detection. In MISCAN-Fadia, treatment results in cure for some women, and in SPECTRUM it results in reductions in the hazards of death. Obesity (body mass index [BMI] &#x02265; 30 kg/m<sup>2</sup>) affects outcomes based on its age- and cohort-specific prevalence<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref> through its impact on multiple model parameters.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref> Current obesity prevalence is projected forward.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Model Parameters</title><p>Both models use a common set of age-specific variables along with model-specific inputs to represent disease history (eg, incidence, stage shifts, or tumor growth).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref> For instance, based on the varying model structures, SPECTRUM uses an age&#x02013;period&#x02013;cohort model<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref> to represent incidence from 1975 to 2000 without screening, whereas MISCAN-Fadia only uses it to estimate tumor onset. Consequently, the models have slightly different incidence rates beginning in 1975, but comparable results for trends over time.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref> Both extrapolate age-specific incidence rates forward based on rates in 2000. Obesity increases the risk for breast cancer in postmenopausal women (relative risk [RR], 1.25) but decreases the risk in premenopausal women (RR, 0.60).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref></p><p>The current dissemination of mammography is depicted based on the age of receipt of the first mammography and the interval between subsequent mammograms using data from the National Health Interview Survey and the Breast Cancer Surveillance Consortium (BCSC), respectively; current rates are carried forward to 2025 for each cohort and age group.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref> Because mammography use does not vary by BMI except at extremes values,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref> we assume that obesity has no effect on mammography use. We use age- and BMI-specific mammography sensitivity and specificity observed in the BCSC (unpublished data) to develop model inputs<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref> and with other data<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref> to define thresholds of detection. The impact of digital mammography was evaluated in sensitivity analyses.</p><p>The American Joint Committee on Cancer stage distribution in the absence of screening is estimated from Surveillance, Epidemiology, and End Results (SEER) data in 1975-1979.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> After 1979 we phase in distributions among clinically detected women using BCSC data. Stage distributions among screened women are estimated using unpublished BCSC data from 1996 to 2007. Because obesity is associated with more advanced tumors at diagnosis,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> we use BCSC data on stage by BMI and age groups for unscreened and screened women.</p><p>The joint distribution of ER and HER2 status by age, year, and stage is estimated from women diagnosed from 1997 to 2005.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref> Because obesity affects the rate of ER-positive tumors differentially by menopausal status,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref> we apply RRs of 0.86 and 1.78 to the probability of ER-positive cancer among obese pre- and postmenopausal women, respectively. We assume that obesity has no impact on HER2 status.</p><p>Dissemination of systemic chemo- and hormonal therapy from 1975 to 2000 was estimated using NCI Patterns of Care data by age, year, stage, and ER status<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> and updated through 2010 (including trastuzumab for HER2-positive cases) using unpublished data from the National Comprehensive Cancer Network Outcomes Database; these data are carried forward. Strategies that include 100% indicated treatment assume: 1) ER-positive invasive cases receive chemotherapy and hormonal treatment based on age and year (tamoxifen between 1980 and 1999, tamoxifen &#x0003c;50 years, and anastrozole if &#x02265;50 years from 2000 to 2010), and DCIS cases only receive hormonal therapy; 2) ER-negative invasive cases receive chemotherapy; and 3) HER2-positive tumors diagnosed in 2005 or later receive trastuzumab.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref> We assume that treatment patterns do not vary by obesity. Treatment effectiveness is based on a synthesis of clinical trials.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref> Chemotherapy effectiveness is reduced in about 30% of obese ER-negative women based on dose reductions.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref> We assume obesity has no impact on hormonal or trastuzumab effectiveness.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref> SEER data from 1975 to 1979 are used to estimate breast cancer survival before screening and adjuvant treatment were available.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> Nonbreast cancer mortality is calculated by subtracting breast cancer from all-cause mortality.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref> The impact of obesity was incorporated using NHANES-mortality linked data.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref></p></sec><sec><title>Benefits and Burden</title><p>The models project the probability of breast cancer death and age-adjusted mortality rates from age 25 years to death based on continuing current patterns of screening and treatment and each of the 6 alternative strategies in 2025. The number of breast cancer deaths averted is calculated by applying model projections of age-specific mortality rates to the age-specific US population projections for 2025.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref> False-positive mammograms are a proxy for burden and are defined as the number of mammograms read as needing further follow-up in women without cancer. Results are presented in absolute terms and incremental numbers compared with current patterns.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>RESULTS</title><p>Observed incidence and mortality rates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Figs. 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">2</xref>) and stage distributions (not shown) from 2000 to 2009 were accurately reproduced by both models. If current patterns continue to 2025, the models project that breast cancer mortality rates would be 31.8-36.3 (range across the models) per 100,000 women, or 50,000-57,400 breast cancer deaths in women aged 25 or older (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>).</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Age-adjusted breast cancer incidence rates from 2000 to 2025 predicted by the models for alternative screening strategies (strategies that include treatment are not included since they do not affect incidence) versus those reported to SEER (breast cancer incidence reported to SEER from 2000 to 2009) for women 25 years and older. (a) SPECTRUM. (b) MISCAN-Fadia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cncr0119-2541-f1"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>TABLE 1</label><caption><p>Predicted Absolute Outcomes in 2025 by Model and Alternative Screening and Treatment Strategies Versus Continuation of Current Patterns for Women 25 Years and Older</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">No. of Mammograms/1000</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">False-Positives/1000</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Age-Adjusted Mortality Rate/100,000</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Number of Breast Cancer Deaths<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-4">d</xref></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Probability of Dying of Breast Cancer<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-5">e</xref></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strategy</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current screening and Rx patterns<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57,400</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">b</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">277.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35,600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.3%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90% screening and current Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51,300</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90% screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">417.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">419.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% screening and current Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">464.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">465.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,400</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43,600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-2">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf1-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">463.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">465.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39,300</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.7%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: Rx, treatment.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-1"><label>a</label><p>Current refers to screening and/or treatment as actually disseminated in the US population.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-2"><label>b</label><p>All women receive indicated treatment based on age, stage, and ER/HER2 status.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-3"><label>c</label><p>Ninety percent or 100% schedules are annual screening from ages 40 to 54 and biennially from ages 55 to 99 (or death). In the 90% strategy, the remaining 10% are assumed to not have any screening.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-4"><label>d</label><p>Rounded to the nearest hundred.</p></fn><fn id="tf1-5"><label>e</label><p>Calculated using Probability of Developing or Dying of Cancer Software, Version 6.6.1; Surveillance Research Program, Statistical Methodology and Applications Branch, National Cancer Institute, 2012; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://surveillance.cancer.gov/devcan">http://surveillance.cancer.gov/devcan</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Predicted age-adjusted breast cancer mortality from 2000 to 2025 by alternative screening and treatment strategies versus that reported to SEER (breast cancer mortality reported in SEER from 2000 to 2009) for women 25 years and older. (a) SPECTRUM. (b) MISCAN-Fadia.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cncr0119-2541-f2"/></fig><sec><title>Increased Screening or Indicated Treatment Versus Continuation of Current Patterns</title><p>If screening rates increase in 2012 from current patterns to 90% of women screened annually from age 40 to 54 and then biennially from age 55 onward (with no change in treatment patterns), incidence rates would have a transient increase at the start, followed by a leveling off at a higher rate than seen presently (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). The higher incidence would be accompanied by mortality reductions of 10.7%-11.5% in 2025 compared with continuing current screening, or about 5100- 6100 deaths averted among women &#x02265;25 years (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). These benefits would require more than 140 additional mammograms per 1000 women in 2025, including about 20 more false-positive tests per 1000 women than would occur if current patterns continue (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>TABLE 2</label><caption><p>Predicted Incremental Outcomes in 2025 by Model and Alternative Screening and Treatment Scenario Versus Continuation of Current Patterns for Women 25 Years and Older<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mammograms/1000</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">False-Positives/1000</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Percent Mortality Reduction</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Breast Cancer Deaths Averted<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-4">d</xref></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strategy (Each Compared Incrementally To Current)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current screening and Rx patterns<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">b</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,400</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14,500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90% screening and current Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90% screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19,400</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% screening and current Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-1">a</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6500</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% screening and 100% Rx<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-2">b</xref>,<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf2-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,400</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Abbreviations: NA, not applicable because no change in screening.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-1"><label>a</label><p>Current refers to screening and/or treatment as actually disseminated in the US population.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>b</label><p>All women receive indicated treatment based on age, stage, and ER/HER2 status.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-3"><label>c</label><p>Ninety percent or 100% schedules are annual screening from ages 40 to 54 and biennially from ages 55 to 99 (or death). In the 90% strategy, the remaining 10% are assumed to not have any screening.</p></fn><fn id="tf2-4"><label>d</label><p>Rounded to the nearest hundred.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>If 100% of women are screened, incidence increases further (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>), but mortality could be reduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>) by 13.4%-16.3% in 2025 versus continuation of current screening use. This translates into almost 6500-8900 more deaths averted than continuation of current patterns, but with an even greater increase in mammograms and false-positives (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref>). However, if screening continues at current levels, but all women receive indicated therapy, then mortality rates could be decreased by 19.8%-27.5% versus continuation of current treatment patterns, and 11,400-14,500 deaths could be avoided (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>One Hundred Percent Screening and 100% Indicated Treatment Versus Continuation of Current Patterns</title><p>Optimizing screening and treatment could reduce mortality by less than the sum of each approach because they interact (eg, the better treatment is, the less screening contributes to mortality reduction). Thus, the maximum aggregate reductions that could be achieved under optimal conditions are about 18,100- 20,400 more deaths averted in 2025 versus maintaining current patterns (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>). This corresponds to reducing a woman's lifetime probability of dying of breast cancer after age 25 years from 2.9% to 1.7%-2.0% (range across models); see <xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">Table 1</xref>. However, even under these idealized circumstances, there would still be 29,700-39,300 breast cancer deaths.</p></sec><sec><title>Elimination of Obesity</title><p>Obesity increases the incidence of breast cancer; 5.4%-5.6% of cases expected to occur in 2025 would be attributable to obesity if current rates are maintained (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">Table 3</xref>). If we could eradicate obesity, there could be about 3300-5700 fewer breast cancer deaths in 2025 in women &#x02265;25 years.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>TABLE 3</label><caption><p>Projected Impact of Obesity on Breast Cancer Outcomes for US Women 25 and Older in 2025 Assuming Current Patterns of Care Are Maintained</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Obese</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Nonobese</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">All Women</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPECTRUM</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MISCAN-Fadia</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-adjusted incidence rate per 100,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270.7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287.0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241.9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of breast cancer cases (invasive and in situ)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157,200</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167,100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245,600</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385,900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">412,700</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attributable fraction of breast cancer cases due to obesity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-2">b</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.4%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of cases that could be avoided if obesity were eliminated<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,000</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Mortality</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age-adjusted mortality rate per 100,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent mortality reduction<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">c</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.4%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of breast cancer deaths<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23,100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20,100</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30,000</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,900</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,100</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attributable fraction of breast cancer deaths due to obesity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-4">d</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2%</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6%</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of deaths that could be averted if obesity were eliminated<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-1">a</xref></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02014;</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5,700</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,300</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3-1"><label>a</label><p>Rounded to the nearest hundred.</p></fn><fn id="tf3-2"><label>b</label><p>Attributable fraction of incident cases based on formula p<sup>*</sup>(i_O &#x02212; i_N)/(p<sup>*</sup>i_O + (1 &#x02212; p)<sup>*</sup>i_N), where p is prevalence of obesity, i_O is incidence in obese, and i_N is incidence in nonobese.</p></fn><fn id="tf3-3"><label>c</label><p>Percent mortality reduction is calculated as the difference in the age-adjusted breast cancer mortality in 2025 between the current pattern and the nonobese scenario divided by the age-adjusted mortality in the current pattern scenario.</p></fn><fn id="tf3-4"><label>d</label><p>Attributable fraction of deaths based on formula p<sup>*</sup>(m_O &#x02212; m_N)/(p<sup>*</sup>m_O + (1 &#x02212;p)<sup>*</sup>m_N), where p is prevalence of obesity, m_O is mortality in obese, and m_N is mortality in nonobese.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Sensitivity Analysis</title><p>Improving test sensitivity or switching to digital mammography does not change the results substantially (not shown) because most lesions are slow growing and if missed on 1 exam are detected on the subsequent screen without much impact on mortality.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Maximal reductions in US deaths from breast cancer might be achieved through ensuring that all women have clinically indicated systemic therapy, followed by increasing screening, then obesity prevention after age 50, although greater screening could exacerbate false-positives and increase incidence. Even if optimal deployment of these currently available breast cancer control strategies were achievable, the number of projected future breast cancer deaths remains high.</p><p>Optimizing use of currently available systemic therapies results in nearly double the number of deaths averted than with enhancing screening levels compared with current patterns. But greater uptake of systemic therapy could lead to more therapy-related toxicity, and there are barriers to use at the system, provider, and patient level. For instance, suboptimal compliance with the full course of hormonal therapy has been noted in other research, so that modeled mortality reductions may not be realized.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref></p><p>In past research, we examined differences between lifetime screening annually or biennially starting at age 40 or 50.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> In the current study, we have extended those results by examining a hybrid approach of screening annually starting at age 40 and changing to a biennial schedule at age 55 and including different rates of use. The results suggest that the majority of added benefit of increased screening use is from increasing screening levels to 90% of women using regular screening compared with current patterns, even though 100% compliance could avoid additional deaths. However, recommendations for and compliance with 90%-100% regular screening at all ages will be difficult to acheive,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref> so that fewer deaths will be averted than projected by the models. Additional screening also imposes a burden of added false-positive results and increased incidence (and overdiagnosis).<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref></p><p>Greater program efficiencies might be achieved by using a community-based approach in populations in which screening and treatment services are suboptimal, as well as &#x0201c;personalized&#x0201d; risk-based approaches to target screening and treatment. The latter approach could result in more intensive screening of women with the highest risk of developing disease and deployment of therapies by women most likely to benefit and decreased use by women unlikely to benefit, minimizing harm and toxicity. However, to date, there is only a limited empiric database to support personalized approaches.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref> Future modeling should consider the impact of individual risk-based cancer control strategies as well as targeting geographic areas and communities with the highest burden of cancer and the least resources.</p><p>The models estimate that obesity, which presently occurs in about one third of the female population older than age 50,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref> accounts for only a modest number of breast cancer cases and deaths. Moreover, these estimates are an upper bound of what is achievable with intensive campaigns to lower obesity rates. As more data become available, it will be interesting to reexamine how strategies to reduce obesity will affect breast cancer outcomes via influences on the immune and metabolic systems that are implicated in breast cancer risk or probability of recurrence.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref></p><p>Overall, the collaboration of 2 groups with different modeling approaches and structures to estimate the same end points by using common data provides a reasonable range of expected results. Despite these strengths and our consistent results, our study has limitations. We do not capture decrements in quality of life associated with false-positive results, living with earlier knowledge of a cancer diagnosis and possible side effects of treatment, or overdiagnosis.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref> We extrapolate current data forward, and patterns may not continue as projected. We include mammography resources and do not include resources associated with increased use of therapy. The models also do not consider other primary prevention approaches beyond obesity reduction (eg, tamoxifen use by high-risk women) or improvements in multimodality local therapy over time.</p><p>In summary, our results suggest that substantial improvements in US breast cancer control can be made by ensuring that all women receive indicated systemic therapy, use regular screening, and avoid obesity after age 50. Multiple leverage points will be required to realize these improvements, but increasing the use of indicated systemic therapy is a necessary component of strategies for women diagnosed with breast cancer. Combinations of other approaches and new paradigms, guided by evidence from modeling, novel trials, and new scientific discovery, will be needed for further reductions in the future burden of breast cancer.</p></sec></body><back><sec><title>FUNDING SOURCES</title><p>Prepared under contract from the American Cancer Society Project #NHSURVGDO. The authors (except Ahemdin Jemal) are also supported in part by the National Institutes of Health, National Cancer Institute (grant numbers U01CA152958 and U01CA088283; grant number KO5CA96940 [to Jeanne Mandelblatt]); grant number P01CA154292) and the Department of Defense (grant #BC043120 [to Jeanne Mandelblatt]).</p></sec><sec><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST DISCLOSURES</title><p>The authors made no disclosures.</p></sec><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Plevritis</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of screening and adjuvant therapy on mortality from breast cancer</article-title><source>New Engl J Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16251534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Naishadham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2012</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2012</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22237781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargis</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollis</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between toxicity and obesity in women receiving adjuvant chemotherapy for breast cancer: results from cancer and leukemia group B study 8541</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>3000</fpage><lpage>3008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8918498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorin</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delays in breast cancer diagnosis and treatment by racial/ethnic group</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>2244</fpage><lpage>2252</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17101943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griggs</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorbero</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyman</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Undertreatment of obese women receiving breast cancer chemotherapy</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2005</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>1267</fpage><lpage>1273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15956006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colleoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relation between chemotherapy dose, oestrogen receptor expression, and body-mass index</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2005</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1108</fpage><lpage>1110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16182899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Brandt</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Spiegelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaun</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pooled analysis of prospective cohort studies on height, weight, and breast cancer risk</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>527</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10997541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Obesity and breast cancer: a review of the literature</article-title><source>Breast</source><year>2004</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15019686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vona-Davis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of socioeconomic disparities on breast cancer tumor biology and prognosis: a review</article-title><source>J Womens Health (Larchmt)</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>893</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19514831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Plevritis</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative review of CISNET breast models used to analyze U.S. breast cancer incidence and mortality trends</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>96</fpage><lpage>105</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>van Oortmarssen</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Habbema</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The MISCAN-Fadia continuous tumor growth model for breast cancer</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032895</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelblatt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SPECTRUM population model of the impact of screening and treatment on U.S. breast cancer trends from 1975 to 2000</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelblatt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of mammography screening under different screening schedules: model estimates of potential benefits and harms</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>738</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19920274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Near</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Race-specific impact of natural history, mammography screening, and adjuvant treatment on breast cancer mortality rates in the United States</article-title><source>Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Schechter</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Collaborative modeling of the impact of obesity on race-specific breast cancer incidence and mortality</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2012</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23104221</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Cancer Society</collab><source>Cancer Prevention &#x00026; Early Detection Facts &#x00026; Figures</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc><publisher-name>American Cancer Society, Inc</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancer.org/acs/groups/content/@epidemiologysurveilance/documents/document/acspc-033423.pdf">http://www.cancer.org/acs/groups/content/@epidemiologysurveilance/documents/document/acspc-033423.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed October 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>CISNET Cancer Intervention and Surveillance Modeling Network</collab><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cisnet.cancer.gov">http://cisnet.cancer.gov</ext-link>. Accessed May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>National Comprehensive Cancer Network</collab><comment>NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology v.2.2008. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nccn.org/professional/physician_gls/f_guidelines.asp">http://www.nccn.org/professional/physician_gls/f_guidelines.asp</ext-link>. Accessed September 2009</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Haines</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Historical Statistics of the United States, Volume One</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Population. New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</collab><source>National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS). National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey Data</source><publisher-loc>Hyattsville, MD</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, CDC</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www/cdc/gov/nchs/nhanes.htm">http://www/cdc/gov/nchs/nhanes.htm</ext-link>. Accessed May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Graubard</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Derivation of background mortality by smoking and obesity in cancer stimulation models</article-title><source>Med Decis Making</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23132901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Colditz</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuntz</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forecasting the obesity epidemic in the aging U.S</article-title><source>population. Obesity</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2855</fpage><lpage>2865</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Beydoun</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The obesity epidemic in the United States--gender, age, socioeconomic, racial/ethnic, and geographic characteristics: a systematic review and meta-regression analysis</article-title><source>Epidemiol Rev</source><year>2007</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flegal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of obesity and trends in the distribution of body mass index among US adults, 1999-2010</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2012</year><volume>307</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>497</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holford</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing patterns in breast cancer incidence trends</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Additional common inputs for analyzing impact of adjuvant therapy and mammography on U.S. mortality</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032891</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Krapcho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Modeling the dissemination of mammography in the United States</article-title><source>Cancer Causes Control</source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16049809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jatoi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shriver</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body mass index and use of mammography screening in the United States</article-title><source>Prev Med</source><year>2006</year><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16516284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><collab>Breast Cancer Surveillance Consortium</collab><comment>Performance Measures for 3,884,059 Screening Mammography Examinations from 1996 to 2007 by Age&#x02014; based on BCSC data as of 2008. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/data/performance/screening/2008/perf_age.html">http://breastscreening.cancer.gov/data/performance/screening/2008/perf_age.html</ext-link>. Accessed April 2008</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altekruse</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosary</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krapcho</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Neyman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Aminou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldron</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><comment>SEER Cancer Statistics Review, 1975-2007, National Cancer Institute. Bethesda, MD. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975-2007/">http://seer.cancer.gov/csr/1975-2007/</ext-link>. Accessed January 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whiteman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Flaws</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Body mass and stage of breast cancer at diagnosis</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2002</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11857420</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Selvan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with advanced disease stage at diagnosis in a population-based study of patients with newly diagnosed breast cancer</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17690220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bekele</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieto-Barajas</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsell</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of partially incomplete tables of breast cancer patients' characteristics with an ordinal variable</article-title><source>J Stat Theory Pract</source><year>2012</year><comment>[in press]</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Orsini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Key</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Body weight and incidence of breast cancer defined by estrogen and progesterone receptor status&#x02014;a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>712</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18988226</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlan</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissemination of adjuvant multiagent chemotherapy and tamoxifen for breast cancer in the United States using estrogen receptor information: 1975-1999</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mariotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Feuer</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlan</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wun</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Abrams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in use of adjuvant multi-agent chemotherapy and tamoxifen for breast cancer in the United States: 1975-1999</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2002</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>1626</fpage><lpage>1634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12419789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Early Breast Cancer Trialists' Collaborative Group (EBCTCG)</collab><article-title>Effects of chemotherapy and hormonal therapy for early breast cancer on recurrence and 15-year survival: an overview of the randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2005</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>1687</fpage><lpage>717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15894097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Early Breast Cancer Trialists' Collaborative Group (EBCTCG)</collab><article-title>Polychemotherapy for early breast cancer: an overview of the randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1998</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>930</fpage><lpage>942</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9752815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Early Breast Cancer Trialists' Collaborative Group (EBCTCG)</collab><article-title>Tamoxifen for early breast cancer: an overview of the randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1998</year><volume>351</volume><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1467</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9605801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Darby</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adjuvant chemotherapy in oestrogen-receptor-poor breast cancer: patient-level meta-analysis of randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2008</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18177773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>National Center for Health Statistics. United States, 2000</collab><year>2000</year><publisher-loc>Hyattsville, Maryland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Public Health Service</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/life_tables.htm">http://www.cdc.gov/nchs/products/life_tables.htm</ext-link>. Accessed May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Human Mortality Database, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Publications and Information Products, Life Tables 2011. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mortality.org">http://www.mortality.org</ext-link>. Accessed May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Competing risks to breast cancer mortality</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst Monogr</source><year>2006</year><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17032889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Projected population by single year of age, sex, race, and hispanic origin for the United States: July 1, 2000 to July 1, 2050. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.census.gov/population/www/projections/downloadableflies.html">http://www.census.gov/population/www/projections/downloadableflies.html</ext-link>. Accessed May 2012</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hershman</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushi</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early discontinuation and non-adherence to adjuvant hormonal therapy are associated with increased mortality in women with breast cancer</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2011</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20803066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigertz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlgren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmqvist</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence and discontinuation of adjuvant hormonal therapy in breast cancer patients: a population-based study</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2012</year><volume>133</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22286315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayanian</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of cost sharing on screening mammography in Medicare health plans</article-title><source>New Engl J Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>358</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18216358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vernon</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>McQueen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiro</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>del Junco</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventions to promote repeat breast cancer screening with mammography: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2010</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1023</fpage><lpage>1039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20587790</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Welch</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of three decades of screening mammogrpahy on breast cancer incidence</article-title><source>New Engl J Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>1998</fpage><lpage>2005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Gelder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Heijnsdijk</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ravesteyn</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Fracheboud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Draisma</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Koning</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interpreting overdiagnosis estimates in population-based mammography screening</article-title><source>Epidemiol Rev</source><year>2011</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21709144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><label>51</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandelblatt</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Trentham-Dietz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>To screen or not to screen women in their 40s for breast cancer: is personalized risk-based screening the answer?</article-title><source>Ann Internal Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21727294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b52"><label>52</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmore</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reisch</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of breast cancer screening in the community according to risk level</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source><year>2005</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>1035</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16030301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b53"><label>53</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>Energy balance and cancer prognosis. In: McTiernan A. Mechanisms Associating Physical Activity With Cancer Incidence: Exercise and Immune Function</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Boca Raton, FL</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group, LLC</publisher-name><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>436</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b54"><label>54</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonomi</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fishman</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality of life valuations of mammography screening</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>801</fpage><lpage>814</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18491217</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>