<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-MED</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17114082</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1805061</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">CI69015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2006.9015</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">jCI.v6.i2.pg82</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="other">ci069015</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>PET: other thoracic malignancies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quint</surname><given-names>Leslie E</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">* </xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">* Department of Radiology, University of Michigan Health System, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA.</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding address: Leslie E Quint, MD, Department of Radiology, University of Michigan Health System, Ann Arbor, Michigan, USA. Email: <email>lequint@med.umich.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2006</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>Spec No A</issue><fpage>S82</fpage><lpage>S88</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2006 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract><p>The vast majority of esophageal cancers are fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) avid; the primary use for positron emission tomography (PET) in patients with esophageal cancer is in the detection of distant metastases, because known distant metastatic disease precludes surgical resection. High standardized uptake values (SUVs) may be predictive of poor prognosis. PET findings may be used to assess therapy response and evaluate for esophageal tumor recurrence after treatment. PET findings may be non-specific in different types of thymic lesions, although thymic carcinomas tend to be extremely FDG avid. PET can be helpful in detecting distant spread from invasive thymomas and thymic carcinomas. Similarly, PET may be used to assess the extent of disease in patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma, thereby facilitating optimal therapy approaches. 
</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Positron emission tomography (PET)</kwd><kwd>fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG)</kwd><kwd>primary thoracic malignancy</kwd><kwd>standardized uptake value</kwd><kwd>therapy response</kwd><kwd>tumor recurrence</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type=""><title>Introduction</title><p>Preliminary studies suggest that PET scanning is useful in evaluating patients with primary thoracic malignancies other than lung cancer. Most published work pertains to esophageal cancer, although there is some data with regard to PET findings in thymic disorders and malignant pleural mesothelioma.
</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Esophageal cancer</title><sec><title>Primary esophageal cancer</title><sec><title>Staging</title><p>Approximately 90&#x02013;100&#x00025; of primary esophageal cancers have been reported to be fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) avid at positron emission tomography (PET) scanning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. False negative cases occasionally occur, predominantly if the tumor is small and confined to the mucosa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>]. Conversely, PET may be falsely positive in areas of inflamed esophageal wall or even in regions of normal esophagus or gastroesophageal junction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>]. Due to the poor spatial resolution of the technique (approximately 7&#x02013;8 mm), PET is not useful in gauging the depth of tumor invasion and thus in determining the T stage or in diagnosing or excluding tumor involvement of regional lymph nodes adjacent to the primary tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. The dominant use for PET in patients with esophageal cancer is in the detection of distant lymph node disease (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2 F3">Figs. 2 and 3</xref>) and other distant metastases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>); published reports have shown approximately 70&#x02013;90&#x00025; sensitivity, 90&#x00025; specificity, and 85&#x02013;90&#x00025; accuracy in this setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>]. One small study found osseous metastases that were detected on PET but missed using bone scintigraphy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>]. The major pitfall of PET in evaluating for distant metastases is lack of sensitivity in detecting very small lesions, due to limited spatial resolution. Despite that limitation, according to published reports, PET detects previously unsuspected distant disease in approximately 10&#x02013;30&#x00025; of patients, thereby preventing unindicated surgery in a substantial number of patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>]. 
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Primary distal esophageal adenocarcinoma (white arrow) with adjacent, regional lymph node metastases (black arrow) on CT (a). Lymph node metastases are indistinguishable from the adjacent primary tumor on PET images (black arrow, b and c). 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008201"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Primary distal esophageal adenocarcinoma with regional and distant lymph node metastases. CT shows thickening of the distal esophagus (white arrow) with adjacent enlarged, regional lymph nodes (black arrow) (a) and a small lymph node adjacent to the superior mesenteric artery (distant lymph node) (blue arrow, b). FDG uptake is seen not only within the primary tumor and adjacent lymph nodes (black arrow, c and e), but also within the small distant lymph node (blue arrow, d) on the fused PET-CT images; distant lymph node disease contraindicated surgical resection. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008202"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>PET scan shows FDG avid primary distal esophageal adenocarcinoma (red arrow). Uptake within a left supraclavicular lymph node (black arrow) represents a distant lymph node metastasis, indicating unresectable disease. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008203"/></fig>
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>PET scan shows FDG avid distal esophageal adenocarcinoma (arrow, a) with previously occult distant metastasis to vertebral body (arrow, b), not visible at CT (c). 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008204"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec><title>Standardized uptake values (SUVs)</title><p>Some published reports have suggested that high SUVs of the primary tumor are predictive of poor survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>]. One report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>] postulates that this is because patients with tumors showing high SUV generally have metastatic disease, and therefore the tumors are not resected. On the other hand, tumors with low SUV tend to be localized and do undergo resection; increased survival in this group may be due to surgery, rather than related to the low metabolic rate of the primary neoplasm. In the study of Hong <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>], baseline SUVs (before treatment) did not correlate with overall survival or disease free survival in 47 patients, all of whom underwent neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy followed by surgery.
</p></sec><sec><title>Radiation therapy planning</title><p>One recent study evaluated the impact of PET findings on radiation therapy treatment planning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>]. These authors found that PET information, co-registered with treatment planning computed tomography (CT), led to substantial increase or decrease in the estimated gross tumor volume (GTV) in 6 of 34 patients. Overall, modifications of the GTV changed the treatment plan in 18 of 34 patients, and affected the percentage of total lung volume receiving &#x0003e;20 Gy in 25 of 34
patients.
</p></sec><sec><title>Evaluating response to therapy</title><p>Small published studies have indicated that resolution of PET abnormalities or decrease in SUV following neoadjuvant chemotherapy, with or without concurrent radiation therapy, correlates well with pathological response and with disease free survival and overall survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>]. Furthermore, PET scanning during administration of therapy has the potential to differentiate non-responders from responders, thereby minimizing the toxicity of therapy and directing non-responders towards alternative therapies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>]. However, Song and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>] reported that metabolic response after neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy correlated with pathologic response only in tumors with an initially high SUV (<inline-formula><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} 
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath} 
\usepackage{amsfonts,amssymb,amsbsy} 
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal} 
\usepackage{mathrsfs} 
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{} 
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}{&#x0003c;-&#x0003e; linotext}{} 
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} 
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext} 
\begin{document} 
$\geq $ 
\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> 4); this relationship was not observed in tumors with an initially low SUV (&#x0003c;4).
</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison between PET and other modalities</title><p>A cost effectiveness study comparing CT, endoscopic ultrasound with fine needle aspiration biopsy (EUS-FNA), PET and thoracoscopy/laparoscopy in patients with esophageal cancer found that the combination of CT and EUS-FNA was the most inexpensive strategy and offered more quality adjusted life-years, on average, than all other strategies except for PET and EUS-FNA. The latter strategy, although slightly more effective, was also more expensive. The authors recommended use of PET and EUS-FNA unless resources are scarce or PET is unavailable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>].
</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Recurrent esophageal cancer</title><p>There is some evidence suggesting that PET is helpful in evaluating for recurrent esophageal cancer, after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>]. PET may help to support or negate the suspicion for malignancy in areas of CT abnormality (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>), may detect additional, previously unsuspected sites of disease, and may assist in locating the easiest site to biopsy, in order to prove recurrence of cancer. False positive scans sometimes occur in tissue with an active inflammatory component, for example related to post-operative healing or benign anastomotic strictures. 
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>FDG avid, peri-anastomotic recurrent esophageal carcinoma (arrow) at PET (a) and CT (b), 4 years following esophagectomy and gastric pull through. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008205"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Thymic lesions</title><p>Thymic lesions, including hyperplasia, thymoma, carcinoid, thymic carcinoma, lymphoma, and germ cell tumors, are frequently FDG avid, and therefore PET may be useful in differentiating between the normal and the abnormal thymus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>]. However, increased thymic uptake may occur in children and young adults without thymic disease, and this is particularly problematic in assessing for lymphomatous involvement of the thymus in patients with a history of lymphoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>]. Other FDG avid benign entities, such as thymic sarcoidosis, may also be seen occasionally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>]. Although it has been suggested that thymic carcinomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) tend to show higher SUVs compared to thymomas (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) and thymic hyperplasia, the latter two entities occasionally also show intense uptake [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>]; therefore, PET is generally unhelpful in distinguishing among these entities. However, if distant foci are identified at PET, then invasive thymoma or carcinoma is suspected. PET has also occasionally been used to evaluate for recurrent thymic neoplasm after resection or chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>]. 
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Small cell carcinoma of the thymus (arrow) shown on CT (a), fused PET-CT image (b) and frontal PET image (c). The cancer is extremely FDG avid. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008206"/></fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Minimally invasive thymoma (arrow) on CT (a) and PET (b). The tumor is moderately FDG avid (first published as Fig. 12 in Cancer Imaging 2005; 5: 139&#x02013;149). 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008207"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Malignant pleural mesothelioma</title><p>FDG PET is helpful in distinguishing benign from malignant pleural diseases, although not infallible. Empyemas and inflammatory processes (including pleural reaction after talc pleurodesis) may be extremely FDG avid, and falsely positive at PET scanning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>]. False negative cases may occur with small and/or low grade pleural malignancies; a case of an FDG negative, slowly growing malignant fibrous tumor of the pleura is reported in the imaging literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>]. In a patient with suspected malignant pleural mesothelioma (MPM), PET may be used to select the location with the highest metabolic activity for tissue sampling.</p><p>MPM may be treated with extrapleural pneumonectomy, chemotherapy and/or radiation therapy. The tumor is generally considered unresectable if there is evidence of tumor spread to mediastinal lymph nodes or direct spread to the upper abdomen; extensive/diffuse chest wall involvement and distant metastases would also preclude resection. Approximately one-quarter of patients with MPM have unresectable disease at exploratory thoracotomy, after preoperative imaging with conventional modalities such as CT or magnetic resonance (MR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>]. Preliminary reports suggest that preoperative FDG PET is superior to CT and MR in staging the tumor, and may show additional sites of disease that are not evident on conventional imaging, thus precluding unnecessary surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>]. The limited spatial resolution of PET, however, leads to difficulty in distinguishing pleural disease from possible adjacent disease in or below the diaphragm or in the mediastinum or chest wall (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>). 
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Malignant pleural mesothelioma. Right pleural thickening on CT (white arrow, a) that shows FDG avidity on the corresponding axial PET image (black arrow, b). The frontal, projection PET image shows ill defined, poorly localized activity in the region of the diaphragm (white arrow, c). Exploratory laparatomy revealed a small tumor implant on the peritoneal surface of the diaphragm, contraindicating full surgical resection. 
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci06008208"/></fig></p><p>Preliminary studies suggest that high SUV in primary MPMs is associated with poor survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>]. Other uses for PET scanning in MPM include evaluating for therapy response and for recurrence after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>].
</p></sec><sec sec-type=""><title>Conclusions</title><p>The use of FDG PET scanning in the evaluation of patients with non-lung primary thoracic neoplasms is becoming increasingly common. There is a growing body of data suggesting that PET is helpful in patients with new, treated or recurrent esophageal cancer. In addition, preliminary reports suggest that PET may also add useful information in patients with thymic lesions and known or suspected MPM.
</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="b1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skehan</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahmias</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging features of primary and recurrent esophageal cancer at FDG PET</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10835124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Himeno</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Makuuchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of esophageal cancer by positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Booya</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison of positron emission tomography, computed tomography, and endoscopic ultrasound in the initial staging of patients with esophageal cancer</article-title><source>Mol Imaging Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>422</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16270235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meltzer</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Luketich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole-body FDG positron emission tomographic imaging for staging esophageal cancer: comparison with computed tomography</article-title><source>Clin Nucl Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>882</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11079584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metastasis to regional lymph nodes in patients with esophageal squamous cell carcinoma: CT versus FDG PET for presurgical detection prospective study</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2003</year><volume>227</volume><fpage>764</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12773680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lerut</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Flamen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ectors</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Histopathologic validation of lymph node staging with FDG-PET scan in cancer of the esophagus and gastroesophageal junction: a prospective study based on primary surgery with extensive lymphadenectomy</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11088069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparison between whole-body positron emission tomography and bone scintigraphy in evaluating bony metastases of esophageal carcinomas</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>4439</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16334123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blackstock</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovato</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A prospective evaluation of the impact of 18-F-fluoro-deoxy-D-glucose positron emission tomography staging on survival for patients with locally advanced esophageal cancer</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2006</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16213103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fukunaga</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazumi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Koide</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Isono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imazeki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of esophageal cancers using fluorine-18-fluorodeoxyglucose PET</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1998</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1002</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9627333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Westreenen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Plukker</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobben</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhoogt</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of the standardized uptake value in esophageal cancer</article-title><source>Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2005</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>436</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16037517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunagomez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Value of baseline positron emission tomography for predicting overall survival in patient with nonmetastatic esophageal or gastroesophageal junction carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1620</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16118804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moureau-Zabotto</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Touboul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerouge</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of CT and 18F-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography image fusion for conformal radiotherapy in esophageal carcinoma</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2005</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16168829</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westerterp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van Westreenen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Esophageal cancer: CT, endoscopic US, and FDG PET for assessment of response to neoadjuvant therapy&#x02014;systematic review</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2005</year><volume>236</volume><fpage>841</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16118165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forshaw</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gossage</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neoadjuvant chemotherapy for oesophageal cancer: the need for accurate response prediction and evaluation</article-title><source>Surgeon</source><year>2005</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>82, 422</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16353857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerfolio</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohja</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartolucci</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eloubeidi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The accuracy of endoscopic ultrasonography with fine-needle aspiration, integrated positron emission tomography with computed tomography, and computed tomography in restaging patients with esophageal cancer after neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1232</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15942562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>FDG-PET in the prediction of pathologic response after neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy in locally advanced, resectable esophageal cancer</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2005</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15964705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nietert</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Earle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An analysis of multiple staging management strategies for carcinoma of the esophagus: computed tomography, endoscopic ultrasound, positron emission tomography, and thoracoscopy/laparoscopy</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1026</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12400740</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flamen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Cutsem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The utility of positron emission tomography for the diagnosis and staging of recurrent esophageal cancer</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1085</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11088030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwabara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ichiya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential diagnosis of thymic tumors using a combination of 11C-methionine PET and FDG PET</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>1595</fpage><lpage>601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10520697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferdinand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrum of thymic uptake at 18F-FDG PET</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2004</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1611</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15537971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wittram</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shepard</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thymic enlargement and FDG uptake in three patients: CT and FDG positron emission tomography correlated with pathology</article-title><source>Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2003</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12540464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karapetis</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Strickland</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yip</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Steer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography scans in patients with advanced germ cell tumour following chemotherapy: single-centre experience with long-term follow up</article-title><source>Intern Med J</source><year>2003</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14511195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Godart</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Weynand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Coche</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Nayer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Daumerie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intense 18-fluorodeoxyglucose uptake by the thymus on PET scan does not necessarily herald recurrence of thyroid carcinoma</article-title><source>J Endocrinol Invest</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1024</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16483183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Markou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bomanji</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>18F]Fluoro-2-deoxy-D-glucose ([18F]FDG) positron emission tomography imaging of thymic carcinoid tumor presenting with recurrent Cushing&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source>Eur J Endocrinol</source><year>2005</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15817906</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwek</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Aquino</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography and CT after talc pleurodesis</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>2004</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>2356</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15189963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Slebos</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PET for the evaluation of pleural thickening observed on CT</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15181135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of PET in the surgical management of malignant pleural mesothelioma</article-title><source>Lung Cancer</source><year>2005</year><volume>49</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>S27</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15950796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ambrosini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubello</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Additional value of hybrid PET/CT fusion imaging vs. conventional CT scan alone in the staging and management of patients with malignant pleural mesothelioma</article-title><source>Nucl Med Rev Cent East Eur</source><year>2005</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16437396</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated computed tomography-positron emission tomography in patients with potentially resectable malignant pleural mesothelioma: staging implications</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1364</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15942579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nanni</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Castellucci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Farsad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of 18F-FDG PET for evaluating malignant pleural mesothelioma</article-title><source>Cancer Biother Radiopharm</source><year>2004</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15186594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerbaudo</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>18F-FDG imaging of malignant pleural mesothelioma: scientiam impendere vero</article-title><source>Nucl Med Commun</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12766595</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>