<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4242760</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1470-7330-14-S1-O2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1470-7330-14-S1-O2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oral Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Challenges of cancer imaging in Africa</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Lockhat</surname><given-names>Zarina I</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>van Rensburg</surname><given-names>Leon J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>du Toit</surname><given-names>Hanlie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Radiology, University of Pretoria, South Africa</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Radiology and Diagnostics, University of Western Cape, South Africa</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Drs SCP Inc, Diagnostic Radiologists, Cape Town, South Africa</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Clinical and Radiation Oncology, VI Oncology, Cape Town, South Africa</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">Proceedings of the International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication charges for this supplement were funded through the International Cancer Imaging Society by support received from Siemens AG, Healthcare Sector, Imaging and Therapy Division.</named-content></supplement><fpage>O2</fpage><lpage>O2</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Lockhat et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Lockhat et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cancerimagingjournal.com/content/14/S1/O2"/><conference><conf-date>9-11 October 2014</conf-date><conf-name>International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</conf-name><conf-loc>Heidelberg, Germany</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title/><p>Africa as a continent is subdivided into different regions, Northern, Eastern, Western, Middle and Southern Africa. Sub-Saharan Africa refers to the combined Eastern, Middle, Southern, and Western regions. These subdivisions are important as the disease and cancer spectrum found in specific regions is quite different. Similar to the differences found between Africa and the developed world, cancer incidence and mortality patterns vary remarkably across regions within Africa because of the substantial differences in economic development, and social, cultural and other environmental factors, including major known risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].The occurrence of cancer in Africa varies remarkably by type of major cancer, stage at diagnosis, survival, incidence and mortality rates. This is largely due to differences in exposure to major risk factors, detection practices (availability of diagnostic and screening services), awareness of early signs and symptoms, and availability of treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>].</p><p>The cancer burden of each region will be discussed and some of the factors related to cancer imaging and the challenges faced will be highlighted.</p><p>Recent statistics and data for some parts of Africa are lacking, relatively representative in other parts, however more available for sub-Saharan Africa, which will probably be the greater focus of the discussion.</p><p>There are many significant global organisations that are constantly working to alleviate the cancer burden, and conduct research. There is significant vendor interest and investment in imaging equipment, and therapeutic modalities in scattered parts of Africa, although more focused in certain parts of Africa.</p><p>There is major local and international focus in establishing cancer centres in Africa, yet the predicted increase in the cancer burden, is phenomenal.</p><p>Collaborative and novel solutions are being explored through initiatives that involve international, regional and local organisations. These programmes include the procurement, installation, and maintenance of diagnostic and therapeutic imaging equipment.</p><p>There is much to be done, in the realm of screening, diagnosis, training, teaching, treatment and research, and this has to be an on-going, focused, enthusiastic effort by all countries in sub-Saharan Africa, the entire continent of Africa and key global cancer bodies. Much has been done in the last few years however much more still has to be done. As Victor Kgomoeswana highlights in his book &#x0201c;Africa is open for business&#x0201d;, Africa needs investment.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>American Cancer Society</collab><source>Global CancerFacts and Figures</source><year>2011</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Atlanta: American Cancer Society</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>