<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4601756</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1470-7330-15-S1-P2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1470-7330-15-S1-P2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Poster Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Contrast enhancement for early cancer imaging by Gd-nanoparticles and active feedback MRI</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sayoni@chem.ucla.edu</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>F-C</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y-Y</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Chemistry of Biochemistry, University Of California, Los Angeles, 607 Charles E. Young Drive East, Los Angeles, CA 90095-1569, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">Proceedings of the International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 15th Annual Teaching Course</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication charges for this supplement were funded through the International Cancer Imaging Society by support received from Siemens Healthcare GmbH.</named-content></supplement><fpage>P2</fpage><lpage>P2</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2015 Ray et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ray et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cancerimagingjournal.com/content/15/S1/P2"/><conference><conf-date>5-7 October 2015</conf-date><conf-name>International Cancer Imaging Society Meeting and 15th Annual Teaching Course (ICIS 2015)</conf-name><conf-loc>London, UK</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Aim</title><p>Early detection of high-grade malignancy using enhanced MRI techniques significantly increases not only the treatment options available, but also the patients&#x02019; survival rate. For this purpose, we have developed a new method, termed &#x0201c;Active-Feedback MRI&#x0201d;. An active feedback electronic device was homebuilt to implement active-feedback pulse sequences to generate avalanching spin amplification, which enhances the weak field originated from T<sub>1</sub> contrast agents such as Gd-nanoparticles that target and label the cancer cells.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The general principles of the &#x0201c;Active-Feedback MRI&#x0201d; can be found in our previous work (e.g., Science 290, 118, 2001). Here, its specific applications to image Gd-nanoparticles in early cancers were developed and demonstrated. (i) First, an active-feedback electronic device was home-built to generate feedback fields from the received FID current. The device is to filter, phase shift, and amplify the signal from the receiver coils and then retransmit the modified signal into the RF transmission coil, with adjustable and programmable feedback phases and gains. (ii) Next, an active-feedback pulse sequence was developed to enhance the contrast originated from local magnetic-field gradient variations due to Gd-nanoparticles.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p><italic>In vivo</italic> subcutaneous glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and cervical cancer mice models were imaged. While T<sub>2</sub> parameter images, T<sub>2</sub>-weighted images, and T<sub>1</sub>-Gd-weighted images could not clearly locate the early cancers, our active-feedback images and decay constant mapping successfully highlight the early cancers with a close correlation with histopathology. Statistical results show that this new approach provides significant improvements in cancer detection sensitivity, as measured by &#x0201c;contrast-to-noise ratio&#x0201d; (CNR) or &#x0201c;Visibility&#x0201d;.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p><italic>In vivo</italic> subcutaneous xenografts GBM and cervical cancer mouse models validated the superior contrast/sensitivity and robustness of this approach towards early cancer detection. Spin dynamics and results from computer simulations will also be discussed.</p></sec></body></article>