<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Immunol Immunother</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Immunol. Immunother</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Immunology, Immunotherapy</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0340-7004</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-0851</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22350070</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3410973</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-012-1217-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>TCR hypervariable regions expressed by T cells that respond to effective tumor vaccines</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>Kimberly R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Buhrman</surname><given-names>Jonathan D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sprague</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Brandon L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Dexiang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>John W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>Jill E.</given-names></name><address><phone>+303-398-1887</phone><fax>+303-398-1396</fax><email>Jill.Slansky@ucdenver.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Integrated Department of Immunology, School of Medicine, University of Colorado Denver, 1400 Jackson Street, Room K511, Denver, CO 80206 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>School of Public Health, University of Colorado Denver, Denver, CO 80045 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, National Jewish Health, Denver, CO 80206 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>61</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1627</fpage><lpage>1638</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2012</copyright-statement></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>A major goal of immunotherapy for cancer is the activation of T cell responses against tumor-associated antigens (TAAs). One important strategy for improving antitumor immunity is vaccination with peptide variants of TAAs. Understanding the mechanisms underlying the expansion of T cells that respond to the native tumor antigen is an important step in developing effective peptide-variant vaccines. Using an immunogenic mouse colon cancer model, we compare the binding properties and the TCR genes expressed by T cells elicited by peptide variants that elicit variable antitumor immunity directly ex vivo. The steady-state affinity of the natural tumor antigen for the T cells responding to effective peptide vaccines was higher relative to ineffective peptides, consistent with their improved function. Ex vivo analysis showed that T cells responding to the effective peptides expressed a CDR3&#x003b2; motif, which was also shared by T cells responding to the natural antigen and not those responding to the less effective peptide vaccines. Importantly, these data demonstrate that peptide vaccines can expand T cells that naturally respond to tumor antigens, resulting in more effective antitumor immunity. Future immunotherapies may require similar stringent analysis of the responding T cells to select optimal peptides as vaccine candidates.</p><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00262-012-1217-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Peptide vaccines</kwd><kwd>T cell repertoire</kwd><kwd>Tumor antigens</kwd><kwd>Peptide variants</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg 2012</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Increased frequencies of cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs), which recognize antigenic peptides from tumors presented by major histocompatibility (MHC) class I molecules, correlate with improved cancer patient survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. CTLs and the effector molecules they produce are critical in the elimination of cancer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]; however, they are also subject to regulatory mechanisms. Tumor-specific CTLs often recognize peptides derived from tumor-associated antigens (TAAs). One important strategy for improving antitumor immunity and overcoming these self-tolerance mechanisms is vaccination with peptide variants of TAAs (also known as mimotopes, heteroclitic peptides, peptide analogues, or altered peptide ligands) that improve binding to either MHC molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] or tumor-specific T cell receptor (TCR) molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. These vaccines stimulate the expansion of the often low-affinity TAA-specific T cells that escape negative selection during development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] and are suboptimally activated by native tumor antigens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Clinical trials have shown increased frequencies of TAA-specific T cells following vaccination with peptide variants, demonstrating the potential of antigen-specific immunotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p>Peptide variants are most often selected as vaccine candidates because they bind with stronger affinity or stimulate TAA-specific T cells more effectively than the native tumor antigen in vitro. Paradoxically, vaccination with these variants often elicits T cells with diminished antitumor activity relative to T cells that naturally respond to native tumor antigens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Using the CT26 transplantable tumor model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], we previously showed that vaccination with variants of the immunodominant peptide, gp70<sub>423&#x02013;431</sub> (AH1), elicited variable antitumor immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These peptides robustly stimulated the tumor-specific T cell clone used to identify the variants and elicited more tumor-specific T cells from the endogenous repertoire of BALB/c mice than the native AH1 peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. However, vaccination with these peptides elicited a range of antitumor immunity. The ineffective peptides elicited T cells that failed to kill AH1-loaded target cells or produce IFN&#x003b3; after stimulation with the native tumor antigen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Surprisingly, these functionally deficient T cells produced IFN&#x003b3; after stimulation with the variant peptide used in the vaccine, suggesting that the ineffective peptide variants were not antagonists or partial agonists, as in other systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p>Understanding the mechanisms underlying the expansion of T cells that respond poorly to native tumor antigens is an important step in developing effective peptide-variant vaccines. The repertoire of T cells responding to peptide variants is often different than the repertoire of T cells responding to native tumor antigens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. As addressed in this study, we hypothesized that the effective peptide variants likely elicited a different repertoire of tumor-specific T cells that expressed TCRs with higher affinity for the native tumor antigen. Since in vitro expansion of tumor antigen-specific T cells can dramatically skew T cell cultures in favor of higher-affinity T cell clones [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], we compared the binding properties and the TCR genes expressed by T cells elicited by peptide variants directly ex vivo. The T cells elicited by an effective peptide-variant bound fluorescent MHC-tetramers containing the native tumor antigen with a higher staining intensity. These T cells did not cross-react with an ineffective peptide variant, suggesting that the repertoires of T cells responding to these variant vaccines were different and did not overlap. In addition, the effective peptide variants elicited a repertoire of T cells that was closely related in sequence to the T cells elicited by the native TAA, expressing a common J&#x003b2; sequence and a common CDR3&#x003b2; motif, and the frequency of sequences containing this CDR3&#x003b2; motif correlated with tumor protection. Thus, the effective peptide-variant vaccines enhanced the expansion of T cells that respond to the native TAA, rather than activating a new subset of T cells. Importantly, these results demonstrate that T cells responding to native tumor antigens can be effectively stimulated to prevent tumor growth, provided they are activated through the TCR by the appropriate signal. The implication of these results is that the most effective peptide vaccines may be identified by measuring the responses of tumor antigen-specific T cells found in patients, rather than isolated T cell clones.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Mice</title><p>Six- to eight-week-old female BALB/cAnNCr mice were purchased from the National Cancer Institute/Charles River Laboratories. All animal protocols were reviewed and approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of National Jewish Health.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Cells</title><p>Sf9 and High Five insect cells ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], Invitrogen) were cultured and infected as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. T cell clones were cultured as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The T cell lines were cloned by limiting dilution and expanded with 5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup>/ml irradiated CT26 tumor cells expressing the costimulatory molecule B7 for 2&#x000a0;weeks prior to flow cytometry and TCR sequence analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Peptides</title><p>&#x003b2;gal (TPHGAGRIL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]), AH1 (SPSYVYHQF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]), A5 (SPSYAYHQF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]), 39 (MNKYAYHML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]), 15 (MPKYAYHML [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]), WMF (SPTYAYWMF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]), and F1A5 (FPSYAYHQF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]) peptides were identified as described. Soluble synthetic peptides were &#x02265;95% pure (Chi Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="Sec50"><title>Vaccination</title><p>Sf9 insect cells were infected with recombinant baculovirus (BV) encoding L<sup>d</sup> and beta-2-microglobulin molecules covalently linked to peptides via a glycine-rich linker as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Antibodies and staining reagents</title><p>Preparation of the fluorescent L<sup>d</sup> tetramer linked to the AH1 peptide using a disulfide trap or loaded with exogenous AH1 peptide has been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Soluble TCRs containing CDR3&#x003b2; motifs were prepared by inserting V&#x003b2;8.3 and V&#x003b1;6 gene segments expressed by the A5-4E11 or 39-1D4 T cell clones into a BV expression vector [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Purified TCR molecules were conjugated to fluorescent streptavidin molecules as described and used to stain insect cells expressing membrane-bound peptide-MHC molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The median fluorescent intensity (MFI) of L<sup>d</sup> high cells was determined. Antibodies specific for the L<sup>d</sup> molecule (28.14.8S), CD8 (53&#x02013;6.7, Southern Biotech), IFN&#x003b3; (XMG1.2, eBioscience), B220 (RA3-6B2, BD Pharmigen), CD4 (RM4-5, BD Pharmigen), and MHC-II (M5/114.15.2, BD Pharmigen) were used for flow cytometric analyses. The B220, CD4, and MHC-II antibodies were analyzed in the &#x0201c;dump gate&#x0201d; for the tetramer, IFN&#x003b3;, and V&#x003b2; staining experiments. For costaining experiments, splenocytes from vaccinated mice were stained with L<sup>d</sup>-tet linked to the AH1 peptide with a disulfide trap and conjugated to steptavidin-PE for 2&#x000a0;h at 37&#x000b0;C to facilitate internalization and limit competition between tetramers and L<sup>d</sup>-tet linked to the F1A5 or WMF peptides conjugated to streptavidin-AF647 were added and stained for an additional 2&#x000a0;h at 4&#x000b0;C. All samples were run on a BD FACSCaliber flow cytometer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Intracellular cytokine staining</title><p>Splenocytes were stimulated with the indicated peptide for 5&#x000a0;h in the presence of monensin, a protein transport inhibitor (GolgiStop, BD Cytofix/Cytoperm Plus Fixation/Permeabilization Kit, BD Pharmingen), fixed, permeabilized, and stained as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec51"><title>Tetramer decay and titration</title><p>For the decay assay, 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> splenocytes were stained in 96-well plates with L<sup>d</sup>-tet loaded with the AH1 peptide for 1&#x000a0;h at RT. The AH1 tetramer with the disulfide trap was not used in these experiments because its fluorescence intensity is not reduced during the timeframe of this experiment. The cells were washed extensively and resuspended in FACS buffer (1x phosphate-buffered saline, 1&#x000d7; HEPES buffer, 0.1% sodium azide, 2% fetal bovine serum) and 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/ml F(ab)&#x02019; fragments of the L<sup>d</sup>-specific antibody (28.14.8S). Approximately 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> cells were removed at each time point and fixed in 1% paraformaldehyde. Total fluorescence (<italic>T</italic><sub>f</sub>) was determined using the following formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]:<disp-formula id="Equa"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$
\begin{aligned}
T_{\text{f}} =&#x00026; \left[ {\left( { {\text{\% of AH1-tet}}^{+}
{\text{of CD8}}^{+} {\text{ cells}}} \right)\left( {{\text{MFI of AH1-tet}}^{+} {\text{ population}}} \right)}
\right]_{\text{peptide\,vaccine}}\\&#x00026; -\left[ {\left( { {\text{\% of
 AH1-tet}}^{+} {\text{ of CD}}8^{+} {\text{ cells}}} \right)\left(
{{\text{MFI of AH1-tet}}^{+} {\text{ population}}} \right)}
\right]_{{\beta {\text{gal vaccine}}}}
\end{aligned}
$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Article_Equa.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>Normalized fluorescence (<italic>N</italic><sub>f</sub>) was calculated by dividing the <italic>T</italic><sub>f</sub> at each time point by the <italic>T</italic><sub>f</sub> at time 0. The natural log (ln) of the <italic>N</italic><sub>f</sub> was plotted versus time and the data for each mouse were fit to a one-phase exponential decay curve [(<italic>y</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<italic>y</italic>0*e(&#x02212;<italic>kt</italic>) where <italic>y</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;ln <italic>N</italic><sub>f</sub>, <italic>k</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;decay constant, and <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;time)] using Prism version 4.0, Graphpad software. The half-lives were calculated for each mouse [(half-life&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;ln(2)/<italic>k</italic>)] and compared using an unpaired two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test.</p><p>For the tetramer titration assay, splenocytes were stained as above for 2&#x000a0;h at 4&#x000b0;C. The MFI was calculated using the following formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]: MFI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;(<italic>T</italic><sub>f</sub>)/(% of AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> of CD8<sup>+</sup> cells). The MFI was plotted versus the concentration of tetramer and fit to a one-site binding curve [<italic>Y</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;(Bmax*<italic>X</italic>)/(<italic>K</italic><sub>D</sub>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;<italic>X</italic>)] using Prism version 4.0, Graphpad software. The <italic>K</italic><sub>D</sub> values for each mouse were compared using an unpaired two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>TCR sequencing</title><p>Approximately 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> splenocytes were separated with a MoFlo<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> High-Performance Cell Sorter. RNA was extracted using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen), and cDNA was synthesized using the QuantiTect Reverse Transcription Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. For the plasmid sequencing method, the cDNA was PCR-amplified using the primer sets described in Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Amplified DNA was cloned into the pCR2.1 vector using the TOPO TA Cloning Kit (Invitrogen), and sequences were determined using an internal C&#x003b2; primer (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1) and capillary DNA sequencing instruments (ABI 3730s). For the high-throughput method, the cDNA was PCR-amplified for 15 cycles using a forward primer specific for all V&#x003b2;8 family members containing an adaptor sequence (in bold) and an internal multiplex identifier (MID) sequence (in italics, Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1) and a reverse primer specific for C&#x003b2; containing a different adaptor sequence (in bold, Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1). PCR fragments were separated by gel electrophoresis, purified using the Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen), and further amplified 30 cycles using primers specific for the adaptor sequences. After gel extraction and quantification, the PCR products were combined and subjected to high-throughput sequencing as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Sequences from both methods were analyzed using a computer software program developed by our laboratory that uses a BLAST-type algorithm to identify V&#x003b2; and J&#x003b2; gene sequence information [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. This program translated and aligned the sequences, identified the MID sequences and sorted the results according to each vaccine, distinguished the germline-encoded and randomized CDR3&#x003b2; region of each sequence, calculated the length of each CDR3&#x003b2; region, and determined the number of sequences containing the shared CDR3&#x003b2; motif. The sequences of the TCRs expressed by the T cell clones (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) were determined by directly sequencing PCR products amplified from their cDNA using the V&#x003b2;8.3 and C&#x003b2; primers or V&#x003b1;6 primers.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Vaccination with the F1A5 peptide elicits T cells with higher affinity for the AH1 peptide</title><p>Previously identified peptide variants effectively stimulated a tumor antigen-specific T cell clone both in vitro and in vivo, but elicited variable antitumor responses from the endogenous T cell repertoire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Vaccination with the F1A5 peptide variant protected 90% of mice from tumor growth, while tumors grew in all of the mice vaccinated with the WMF peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The increased tumor protection afforded by the F1A5 peptide was attributed to the expansion of more tumor-specific T cells that exhibited effector function after stimulation with the AH1 peptide, although the mechanism for this differential expansion of functional T cells was not determined [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p>When factors such as CD8 and TCR expression levels are considered, the relative median fluorescence intensity (MFI) of multimerized peptide-MHC (tetramer) staining reflects the binding affinity of T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Although direct affinity measurements would be ideal, this cannot be performed with current technology on multiclonal T cells ex vivo. We hypothesized that the WMF peptide was less effective because the T cells responding to this vaccine bound to the AH1&#x02013;L<sup>d</sup> complex with lower affinity. Thus, we measured the MFI of tetramer staining of splenocytes from mice vaccinated with a previously described insect cell vaccine expressing either an effective (F1A5) or ineffective (WMF) variant peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. We detected differences in the relative MFI of the AH1-tetramer<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>ai). After normalizing for the differences in the number of AH1-specific T cells (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;1a), the F1A5-elicited T cells required a lower concentration of tetramer for half of the maximum number of tetramer<sup>+</sup> cells to bind the AH1-tetramer (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>aii). Using both the binding affinities and the EC<sub>50</sub> values from these data curves, we determined that the F1A5-elicited T cells have a higher affinity for the AH1 tumor antigen than the WMF-elicited T cells, consistent with our hypothesis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>aiii). These differences may be underestimated due to the limitations of analog instruments and the loss of linearity at higher fluorescence intensities. Due to the limited number of AH1-specific cells in AH1-vaccinated mice relative to background tetramer staining in &#x003b2;gal-vaccinated mice, we were not able to reliably determine the KD or EC<sub>50</sub> of tetramer binding for these cells (Supplemental Fig&#x000a0;1b).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>T cells elicited by peptide-variant vaccines have different affinity for the tumor antigen. <bold>a</bold> (<italic>i</italic>) Splenocytes from mice vaccinated with the indicated peptides were stained with antibodies specific for dump, CD8, and LFA-1 molecules and a titration of L<sup>d</sup>-tet loaded with the AH1 peptide. The MFI of AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> LFA-1<sup>+</sup> cells was graphed after subtracting the fluorescence of tetramer-binding cells in mice vaccinated with the irrelevant &#x003b2;gal peptide and fit to a one-site binding curve. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6 mice). Curves were compared using an <italic>F</italic> test (***<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). (<italic>ii</italic>) Cells from (<bold>a</bold>i) were graphed as a percentage of the maximum number of AH1-tet-binding cells at each concentration of tetramer and fit to a sigmoidal dose&#x02013;response curve. Curves were compared using an <italic>F</italic> test (***<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). (<italic>iii</italic>) K<sub>D</sub> and EC<sub>50</sub> values were determined for individual mice using one-site binding curves or sigmoidal dose&#x02013;response curves as in (<bold>a</bold>i) and (<bold>a</bold>ii) and compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (**<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.002, *<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0097, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6 mice). <bold>b</bold> Splenocytes from (<italic>i</italic>) F1A5- or (<italic>ii</italic>) WMF-vaccinated mice were stained as in (<bold>a</bold>). The total fluorescence of the dump<sup>&#x02212;</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> LFA-1<sup>+</sup> AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> cells was determined at the indicated time. The natural log (ln) of the normalized fluorescence was graphed and fit to an exponential decay curve. (<italic>iii</italic>) The half-life of AH1-tet staining (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>) was determined for each mouse and compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (n.s.&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;not significant)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig1_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>Since tetramer-dissociation rates correlate with peptide-MHC/TCR affinities in some systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], we measured the half-life (<italic>t</italic><sub>1/2</sub>) of tetramer binding to the responding T cell repertoire (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The average <italic>t</italic><sub>1/2</sub> of T cells from F1A5- and WMF-vaccinated mice was not statistically different (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>biii). Although many factors contribute to <italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> values calculated using multivalent interactions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], these observed avidity differences may be due to faster on-rates rather than longer half-lives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. In summary, the F1A5-elicited T cells bound to the AH1 antigen with increased affinity, which may explain the previously described improved effector function exhibited by T cells responding to this peptide vaccine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Few tumor-specific T cells cross-react with both the F1A5 and WMF peptides</title><p>Next, we determined the mechanism involved in the decreased affinity of the WMF-elicited T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and their decreased effector responses to the AH1 peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Diminished T cell responses may have been caused by incomplete activation of these cells or by the expansion of a different repertoire of T cells with lower affinity. To distinguish these possibilities, we determined whether the effective and ineffective peptide variants elicit overlapping repertoires of T cells. Splenocytes from vaccinated mice were co-stained with the AH1-tetramer and variant tetramers (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). It is intriguing that so few of these T cells cross-reacted with both peptide variants, since they were designed to stimulate the same AH1-specific T cell clone. However, even among the AH1-specific T cells expanded by the vaccines, few cells bound to both variant tetramers (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). Furthermore, the differences in the MFI of AH1-tetramer staining (described in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) were also detected in this experiment and are shown in the dot plots (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>The repertoire of T cells elicited by the variant peptides F1A5 and WMF is distinct and few cells overlap. <bold>a</bold> Splenocytes from mice vaccinated with the indicated peptide were stained and gated on CD8<sup>+</sup> dump<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells. Staining with the L<sup>d</sup>-tet linked to the AH1 peptide (<italic>y</italic>-axis) and L<sup>d</sup>-tet linked to the F1A5 or WMF peptides (<italic>x</italic>-axis) is shown. The <italic>dot plots</italic> are representative of 3 independent experiments. <bold>b</bold> Splenocytes from multiple mice were stained as in (<bold>a</bold>), and the percentage of tet<sup>+</sup> cells was determined by histogram analysis (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6 mice). <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the SEM, and groups were compared by an unpaired two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0002, **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001). <bold>c</bold> Splenocytes from (<bold>a</bold>) were assessed for intracellular IFN&#x003b3; production after stimulation with the indicated peptides by staining with antibodies specific for dump, CD8, and IFN&#x003b3; molecules. The events shown are representative dot plots of 2 independent experiments. <bold>d</bold> T cells from multiple mice were assessed for intracellular cytokine production as in (<bold>c</bold>) (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 mice). Although not shown in (<bold>c</bold>), IFN&#x003b3; production by splenocytes stimulated with the AH1 peptide was assessed using the same gating. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the SEM, and groups were compared by an unpaired two-tailed <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0017, **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig2_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p>In some systems, functional measurements more accurately assess the number of antigen-specific T cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. To ensure the tetramer-binding experiments did not underestimate the number of T cells that cross-react with both peptide variants, we analyzed intracellular IFN&#x003b3; production by splenocytes from vaccinated mice stimulated with either the F1A5 or the WMF peptides (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, d). Similar to the tetramer staining results, few T cells cross-reacted with both variant peptides. In addition, as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], few WMF-elicited T cells produced IFN&#x003b3; after stimulation with the AH1 peptide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>d). Together, these data suggest that vaccination with the F1A5 and WMF peptides elicited different portions of the endogenous AH1-specific T cell repertoire.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>F1A5 and WMF peptides elicit different repertoires of T cells</title><p>To directly characterize the TCR gene usage of the AH1-specific T cells elicited by the peptide variants, we co-stained splenocytes from vaccinated mice with the AH1-tetramer and a panel of antibodies to the mouse TCR V&#x003b2; genes (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;2a). In addition to the F1A5 and WMF peptides, we also analyzed the response to the native tumor antigen and to three other previously characterized peptide variants, 15 (ineffective), and A5 and 39 (effective) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. All of these peptide variants were also selected using the V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> CT T cell clone and, not surprisingly, they elicited AH1-specific T cells that predominantly expressed the V&#x003b2;8 family of TCRs (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;2b).</p><p>Since most of the T cells responding to these peptide vaccines expressed V&#x003b2;8 TCR genes, it was not clear whether the peptides elicited different repertoires of T cells. Thus, we analyzed the CDR3&#x003b2; and J&#x003b2; sequences expressed by AH1-specific T cells in mice vaccinated with the F1A5 and WMF peptides. The identified TCR sequences with in-frame gene rearrangements are listed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Nearly all of the T cells elicited by the F1A5 peptide expressed TCRs with the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment (97%), in contrast to the WMF-elicited TCR sequences that encoded several different J&#x003b2; gene segments (72% J&#x003b2;2.6). While there was some junctional diversity in the F1A5-elicited TCR sequences, we identified a shared three amino acid motif in the predicted CDR3&#x003b2; loop that was absent from the WMF-elicited TCR sequences. This CDR3&#x003b2; motif consisted of a glycine or alanine residue, followed by a large polar residue and the tyrosine residue of J&#x003b2;2.6 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The first two amino acids of the motif were not germline-encoded, but encoded by different frames of D&#x003b2;2 in combination with <italic>N</italic>-nucleotides. A second CDR3&#x003b2; pattern consisting of a glycine residue, followed by a glycine or alanine residue may also be unique to mice vaccinated with effective peptides. Strikingly, most of the TCRs used a J&#x003b2;2.6 segment that was truncated during rearrangement at its N-terminus precisely at the tyrosine residue. This tyrosine residue is unique to J&#x003b2;2.6 and is predicted to lie on the exposed portion of the CDR3&#x003b2; loop available for contact with peptide-MHC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. A second common feature of nearly all of the F1A5-elicited V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> T cells was a relatively short CDR3&#x003b2; length of 10 amino acids. Although the structural analysis of these interactions has yet to be performed, it is tempting to suggest that the short CDR3&#x003b2; loop and the tyrosine residue in the CDR3&#x003b2; motif are required for more stable interactions with the tyrosine residues at positions 4 or 6 of the AH1 peptide. These results are consistent with the affinity analyses and tetramer staining data and demonstrate that vaccination with the effective F1A5 and ineffective WMF peptides elicits different repertoires of AH1-specific T cells.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>The AH1-specific T cells elicited by the F1A5 peptide express TCRs with the V&#x003b2;8.3 and J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segments and a common CDR3&#x003b2; motif, and are different from the T cells elicited by the WMF peptide. <sup>1</sup>AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> cells from the spleens of 5 mice vaccinated with the indicated peptide were pooled, separated by FACSorting, and the gene segments encoding V&#x003b2;8.3 TCRs were sequenced. <sup>2</sup>Replicates: the number of analyzed sequences that encoded a particular amino acid sequence. <sup>3</sup>Codons: the number of nucleotide sequences that encoded a particular amino acid sequence. <sup>4</sup>The sequences were aligned using the shared cysteine residue in the V&#x003b2; sequence and the shared phenylalanine residue in the J&#x003b2; sequence. Germline-encoded sequences are shown as normal text, and sequence encoded by &#x0201c;n&#x0201d; nucleotide additions is shown in italics. <italic>Capital letters</italic> indicate the CDR3&#x003b2; loop. <sup>6</sup>Sequences encoding the common CDR3&#x003b2; motif, consisting of a small hydrophobic residue, followed by a larger polar residue, followed by the tyrosine residue encoded by the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment, are shown in <italic>bold</italic>. <sup>7</sup>The J&#x003b2; gene segments encoded by each sequence are listed</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig3_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Effective and ineffective peptides elicit different repertoires of AH1-specific T cells</title><p>To determine whether the frequency and number of AH1-specific T cells expressing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif correlates with tumor protection, we extended the repertoire analysis to the responses elicited by the native tumor antigen and other previously identified peptide variants using two different techniques. We sorted AH1-specific T cells from individual vaccinated mice, generated cDNA, and performed PCR using V&#x003b2;8 and C&#x003b2; primers. Between 1,000 and 35,000, sequences were obtained per mouse using the Roche 454 Sequencing System and around 20 sequences were obtained per mouse using standard sequencing methods (Supplemental Table&#x000a0;1). We first verified that both techniques produce similar results by comparing the sequences obtained from the same preparation of cDNA using either method (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Both sequencing methods revealed that V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> T cells responding to the native tumor antigen express the CDR3&#x003b2; motif, similar to the T cells responding to an effective peptide variant, the A5 peptide. Many identical sequences were identified from the same cDNA sample (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a) and the frequencies of sequences expressing the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment and the CDR3&#x003b2; motif for most of the samples were similar (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, c), demonstrating that standard sequencing methods and high-throughput sequencing give similar results.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>T cells elicited by the native tumor antigen are similar to those elicited by an effective peptide variant, and similar results are obtain with plasmid and high-throughput sequencing methods. <bold>a</bold><sup>1</sup>This figure is formatted as in Fig.&#x000a0;3. <sup>2</sup><italic>Gray</italic> shaded regions indicate CDR3&#x003b2; sequences that were identified using both traditional sequencing methods of plasmids encoding the PCR-amplified region (<italic>left</italic>) or high-throughput sequencing of PCR products amplified from the same cDNA (<italic>right</italic>). <bold>b</bold> V&#x003b2;8.3 TCR sequences were amplified from the cDNA of AH1-specific cells isolated from vaccinated mice and sequenced using traditional sequencing methods (<italic>white bars</italic>) or high-throughput sequencing (<italic>patterned bars</italic>). The percentage of V&#x003b2;8.3 TCR sequences encoding the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment was calculated for each sample. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the 95% confidence intervals (**<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.008). <bold>c</bold> As in (<bold>b</bold>), the average percentages of sequences encoding the common CDR3&#x003b2; motif were calculated for each sample. <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the 95% confidence intervals (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.017)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig4_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p>Similar to the AH1-elicited TCR sequences, many of the V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> TCRs elicited by the effective A5, F1A5, and 39 peptides expressed the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment and the CDR3&#x003b2; motif (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, b). The distribution of CDR3&#x003b2; lengths expressed by T cells elicited by the effective peptides was also more similar to the AH1-elicited T cells than those elicited by the WMF peptide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c, d). Peptide 15 elicited a highly variable repertoire of T cells, consistent with its variable tumor protection and other previously measured T cell responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. These data suggest that the T cells elicited by the effective peptides and the native tumor antigen were related, expressing a heavily selected CDR3&#x003b2; motif, which may be involved in the specific recognition of the AH1&#x02013;L<sup>d</sup> complex.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>T cells elicited by effective peptide variants express V&#x003b2;8.3 TCRs with a CDR3&#x003b2; motif that correlates with tumor protection. <bold>a</bold> The average percentages of sequences encoding the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment were calculated for the sequences of the V&#x003b2;8.3-expressing TCRs from vaccinated mice (analyzed as in Fig.&#x000a0;4). <italic>Symbols</italic> represent individual mice analyzed by traditional sequencing methods (<italic>black</italic>) or high-throughput sequencing (<italic>gray</italic>). The<italic> bar</italic> indicates the mean, and groups were compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.009, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 mice). <bold>b</bold> As in (<bold>a</bold>), the average percentages of sequences encoding the common CDR3&#x003b2; motif were calculated for each vaccine. <bold>c</bold> The number of amino acids encoded in the CDR3&#x003b2; loop of each V&#x003b2;8.3 sequence was determined. The percentage of sequences encoding the indicated CDR3&#x003b2; length was calculated for each mouse, as in traditional spectratyping analysis. The <italic>errors bars</italic> represent the SEM (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 mice). <bold>d</bold> The average length of the CDR3&#x003b2; chains was determined as in (<bold>c</bold>) for the V&#x003b2;8.3 sequences and compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, ***<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.007, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 mice). <bold>e</bold> The average percentage of sequences encoding the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment (<italic>left</italic>) or the CDR3&#x003b2; motif (<italic>right</italic>) was calculated for the effective (A5, F1A5, and 39 in <italic>black</italic>), ineffective (15 and WMF in <italic>gray</italic>), and native peptides (<italic>white</italic>). <italic>Error bars</italic> represent the SEM. Groups were compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (**<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0073, *<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.039). <bold>f</bold> The frequency of sequences encoding the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment (<italic>x</italic>-axis, from a) was plotted versus the frequency of tumor-free survival observed for each vaccine (35), and a positive correlation was found using a Spearman&#x02019;s nonparametric correlation test (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.6256, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0032). <bold>g</bold> As in (<bold>f</bold>), the correlation of the frequency of sequences encoding the CDR3&#x003b2; motif (<italic>x</italic>-axis, from <bold>b</bold>) and tumor-free survival was analyzed (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.5582, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.0105). <bold>h</bold> The estimated number of AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> T cells expressing V&#x003b2;8.3 TCRs with the CDR3&#x003b2; motif was determined by multiplying the average frequency of CDR3&#x003b2; motif-containing TCR sequences (from <bold>b</bold>) by the number of V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> cells in the spleens of a separate cohort of mice (frequencies from these mice are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;1a) and compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (***<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.004)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig5_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p>Combining the data for the effective and ineffective peptides, we found a significant increase in the frequency of sequences encoding the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment and the CDR3&#x003b2; motif in TCRs elicited by the effective peptides (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). Furthermore, there was a statistically significant correlation between the frequency of both the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment and the CDR3&#x003b2; motif and tumor-free survival afforded by these peptide vaccines (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>f, g). Finally, we estimated the number of V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> T cells expressing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif in the spleens of vaccinated mice. Effective peptide vaccines have significantly more of these cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>h), suggesting that the increased frequency and number of V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> T cells expressing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif in mice vaccinated with effective peptide vaccines may contribute to effective antitumor immunity. We found similar trends among the V&#x003b2;8.1<sup>+</sup> T cells (Supplemental Fig.&#x000a0;3), but not the V&#x003b2;8.2<sup>+</sup> T cells (data not shown).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>CDR3&#x003b2; motif-containing TCRs bind poorly to the WMF peptide. <bold>a</bold><sup>1</sup>T cell clones were screened for CD8<sup>+</sup> AH1-tet<sup>+</sup> V&#x003b2;8.3<sup>+</sup> cells and expanded using irradiated CT26-B7 tumor cells. T cell clones were named after the vaccine used to generate the clone and the plate and well number they were located in. <sup>2</sup>Sequences of the CDR3&#x003b2; region were determined after PCR amplification using V&#x003b2;- and C&#x003b2;-specific primers. <sup>3</sup>Sequences of the CDR3a region were determined after PCR amplification using V&#x003b1;- and C&#x003b1;-specific primers. <sup>4</sup>The cDNA sequence of 39-1D4 and A5-4E11 was subcloned into a protein expression vector for binding studies. <sup>5</sup>The CT T cell clone was derived from a BALB/c mouse vaccinated with irradiated CT26 tumor cells expressing the cytokine GM-CSF (9). <bold>b</bold> Sequence encoding the TCRs derived from T cell clones expressing V&#x003b2;8.3 TCRs with the CDR3&#x003b2; motif (39-1D4 and A5-4E11) was inserted into a BV expression vector, and purified TCR protein was multimerized and conjugated to a fluorescent molecule. A5-4E11 (<bold>b</bold>) or 39-1D4 (<bold>c</bold>) TCR multimers and the L<sup>d</sup> antibody 28.14.8 were used to stain insect cells infected with BV encoding the indicated peptide variant&#x02013;L<sup>d</sup> complex. The soluble TCR MFI was determined for insect cells expressing similar levels of L<sup>d</sup> molecules (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3). Groups were compared using a Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="262_2012_1217_Fig6_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p>Surprisingly, although these junctional sequences were similar to that expressed by the CT T cell clone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a), we did not find the exact CT-TCR sequence in these mice or in the mice vaccinated with the peptide variants. The absence of the CT T cell clone in this study suggests that this clone is not representative of the endogenous repertoire of T cells responding to these vaccines and explains the lack of cross-reactivity between the F1A5- and WMF-elicited repertoires (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Perhaps the different mode of immunization (whole cell irradiated CT26-GM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]) and the in vitro expansion used to generate the CT clone accounts for its dominance in those studies, and absence here.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>TCRs containing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif bind to the WMF peptide with lower affinity</title><p>To study the binding properties of the motif-containing T cells described above, we required both the &#x003b2;- and &#x003b1;-chain sequences of the TCRs identified in Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. We expanded and cloned AH1-specific T cells from vaccinated mice as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The TCR genes expressed by these T cell clones did not reflect the sequencing results we obtained from fresh uncultured splenocytes, particularly for the T cell clones from mice vaccinated with the ineffective peptide variants (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a). However, we obtained several antigen-specific T cell clones that expressed TCRs containing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif and that had identical V&#x003b2; chains as some of those identified ex vivo. These T cell clones expressed a V&#x003b1;6 TCR, distinct from the V&#x003b1;4.11 TCR expressed by the CT T cell clone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a).</p><p>To determine the binding properties of TCRs containing the CDR3&#x003b2; motif, we subcloned the TCR molecules expressed by the A5-4E11 and the 39-1D4 T cell clones (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) into a BV expression vector. The sequences of these TCRs were highly selected in mice vaccinated with AH1, A5, and F1A5 peptides and not identified in mice vaccinated with the ineffective 15 and WMF peptides. We previously showed that the relative binding of multimeric-soluble TCRs to peptide&#x02013;MHC complex expressed on BV-infected insect cells correlates with the affinity of monomeric TCR for the peptide&#x02013;MHC complex determined by surface plasmon resonance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Therefore, we stained insect cells expressing each of the peptide variant&#x02013;L<sup>d</sup> complexes with fluorescent multimeric TCRs derived from the A5-4E11 and 39-1D4 clones. The soluble TCRs bound to insect cells expressing the native tumor antigen, but not the irrelevant &#x003b2;gal peptide, demonstrating that these TCRs are specific for the AH1 peptide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, c). The staining intensity of insect cells expressing the WMF peptide was significantly lower, indicating that this CDR3&#x003b2; motif-containing TCR does not bind efficiently to the WMF peptide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). The binding of the 39-1D4 TCR more closely correlated with its representation in the ex vivo repertoire analysis, binding to the A5 and F1A5 peptides and not to the WMF peptide (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). The low-affinity interaction between the CDR3&#x003b2; motif-containing TCRs and the WMF peptide provides a simple mechanistic explanation for the absence of these cells following vaccination with the WMF peptide.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Although the peptide variants used in our study effectively stimulated a tumor-specific T cell clone in vitro, they elicited variable responses from the endogenous T cell population. In this study, we found that effective cancer peptide vaccines stimulate T cells with hypervariable regions similar to those that respond to the natural tumor antigen, not a de novo T cell repertoire. These results suggest that the heterogeneity in the repertoire of AH1-specific T cells contributes to the ineffectiveness of some of the peptide-variant vaccines.</p><p>Similar to our results, a study of the T cell response to the Melan-A/MART-1<sub>26&#x02013;35</sub> TAA showed that the TCR&#x003b2; gene usage of the T cells responding to the native peptide was broader than that responding to the peptide variant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. They also identified a CDR3&#x003b2; motif that was shared among several patients, a so-called public TCR, although these motif-containing T cells were not among the dominant clones identified in each patient and did not have a higher functional avidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. They concluded that the repertoires responding to the peptide variants and the native tumor antigen were subtly different but over-lapping, and that the observed functional differences were due to subtle structural changes in the TCR. In contrast, the T cells responding to the ineffective peptide variants in our study express a unique repertoire of TCRs that do not overlap with the repertoire responding to the native tumor antigen and that do not contain a significant fraction of the shared CDR3&#x003b2; motif. Therefore, in our study, only the effective peptide variants elicited a repertoire of T cells that over-lapped with those responding to the native tumor antigen.</p><p>The most effective peptide variants (A5 and F1A5) have minimal amino acid sequence changes relative to the AH1 peptide. It is, therefore, not surprising that these vaccines raise similar T cell repertoires. These data suggest that peptides with conservative amino acid changes may be more effective in stimulating antitumor immunity by eliciting a repertoire of T cells that mimics the response to the native tumor antigen. In agreement with this premise, another study concluded that substitutions at MHC-binding positions create immunogenic peptide variants with an overall similar structure to the native peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, the opposite has also been shown in these studies. Peptides specifically designed to encode conservative amino acid changes were ineffective vaccines and raised a repertoire of T cells different from that of the native tumor antigen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. These discrepancies suggest that even subtle amino acid substitutions may cause unpredictable changes in the repertoire and binding kinetics of the responding endogenous T cells.</p><p>The T cells responding to the F1A5 peptide express higher-affinity T cell receptors that functionally recognize the AH1 TAA better than the T cells responding to the ineffective peptide, WMF. Furthermore, soluble TCRs encoding the common CDR3&#x003b2; motif do not bind efficiently to the WMF peptide, providing a mechanistic explanation for the lack of these TCRs in the responding repertoire. We predict from these data that the structure of the WMF peptide prevents productive interactions with TCRs containing the common CDR3&#x003b2; motif. Specifically, the tryptophan residue at position 7 of the WMF peptide may affect the position of the adjacent tyrosine residue at position 6, precluding its predicted interaction with the tyrosine residue encoded by the J&#x003b2;2.6 gene segment of the motif-containing TCRs. Important for peptide vaccine development, these results imply that T cells responding to the ineffective variants (like WMF) cannot be &#x0201c;rescued&#x0201d; or forced to respond to the tumor antigen with better adjuvants; they are not anergic or improperly activated, they simply express T cell receptors that interact poorly with the native tumor antigen.</p><p>A clinically relevant strategy in the design of effective peptide vaccines is to optimize the T cells used in the identification of peptide variants. We selected our peptide variants based on improved binding to and activation of the CT clone, an AH1-specific T cell clone that was in vitro expanded and is not similar to those analyzed ex vivo (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The T cell clones that were found in the endogenous repertoire bound to the peptides that elicit better tumor-specific responses (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Therefore, we predict that peptide variants selected with an ex vivo tumor-specific repertoire, rather than an in vitro selected T cell clone, may be the most effective peptides for cancer vaccines<bold><italic>.</italic></bold></p><p>Due to the unpredictable nature of the responding T cell repertoire, even if optimal T cells are used for peptide selection, ineffective peptides may be unavoidable in peptide-variant vaccine development. Therefore, a general strategy to improve the response to peptide variants such as the WMF peptide should be considered. In this particular case, rather than providing additional adjuvants or cytokines during T cell activation, the repertoire of the T cell response needs to be re-focused to those with high affinity for the native tumor antigen. Although strategies to engineer T cells with receptors that have high affinity for tumor antigens have been developed and employed in the clinical treatment for cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], effective antitumor immunity may be more easily achieved by &#x0201c;boosting&#x0201d; the peptide-variant responses with native tumor antigens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. This strategy may increase the number of high-affinity T cells that cross-react with native tumor antigens and reduce competition with T cells that only bind to peptide variants.</p><p>In summary, peptide-variant vaccines improve the proliferation and activation of T cells that respond to native tumor antigens. Because the T cell response is unpredictable and different for every antigen, optimal peptide variants may be most successfully identified using a representative TAA-specific T cell population to select preferred residue changes from a large and random set of peptides.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="AppESM1"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="SecESM1"><p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="262_2012_1217_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary material 1 (DOCX 2155 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported by NCI CA109560 and ACS RSG-08-184-01-LIB. K.R.J. and J.D.B. were supported in part by the Cancer Research Institute Predoctoral Emphasis Pathway in Tumor Immunology Fellowship.</p><sec id="d29e1511"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors have no conflicting financial interests.</p></sec><sec id="d29e1516"><title>Open Access</title><p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeleniuch-Jacquotte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shapiro</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roses</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bystryn</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccine-induced CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell responses to MAGE-3 correlate with clinical outcome in patients with melanoma</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12576432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pipeling</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedl</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Baculovirus-infected insect cells expressing peptide-MHC complexes elicit protective antitumor immunity</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18097019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Old</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The three Es of cancer immunoediting</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>360</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.22.012703.104803</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15032581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stipdonk</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Badia-Martinez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluijter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Offringa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Achour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Design of agonistic altered peptides for the robust induction of CTL directed towards H-2Db in complex with the melanoma-associated epitope gp100</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>7784</fpage><lpage>7792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-1724</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19789338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kersh</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Miley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Grakoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donermeyer</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fremont</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structural and functional consequences of altering a peptide MHC anchor residue</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2001</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>3345</fpage><lpage>3354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11207290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhns</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedline</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Class I major histocompatibility complex anchor substitutions alter the conformation of T cell receptor contacts</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>21443</fpage><lpage>21449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M010791200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11287414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemmler</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>McDuffie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-dependent tolerance to an endogenous tumor-associated antigen</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>1863</fpage><lpage>1873</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2008.01.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18329760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colella</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mullins</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Overwijk</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Restifo</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhard</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-tolerance to the murine homologue of a tyrosinase-derived melanoma antigen: implications for tumor immunotherapy</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.191.7.1221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattis</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahmy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffee</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Margulies</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced antigen-specific antitumor immunity with altered peptide ligands that stabilize the MHC-peptide-TCR complex</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2000</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>538</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)00052-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11070171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang-Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabaglia</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimachi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Grey</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The stimulation of low-affinity, nontolerized clones by heteroclitic antigen analogues causes the breaking of tolerance established to an immunodominant T cell epitope</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>983</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.190.7.983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10510088</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fourcade</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudela</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade Filho</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Janjic</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Krieg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkwood</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarour</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization with analog peptide in combination with CpG and montanide expands tumor antigen-specific CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in melanoma patients</article-title><source>J Immunother</source><year>2008</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CJI.0b013e318183af0b</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18779741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell repertoires primed with agonist and native peptides derived from a tumor-associated antigen</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>1526</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18209048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Squarcina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarselli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerino</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrabba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toutirais</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmiani</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivoltini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low TCR avidity and lack of tumor cell recognition in CD8(+) T cells primed with the CEA-analogue CAP1-6D peptide</article-title><source>Cancer Immunol Immunother</source><year>2007</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1979</fpage><lpage>1991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00262-007-0342-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17564703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuge</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Saharan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuettenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roederer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity and recognition efficiency of T cell responses to cancer</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e28</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0010028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15578105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Speiser</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgaertner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Voelter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Devevre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unmodified self antigen triggers human CD8 T cells with stronger tumor reactivity than altered antigen</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>3849</fpage><lpage>3854</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0800080105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18319339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gulden</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Engelhard</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasternack</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffee</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The immunodominant major histocompatibility complex class I-restricted antigen of a murine colon tumor derives from an endogenous retroviral gene product</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>9730</fpage><lpage>9735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.18.9730</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8790399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemmler</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peptide vaccines prevent tumor growth by activating T cells that respond to native tumor antigens</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>4652</fpage><lpage>4657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0914879107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McMahan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relating TCR-peptide-MHC affinity to immunogenicity for the design of tumor vaccines</article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>2006</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>2543</fpage><lpage>2551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16932807</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sloan-Lancaster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered peptide ligand-induced partial T cell activation: molecular mechanisms and role in T cell biology</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>1996</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.14.1.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8717505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gal</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayyoub</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dutoit</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Widmer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerottini</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Valmori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distinct structural TCR repertoires in naturally occurring versus vaccine-induced CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell responses to the tumor-specific antigen NY-ESO-1</article-title><source>J Immunother</source><year>2005</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>257</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.cji.0000161398.34701.26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15838382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wieckowski</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgaertner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Corthesy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Voelter</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Speiser</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rufer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fine structural variations of alphabetaTCRs selected by vaccination with natural versus altered self-antigen in melanoma patients</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>183</volume><fpage>5397</fpage><lpage>5406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.0901460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19786555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnuriger</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Saas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guillard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caignard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TCR analysis reveals significant repertoire selection during in vitro lymphocyte culture</article-title><source>Int Immunol</source><year>1997</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1073</fpage><lpage>1083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/intimm/9.8.1073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9263004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Huseby</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mimotopes for alloreactive and conventional T Cells in a peptide-MHC display library</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0020090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavin</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Riddell</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bevan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alkali hydrolysis of recombinant proteins allows for the rapid identification of class I MHC-restricted CTL epitopes</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1993</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>3971</fpage><lpage>3980</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7691936</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jordan KR, Crawford F, Kappler JW, and Slansky JE (2009) Vaccination of mice with baculovirus-infected insect cells expressing antigenic proteins. Current protocols in immunology/edited by John E Coligan et al. [Chapter 2:Unit 2 15]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boniface</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A kinetic basis for T cell receptor repertoire selection during an immune response</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>1999</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)80048-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10229191</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pannetier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Darche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Casrouge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zoller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kourilsky</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sizes of the CDR3 hypervariable regions of the murine T-cell receptor beta chains vary as a function of the recombined germ-line segments</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>4319</fpage><lpage>4323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.9.4319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8483950</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arden</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabelitz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mouse T-cell receptor variable gene segment families</article-title><source>Immunogenetics</source><year>1995</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8550093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefranc</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Giudicelli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginestoux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontrop</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbie</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaume</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IMGT, the international ImMunoGeneTics database</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/27.1.209</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanders</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>HW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Babrzadeh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharizadeh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High throughput sequencing reveals a complex pattern of dynamic interrelationships among human T cell subsets</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1518</fpage><lpage>1523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0913939107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barth</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunkapiller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobieck</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Winoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gershenfeld</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansburg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The murine T-cell receptor uses a limited repertoire of expressed V beta gene segments</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1985</year><volume>316</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>523</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/316517a0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2412120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lissina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tricks with tetramers: how to get the most from multimeric peptide-MHC</article-title><source>Immunology</source><year>2009</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2567.2008.02848.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19125886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozono</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of antigen-specific T cells with multivalent soluble class II MHC covalent peptide complexes</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>1998</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>675</fpage><lpage>682</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)80572-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9655481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of high avidity melanoma-reactive CTL from heterogeneous populations using peptide-MHC tetramers</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>2227</fpage><lpage>2234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9973498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fahmy</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bieler</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Edidin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneck</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased TCR avidity after T cell activation: a mechanism for sensing low-density antigen</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Govern</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paczosa</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakraborty</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Huseby</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast on-rates allow short dwell time ligands to activate T cells</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>8724</fpage><lpage>8729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000966107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>McGurran</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Slansky</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kedl</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified tyrosinase-related protein 2 epitope generates high-affinity tumor-specific T cells but does not mediate therapeutic efficacy in an intradermal tumor model</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16785510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gras</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kjer-Nielsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Burrows</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossjohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T-cell receptor bias and immunity</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2007.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18207719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huseby</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interface-disrupting amino acids establish specificity between T cell receptors and complexes of major histocompatibility complex and peptide</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1191</fpage><lpage>1199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fremont</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrack</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soluble class I MHC with beta2-microglobulin covalently linked peptides: specific binding to a T cell hybridoma</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>2671</fpage><lpage>2676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Wynn</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Clement</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miles</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ladell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ekeruche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gostick</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Skowera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Peakman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wooldridge</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sewell</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of MHC anchor residues generates heteroclitic peptides that alter TCR binding and T cell recognition</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>2600</fpage><lpage>2610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1000629</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20639478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlich</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Royal</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Topalian</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kammula</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name><name><surname>Restifo</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahvi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vries</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers-Freezer</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavroukakis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer regression in patients after transfer of genetically engineered lymphocytes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>314</volume><fpage>126</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1129003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16946036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobisse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rondina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisato</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandruzzato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Amendola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Naldini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Willemsen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Debets</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanovello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reprogramming T lymphocytes for melanoma adoptive immunotherapy by T-cell receptor gene transfer with lentiviral vectors</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>9385</fpage><lpage>9394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-0494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolonaki</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotsakis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadimitraki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggouraki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Konsolakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vagia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Christophylakis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikoloudi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Magganas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordopatis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosmatopoulos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Georgoulias</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mavroudis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination of patients with advanced non-small-cell lung cancer with an optimized cryptic human telomerase reverse transcriptase peptide</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>2727</fpage><lpage>2734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2006.10.3465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17602077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>