<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-Med</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21771710</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3205759</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2011.0017</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ci110017</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Urinary bladder: normal appearance and mimics of malignancy at CT urography</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Shinagare</surname><given-names>Atul B.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadow</surname><given-names>Cheryl A.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anik Sahni</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>Stuart G.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><aff>Division of Abdominal Imaging and Intervention, Department of Radiology, Brigham and Women&#x02019;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA 02115, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding address: Atul B. Shinagare, Division of Abdominal Imaging and Intervention, Department of Radiology, Brigham and Women&#x02019;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, 75 Francis Street, Boston, MA 02115 USA. Email: <monospace><email>ashinagare@partners.org</email></monospace></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2011 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>The objective of this review article is to learn how to recognize anatomic variants and benign entities that mimic bladder cancer at computed tomography (CT) urography. Building on recent data that suggest that CT urography can be used to diagnose bladder cancer, recognition of anatomic variants and benign entities will help improve radiologists&#x02019; ability to diagnose bladder cancer.</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Computed tomography</kwd><kwd>urography</kwd><kwd>bladder cancer</kwd><kwd>anatomic variants</kwd><kwd>pitfalls</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>With an estimated 70,530 new cases and 14,680 deaths in the United States in 2010, bladder cancer is the most common malignancy of the urothelium and kidneys<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"><sup>1</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Metachronous disease is common, and surveillance for additional tumors is a lifelong challenge in patients with bladder cancer<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2"><sup>2</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>.</p><p>CT urography (CTU) is defined as a CT examination of the urinary tract that is performed both before and after intravenous (IV) contrast material, and includes excretory phase images<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. CTU is emerging as the imaging test of choice for the evaluation of the urinary tract for a variety of disorders, including hematuria<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Although the precise role of CTU has not been defined, recent data suggest that CTU can be used to detect bladder cancer with a sensitivity and specificity close to cystoscopy<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9"><sup>6&#x02013;9</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. This article reviews the anatomic variants and benign entities that mimic bladder cancer at CTU.</p></sec><sec><title>CT urography technique</title><p>Although techniques vary among institutions, the goal of CTU is to achieve a set of images that include a fully opacified and distended intrarenal collecting system, ureters, and bladder<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Excretory phase images are considered essential in the evaluation of the urothelium<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10"><sup>10</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. We obtain an unenhanced CT scan of the abdomen and pelvis to identify calculi, including those in the bladder, that could be masked by excreted contrast material. Unenhanced CT scans also allow measurement of the native attenuation of masses throughout the urinary tract that can be used to assess for enhancement. In patients over the age of 40 years, we image the kidneys in the nephrographic phase at 100&#x02009;s after contrast material injection (80&#x02009;ml of iodinated contrast material; 370&#x02009;mg I/ml), to detect and characterize renal masses. An excretory phase scan of the abdomen and pelvis is obtained at 15&#x02009;min<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5"><sup>3&#x02013;5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12 B13 B14"><sup>10&#x02013;14</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. In patients 40 years or younger, a split-bolus, two-phase protocol is used to limit radiation exposure. Following an unenhanced scan of the abdomen and pelvis, 40&#x02009;ml of IV contrast medium are administered. After an 8-min delay, 80&#x02009;ml of IV contrast medium are administered and followed by a scan of the abdomen and pelvis at 100&#x02009;s. Both protocols may be augmented with 250&#x02009;ml of IV normal saline infused during the delay periods<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5"><sup>3&#x02013;5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"><sup>7</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10 B11 B12 B13 B14"><sup>10&#x02013;14</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. We prefer to administer 10&#x02009;mg of IV furosemide (Lasix; Abbott Laboratories, North Chicago, IL) 2&#x02013;3&#x02009;min before the intravenous contrast material in patients over the age of 40 years. Furosemide, and to some extent saline, contribute to distension of the upper urinary tracts and bladder during excretory phase imaging.</p><p>An underdistended bladder can appear thickened, particularly along its anterior wall, and mimic bladder cancer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Since the specific gravity of contrast medium is higher than urine, incomplete mixing of unopacified urine and contrast material often results in a urine contrast level. Furosemide increases urinary flow rate, thereby increasing both distention and mixing of the contrast material, the latter likely via an increased ureteral jet phenomenon<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11"><sup>11</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Others have used a log-rolling technique to promote mixing of contrast material and urine in the bladder<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Wide window settings may be required, particularly if CTU is not supplemented with furosemide, as dense contrast material may obscure small urothelial masses<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"><sup>12</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(a) A 67-year-old man with painless hematuria. Axial image from the unenhanced phase of a CT urogram shows apparent thickening of the anterior bladder wall (arrowheads) concerning for bladder cancer. (b) Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram supplemented with IV furosemide demonstrates that the bladder is normal. The bladder is well distended, and the urine and contrast material are mixed providing a homogeneous background ideal for detection of bladder masses.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001701"/></fig>
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(a) A 61-year-old woman with hematuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram (window level 50, window width 350) supplemented with IV normal saline demonstrates a distended bladder with dense contrast material layering dependently. No mass is visible. (b) Same image viewed with a wider windowing (window level 50, window width 630) demonstrates a 2-mm papillary urothelial carcinoma (arrowhead) that was obscured using soft tissue windows.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001702"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Normal anatomy</title><p>The distended bladder has a round or oval form with a peritoneum-covered dome. The remaining surfaces of the bladder abut the extraperitoneal space. The apex of the bladder, connected to the umbilicus by the urachus during embryologic development, is directed anterosuperiorly; the bladder neck is positioned inferiorly. A prominent urachal remnant may cause focal nodularity at the anterosuperior aspect of the bladder and mimic a mass (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). This pitfall may be avoided by noting that the thickening is limited to the serosal side of the bladder, midline, and is contiguous with the fibrous urachal remnant (the median umbilical ligament) extending anterosuperiorly towards the umbilicus.
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>(a) A 31-year-old woman with hematuria and a prominent urachal remnant. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates focal thickening of the anterior bladder wall in the midline (arrow). Physiologic changes are seen in the left ovary (arrowhead). (b) Sagittal image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates thickening limited to the serosal surface of the bladder wall (arrow). Also note a thin linear remnant extends from the bladder dome to the umbilicus (arrowheads). The urine analysis was normal 2 years after the examination, and no cause for the patient&#x02019;s hematuria was found.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001703"/></fig></p><p>The internal urethral orifice is located at the bladder neck at the inferior angle of the trigone. The ureters traverse a short, oblique, intramuscular course before opening at the posterolateral angles of the trigone at the ureterovesical junction (UVJ). The intramural ureter may appear to protrude into the bladder lumen, and can simulate a bladder mass depending on the location of the UVJ, the angle at which the ureter inserts, and the imaging plane (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). A tumor can often be excluded by noting that the bulge is subtle, located at the UVJ, and bilateral, with symmetry in at least one imaging plane. In contradistinction, cancers at the UVJ (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>) typically cause more mass effect. However, benign processes such as post-operative changes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>) and endometriosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) can be mass-like and mimic cancer.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>(a) An 84-year-old man with a history of bladder cancer and normal CT urogram. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows apparent thickening of a normal left ureterovesical junction (UVJ) (arrow). (b) Coronal reformations demonstrate normal symmetric appearance of the bilateral ureterovesical junctions (arrows). Note the enlarged prostate gland (curved arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001704"/></fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>A 50-year-old man with hematuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows mild asymmetric thickening of the left UVJ (arrow). Cystoscopic biopsy demonstrated urothelial carcinoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001705"/></fig>
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>A 71-year-old man with a history of resected bladder cancer. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates focal wall thickening (arrow) just anterolateral to the right UVJ (arrowhead), at the site of the previous resection. Urine cytology was negative, and cystoscopic biopsy demonstrated postoperative inflammatory changes. Note the normal left UVJ (curved arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001706"/></fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>A 53-year-old woman with endometriosis. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates focal mass-like wall thickening just superolateral to the right UVJ (arrow). Cystoscopic biopsy demonstrated endometriosis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001707"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Inflammatory processes</title><p>Several inflammatory and infectious processes, such as hemorrhagic cystitis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>), schistosomiasis, tuberculosis, and radiation-induced cystitis generally cause diffuse, symmetric bladder wall thickening<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13"><sup>13</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Bladder cancer only rarely causes diffuse symmetric bladder wall thickening<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Diffuse or multifocal bladder cancer typically causes asymmetric, multifocal wall thickening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). Rarely, inflammatory conditions such as cystitis glandularis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref>) and endometriosis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>) can cause focal bladder wall thickening and mimic cancer. Calcifications not associated with a mass or focal thickening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref>), and those associated with diffuse wall thickening are likely benign. However, urothelial carcinoma may calcify (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>), and therefore cancer should be suspected when calcification is associated with a mass.
<fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>A 55-year-old man with gross hematuria. Coronal image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows diffuse bladder wall thickening with irregularity of the urothelial surface (arrowheads). Cystoscopy revealed severe hemorrhagic cystitis. The left ureter (curved arrow) is mildly obstructed due to the thickened wall.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001708"/></fig>
<fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>A 53-year-old man with gross hematuria and urothelial carcinoma. Coronal image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates multifocal nodular wall thickening (arrows) involving most of the bladder, and causing bilateral hydronephrosis and hydroureter (arrowheads). Cystoscopic biopsy revealed urothelial carcinoma. Surgical pathology at cystectomy revealed multifocal high grade urothelial carcinoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci11001709"/></fig>
<fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>A 75-year-old man with hematuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows focal thickening of the posterior bladder wall (arrow), and an enlarged left external iliac lymph node (arrowhead). Cystoscopic biopsy revealed cystitis glandularis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017010"/></fig>
<fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>A 75-year-old woman with a history of bladder cancer treated with intravesical Bacillus Calmette-Gu&#x000e9;rin (BCG). Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates foci of bladder wall calcification (arrows) without associated mass or wall thickening. Multiple other similar foci were present. Biopsy revealed chronic inflammation and granulomas at all sites, related to prior BCG treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017011"/></fig>
<fig id="F12" position="float"><label>Figure 12</label><caption><p>A 57-year-old man with hematuria and urothelial carcinoma of the bladder. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows a mass along the right lateral bladder wall with calcifications (arrowheads). Cystoscopic biopsy revealed urothelial carcinoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017012"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Treatment effects</title><p>In patients with a history of bladder cancer, prior surgical treatment may cause focal wall thickening and abnormal enhancement that may be indistinguishable from recurrent tumor, even at cystoscopy<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Figs. 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F14">14</xref>). Patients who have received intravesical immunotherapy with Bacillus Calmette-Gu&#x000e9;rin (BCG) may develop granulomatous changes in the bladder wall, mimicking bladder cancer<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15"><sup>15</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F12">Fig. 12</xref>). As above, radiation therapy can cause diffuse bladder wall thickening due to cystitis. Knowledge of past history and the presence of radiation-induced changes in nearby small bowel loops can help reach the diagnosis.
<fig id="F13" position="float"><label>Figure 13</label><caption><p>A 56-year-old man with hematuria 6 weeks following transurethral resection of superficial bladder cancer. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows focal wall thickening at the site of prior resection (arrow). Cystoscopic biopsy and urine cytology revealed no evidence of residual malignancy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017013"/></fig>
<fig id="F14" position="float"><label>Figure 14</label><caption><p>A 62-year-old man with a history of resected bladder cancer. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram demonstrates focal bladder wall thickening along the left lateral wall (arrowheads), at the site of previous resection. Cystoscopy revealed no evidence of malignancy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017014"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Blood clot</title><p>Blood clots can simulate bladder neoplasms, however, they are typically odd-shaped or linear, smoothly marginated; they do not enhance. Also, they are luminal findings, and multiplanar reformations can be used to demonstrate that they do not arise from the bladder mucosa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F15">Fig. 15</xref>). Cystoscopy may be needed to distinguish clots that abut or adhere to the bladder wall, from urothelial cancer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F16">Fig. 16</xref>).
<fig id="F15" position="float"><label>Figure 15</label><caption><p>(a) A 74-year-old man with hematuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows irregular soft tissue at the bladder base, projecting into the bladder lumen (arrows). (b) Coronal reformations demonstrate linear structures in the bladder lumen without attachment to the bladder mucosa (arrows). Also note nodular enlarged prostate gland indenting the bladder base (curved arrow). Cystoscopy demonstrated blood clots without bladder cancer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017015"/></fig>
<fig id="F16" position="float"><label>Figure 16</label><caption><p>A 77-year-old man with hematuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows an apparent papillary mass at the bladder base (arrow), concerning for bladder cancer. Cystoscopy revealed a blood clot adherent to the bladder wall, without evidence of bladder cancer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017016"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Enlarged prostate gland</title><p>Benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH) can cause bladder outlet obstruction and bladder wall thickening due to detrusor muscle hypertrophy (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F17">Fig. 17</xref>). Both BPH (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F18">Fig. 18</xref>) and prostate cancer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F19">Fig. 19</xref>) can cause protrusion of nodular, mass-like tissue into the bladder at its base<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16"><sup>16</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. This nodular tissue may be asymmetric, and can have either a smooth or an irregular surface. Distinguishing a bladder base cancer from an enlarged prostate gland therefore may be difficult with excretory phase imaging, even using coronal reformations<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>]</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F20">Fig. 20</xref>). Since urothelial cancers are typically hypervascular, bladder base urothelial cancers can be differentiated from the prostate gland when the pelvis is examined 70&#x02009;s after the injection of IV contrast material, when the bladder is distended with unopacified urine<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"><sup>8</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9"><sup>9</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. However, addition of these images to the CTU protocol described above would increase the radiation dose of the examination.
<fig id="F17" position="float"><label>Figure 17</label><caption><p>An 83-year-old man with a prolonged history of urinary frequency, urgency and dysuria secondary to benign prostatic hyperplasia. Severe diffuse symmetric bladder wall thickening (arrows) due to detrusor muscle hypertrophy is mildly obstructive, manifested as mild left hydroureteronephrosis (arrowheads) and mild right hydroureter (curved arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017017"/></fig>
<fig id="F18" position="float"><label>Figure 18</label><caption><p>A 76-year-old man with urinary frequency, urgency and dysuria. Axial image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows papillary-appearing soft tissue at the bladder base (arrows). Cystoscopy revealed benign prostatic hyperplasia with prostatic tissue protruding into the bladder lumen.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017018"/></fig>
<fig id="F19" position="float"><label>Figure 19</label><caption><p>An 87-year-old man with urinary frequency, urgency, and dysuria. Coronal image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows a smooth nodular soft tissue mass contiguous with prostate, projecting into the bladder base (arrow) to the left of a urinary catheter (curved arrow). Histopathology revealed prostate cancer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017019"/></fig>
<fig id="F20" position="float"><label>Figure 20</label><caption><p>An 81-year-old man with urinary frequency, urgency and dysuria. Coronal image from the excretory phase of a CT urogram shows an apparent mass (arrows) at the bladder base inseparable from the prostate gland. Cystoscopic biopsy revealed a urothelial carcinoma at the bladder base.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci110017020"/></fig></p><p>CTU is emerging as a method that can be used to diagnose bladder cancer<sup>[</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6 B7 B8 B9"><sup>6&#x02013;9</sup></xref><sup>]</sup>. Knowledge of normal anatomy and benign conditions that mimic neoplastic disease will help reduce the number of false-positive CT urograms. Although cystoscopy will be needed to differentiate benign from malignant bladder processes in some situations, continued experience with CTU and knowledge of the appearance of benign conditions will help limit the number of patients needing further investigation.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This paper is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancerimaging.org">http://www.cancerimaging.org</ext-link>. In the event of a change in the URL address, please use the DOI provided to locate the paper.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2010</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2010</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3322/caac.20073">doi:10.3322/caac.20073</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20610543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donat</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation and follow-up strategies for superficial bladder cancer</article-title><source>Urol Clin North Am</source><year>2003</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>765</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0094-0143(03)00060-0">doi:10.1016/S0094-0143(03)00060-0</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14680313</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Washburn</surname><given-names>ZW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dillman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Caoili</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computed tomographic urography update: an evolving urinary tract imaging modality</article-title><source>Semin Ultrasound CT MR</source><year>2009</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1053/j.sult.2009.03.005">doi:10.1053/j.sult.2009.03.005</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19711637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyendecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Amis</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the current role of CT urography and MR urography in the evaluation of the urinary tract?</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2009</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2502080534">doi:10.1148/radiol.2502080534</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choyke</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiologic evaluation of hematuria: guidelines from the American College of Radiology's appropriateness criteria</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><year>2008</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18711950</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sadow</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Signorovitch</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bladder cancer detection with CT urography in an Academic Medical Center</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2008</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2491071860">doi:10.1148/radiol.2491071860</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18796677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turney</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Willatt</surname><given-names>JMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crew</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Computed tomography urography for diagnosing bladder cancer</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2006</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1464-410X.2006.06216.x">doi:10.1111/j.1464-410X.2006.06216.x</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16879676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematuria: portal venous phase multi detector row CT of the bladder-a prospective study</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2007</year><volume>245</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2452061060">doi:10.1148/radiol.2452061060</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17951346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinmoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of bladder tumors with dynamic contrast-enhanced MDCT</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2007</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>913</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2214/AJR.06.0511">doi:10.2214/AJR.06.0511</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17377023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McTavish</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinzaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawfel</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-detector row CT urography: comparison of strategies for depicting the normal urinary collecting system</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>225</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2253011515">doi:10.1148/radiol.2253011515</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12461262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverman</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortele</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuncali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhagwat</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifter</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-detector row CT urography of normal urinary collecting system: furosemide versus saline as adjunct to contrast medium</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1148/radiol.2403050233">doi:10.1148/radiol.2403050233</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16926326</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caoili</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Inampudi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MDCT urography of upper tract urothelial neoplasms</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2005</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>1873</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15908545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maher</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rizzo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Saini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidetector CT urography in imaging of the urinary tract in patients with hematuria</article-title><source>Korean J Radiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3348/kjr.2004.5.1.1">doi:10.3348/kjr.2004.5.1.1</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15064553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohan</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Caoili</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weizer</surname><given-names>AZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MDCT Urography: exploring a new paradigm for imaging of bladder cancer</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2009</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>1501</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2214/AJR.09.2344">doi:10.2214/AJR.09.2344</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19457811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hricak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerst</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging appearance of granulomatous disease after intravesical Bacille Calmette-Guerin (BCG) treatment of bladder carcinoma</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2009</year><volume>192</volume><fpage>1494</fpage><lpage>500</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2214/AJR.08.1962">doi:10.2214/AJR.08.1962</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19457810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McGree</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>St Sauver</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Girman</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravesical prostatic protrusion in men in Olmsted County, Minnesota</article-title><source>J Urol</source><year>2009</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>2819</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.juro.2009.08.086">doi:10.1016/j.juro.2009.08.086</ext-link></comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19837429</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>