<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CI</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>e-Med</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18055292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2151326</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ci070028</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2007.0028</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group><series-title>Article</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spectrum of findings and usefulness of integrated PET/CT in patients with known or suspected neuroendocrine tumors of the lung</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>Semin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Kyung Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1"><sup>b</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><sup>a</sup>Department of Radiology, Chung-Ang University Medical Center, Chung-Ang University College of Medicine, Seoul 156-755, Korea; <sup>b</sup>Department of Radiology and Center for Imaging Science, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, Seoul 135-710, Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding address: Kyung Soo Lee, MD, Department of Radiology, Samsung Medical Center, Sungkyunkwan University School of Medicine, 50, Ilwon-dong, Kangnam-gu, Seoul 135-710, Korea. <email>kyungs.lee@samsung.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>17</day><month>10</month><year>2007</year></date></history><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007 International Cancer Imaging Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Positron emission tomography (PET) with fluorine-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) has been known to increase diagnostic accuracy in differentiating benign and malignant lung lesions and to improve identification of lymph node and extrathoracic metastasis in pulmonary neoplasms. In this review, the authors describe the spectrum of integrated PET/CT findings on neuroendocrine (NE) tumors of the lung. We also demonstrate the usefulness of this imaging modality in patients with known or suspected NE tumors of the lung.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Chest</kwd><kwd>CT</kwd><kwd>lung</kwd><kwd>oncologic imaging</kwd><kwd>PET/CT</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Neuroendocrine (NE) tumors of the lung, arising from Kulchitzky cells of the bronchial mucosa, can be categorized into typical carcinoid, atypical carcinoid, large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma (LCNEC), and small cell lung carcinoma (SCLC)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]</sup>. The prognosis and behavioral features of these NE tumors worsen as the grade of malignancy increases<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>It is reported that positron emission tomography (PET) with fluorine-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) increases diagnostic accuracy when differentiating benign and malignant lesions. In addition, it is shown to improve identification of lymph node and extrathoracic metastasis in pulmonary neoplasms. Pulmonary carcinoid tumors have been known to exhibit little activity on PET scans and usually have less FDG uptake than expected for malignant tumors<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]</sup>. Recently, it was reported that most LCNECs have homogeneously high FDG uptake<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup>. As much as it is used to evaluate non-small cell carcinoma of the lung, FDG PET has also been studied for the evaluation of SCLC. FDG PET was found to be highly sensitive in detecting SCLC and useful for evaluating prognosis and tumor stage<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]</sup>. In this review, we describe the spectrum of integrated PET/CT findings on NE tumors of the lung. We also describe the usefulness of this imaging modality in patients with known or suspected NE tumors of the lung.</p></sec><sec><title>Tumor histology</title><p>Neuroendocrine tumors of the lung share NE morphologic features such as organoid nesting, palisading, rosettes, and a trabecular growth pattern. In 1991, Travis <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]</sup> proposed the following classification of pulmonary NE tumors: low-grade malignancy, namely, typical carcinoid tumors; medium-grade malignancy, which includes atypical carcinoid tumors; and high-grade malignancy, such as LCNEC and SCLC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>).
<fig id="F1" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 1</italic></label><caption><p>Histopathologic features of pulmonary neuroendocrine tumor of the lungs. (a) Typical carcinoid. Photomicrograph shows small nests of uniform cells without mitotic or necrotic features (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;40). (b) Atypical carcinoid. Photomicrogra ph shows nuclear pleomorphism and mitosis (arrow) (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;400). (c) Large cell neuroendocrine carcinoma. Photomicrograph shows a neuroendocri ne appearance with peripheral palisading and rosettes (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;4 0). (d) Small cell lung carcinoma. Photomicrograph shows high cellularity; the small round cells have scanty cytoplasm and coarse chromatin. Also note frequent mitoses (H&#x00026;E, &#x000d7;200).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002801"/></fig>\</p><p>These tumors represent a broad clinicopathologic spectrum with variable morphologic features and biologic behaviors. In terms of histologic features predictive of prognosis, typical carcinoid tumors show no evidence of necrosis and less than 2 mitoses per 10 high power fields (HPFs) (or 2&#x02009;mm<sup>2</sup>) of viable tumor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>a), whereas atypical carcinoid tumors have areas of necrosis or 2&#x02013;10 mitoses per 10 HPFs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>b)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]</sup>. The histopathologic diagnostic criteria for LCNEC proposed by the World Health Organization (WHO) in 1999 is as follows: (1) NE morphologic features (organoid nesting, palisading, rosettes, or trabecular growth pattern); (2) high mitotic rate (&#x0003e;10 per 10 HPFs); (3) necrosis (often large zones); (4) cytologic features different from SCLC (large cell size, polygonal, low nuclear/cytoplasmatic ratio, finely granular eosinophilic cytoplasm, coarse nuclear chromatin, and frequent nucleoli); (5) positive immunohistochemical staining for one or more NE markers including chromogranin A, synaptophysin and neural cell adhesion molecule (NCAM/CD56) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>c)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]</sup>. The cells in SCLCs are usually small and round or fusiform in shape. Also, SCLSs have high cellularity with a very high mitotic rate. Therefore, the prognosis and tumor biology of these NE tumors worsen as the grade of malignancy increases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>d)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Typical imaging findings</title><p>The majority of carcinoid tumors are centrally located and thus related to airways. Therefore, imaging studies show a well-defined hilar or perihilar mass as an isolated finding or with associated distal parenchymal changes of atelectasis or obstructive pneumonia (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). About 16&#x02013;40% of these tumors occur in the peripheral lung<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>. The tumors appear at CT as a spherical or ovoid nodule or mass with well-defined and slightly lobulated border. They are typically located close to central bronchi, often near the bifurcation area. On CT scans, calcification or ossification can be seen in up to 30% of tumors, and manifests as punctate or diffuse. Moreover, calcification is more frequent in central carcinoids than in peripheral carcinoids. Therefore, observation of a central tumor that causes a bronchus to be narrowed, deformed or obstructed and that displays punctate or diffuse calcification should suggest the diagnosis of bronchial carcinoids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>. They occasionally present with a small nodule entirely located within the lumen of a bronchus. Even a small nodule, located beyond the origin of a subsegmental bronchus, may be noticed abutting a subsegmental bronchus or displaying a small endoluminal component of tumor at thin-section CT. Peripheral carcinoids may manifest as a well-defined, lobulated nodule or mass without CT evidence of a bronchial relationship. Carcinoids tend to be vascular and may demonstrate intense enhancement (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). In a dynamic enhanced CT study, typical and atypical carcinoid tumors show high enhancement, more than 30 HU of net enhancement<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>.
<fig id="F2" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 2</italic></label><caption><p>A 24-year-old man with typical carcinoid. (a) Chest radiograph shows a large mass in the right infrahilar area. (b) Transverse unenhanced CT scan (5-mm section thickness, 130&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the level of the left lower lobar bronchus demonstrates the upper portion of the tumor involving the distal bronchus intermedius with an intrabronchial component of the tumor (arrow). (c) Mediastinal window image of a transverse CT scan (1.0-mm section thickness, 120&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the level of the inferior pulmonary vein shows a large mass containing nodular calcifications (arrows) within the lesion in the right middle lobe. (a) and (c) are reproduced with permission from Chong et al.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002802"/></fig>
<fig id="F3" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 3</italic></label><caption><p>A 58-year-old man with typical carcinoid. Mediastinal window images of transverse CT scans before (left) and 60&#x02009;s after (right) contrast medium injection show enhancing nodules (arrows; 37 HU on unenhanced scan and 76 HU on enhanced scan) in the right middle lobe.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002803"/></fig></p><p>Imaging findings of LCNECs are similar to those of other common non-small cell lung cancers. Approximately 80% of LCNECs appear as a peripheral mass or nodule, whereas 20% of the tumors present with a central mass and attendant atelectasis or distal mucus plugging. Intratumoral calcifications are seen in 9% of patients with LCNEC<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>.</p><p>Most SCLCs are located centrally and appear with mediastinal (92%) or hilar (84%) lymphadenopathy with displacement or narrowing of the tracheobronchial trees (68%) or major vessels (68%). Other intrathoracic CT findings are major (at least lobar) atelectasis (30%), a non-contiguous parenchymal mass (41%), and pleural effusion (38%). In 5&#x02013;10% of cases, SCLC manifests as a peripheral nodule without associated lymphadenopathy. Intratumoral calcification may be seen in up to 23% of SCLCs<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>Tumor staging</title><p>In carcinoids and LCNECs, tumor stages are determined by the TNM and American Joint Committee on Cancer staging systems as in non-small cell lung cancers<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]</sup>. However, SCLC is usually classified using a two-stage system, i.e., limited (LD) or extensive disease (ED). LD is defined as a tumor confined to one hemithorax including regional mediastinal and supraclavicular lymph nodes, whereas ED is defined as disease beyond these boundaries. The criteria for these two categories remain controversial. However, the Veterans Administration Lung Study Group (VALG) definition of LD, primary tumor and nodal involvement limited to one hemithorax, is widely used<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]</sup>.</p></sec><sec><title>FDG uptake of tumors</title><p>In a few studies about the PET findings of carcinoid tumors<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3 B4 B5">3&#x02013;5</xref>]</sup>, it has been initially reported that typical carcinoid tumors do not exhibit increased activity during PET and usually have less FDG uptake than expected for malignant tumors (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). However, subsequent reports described that typical carcinoid tumors show variable uptake according to mitotic figures and tumor proliferation<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]</sup>. Atypical carcinoid tumors also show variable FDG uptake (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>). According to a report, three (60%) of five atypical carcinoids had higher than mediastinal uptake (maximum SUV, 4.0&#x02013;7.1)<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup>. Therefore, both typical and atypical carcinoid tumors show variable FDG uptake according to mitotic figure and tumor proliferation.
<fig id="F4" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 4</italic></label><caption><p>A 56-year-old man with typical carcinoid (T2N0M0, IB). (a) Transverse unenhanced CT scan (5-mm section thickness, 40&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the level of the right inferior pulmonary vein shows a 42-mm-sized mass (arrow) in the right lower lobe. (b),(c) FDG PET (b) and integrated PET/CT (c) scans show little FDG uptake (arrow) within the tumor (SUV<sub>max</sub>, 3.4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002804"/></fig>
<fig id="F5" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 5</italic></label><caption><p>A 44-year-old woman with atypical carcinoid (T1N0M0, IA). (a) Lung window image of a transverse unenhanced CT scan (5-mm section thickness, 40&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the level of the right inferior pulmonary vein shows a 25-mm-sized nodule (arrow) in the right middle lobe. (b) Integrated PET/CT scan shows high FDG uptake (arrow) within the tumor (SUV<sub>max</sub>, 7.1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002805"/></fig></p><p>In the PET/CT analysis study of LCNECs<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup>, all tumors had homogeneously high FDG uptake with their maximum SUVs ranging from 3.9 to 25.6 (mean 12.0, median 10.7) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). In cases of SCLCs, the tumors showed high FDG uptake with their SUVs ranging from 6.1 to 17.3 (mean 11.6, median 11.7) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). Therefore, the maximum SUVs of NE tumors are significantly different, listed in increasing order, in carcinoids, LCNECs and SCLCs.
<fig id="F6" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 6</italic></label><caption><p>A 70-year-old man with a large cell neuroendocrine cell carcinoma (T1N0M0, IA). (a) Mediastinal window image of a transverse contrast-enhanced CT scan (5-mm section thickness, 130&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the level of the left upper divisional bronchus shows a 19-mm-sized peripheral nodule (arrow) in the left lower lobe. (b) Integrated PET/CT scan shows high FDG uptake (arrow) within the tumor (SUV<sub>max</sub>, 10.7).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002806"/></fig>
<fig id="F7" position="float"><label><italic>Figure 7</italic></label><caption><p>A 39-year-old woman with small cell lung carcinoma (limited disease). (a) A mediastinal window image of a transverse contrast-enhanced CT scan (5-mm section thickness, 130&#x02009;mAs) obtained at the subcarinal area shows an enlarged lymph node in the subcarinal and left hilar areas (arrows). (b) Integrated PET/CT scan shows high FDG uptake (arrows) within the nodes (SUV<sub>max</sub>, 15.7).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ci07002807"/></fig></p></sec><sec><title>Correlation with tumor staging and prognosis</title><p>As for the relationship between the maximum SUVs of pulmonary NE tumors and tumor stages, Chong <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup> reported that there is no significant positive correlation between the maximum SUV of primary tumors and tumor stage of carcinoids and LCNECs. In addition, the difference in maximum SUV between limited and extensive stages of SCLCs is not statistically significant. Therefore, the estimation of maximum SUVs in pulmonary NE tumors seems to be not helpful in the initial differentiation of early from advanced stages of disease.</p><p>However, the maximum SUV appears to be related to the patients&#x02019; survival. Chong <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup> found a significant negative correlation between the initial maximum SUVs of LCNECs and SCLCs and patients&#x02019; survival. For example, a maximum SUV greater than 13.7 suggests relatively shorter survival time for patients with LCNEC and those with SCLC. Pandit <italic>et al</italic>.<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]</sup> reported that PET of patients with SCLC is useful for predicting prognosis, especially among treated patients. After-treatment survival in PET-positive cases is significantly worse than in PET-negative cases.</p></sec><sec><title>Accuracy of tumor staging</title><p>Accurate tumor staging, particularly accurate detection of N1&#x02013;N3 metastatic lesions or extrathoracic tumor involvement is a determining factor in treatment modality and patient prognoses. According to a report<sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]</sup>, in LCNEC, integrated PET/CT and standalone CT both showed similar and high accuracy in predicting the presence of N1 and N2 metastasis. However, PET/CT was more effective for identifying N3 (supraclavicular) disease and extrathoracic (bone) metastasis.</p><p>Accurate staging is also important for patients with a SCLC. Patients with limited disease are treated with chemoradiation therapy, whereas those with extensive disease usually receive chemotherapy alone. PET has been considered valuable for initial tumor staging and for treatment planning of SCLC. Stage evaluation using PET is accurate and it usually concurs with the final clinical stage determined by conventional methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Carcinoids show variable FDG uptake at PET depending on their mitotic figures and the extent of tumor proliferation. Most patients with a LCNEC show homogeneously high FDG uptake on PET scans. The maximum SUVs of NE tumors are significantly different for carcinoids, LCNECs and SCLCs (listed in order of increasing value). Integrated PET/CT is more accurate than standalone CT or conventional staging methods in detecting extrapulmonary metastatic lesions especially in LCNECs and SCLCs. Moreover, the maximum SUVs in LCNECs and SCLCs appear to be related to patient survival. Thus, integrated PET/CT is useful not only in characterizing and staging of pulmonary NE tumors but also in predicting patient prognoses in these tumors.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>This work was supported by the Korea Research Foundation Grant funded by the Korean government (MOEHRD) (KRF-2004-E00132).</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Linnoila</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsokos</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neuroendocrine tumors of the lung with proposed criteria for large-cell neuroendocrine carcinoma. An ultrastructural, immunohistochemical, and flow cytometric study of 35 cases</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>1991</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1709558</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rush</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Flieder</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Survival analysis of 200 pulmonary neuroendocrine tumors with clarification of criteria for atypical carcinoid and its separation from typical carcinoid</article-title><source>Am J Surg Pathol</source><year>1998</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>934</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9706973</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Patz</surname><given-names>EF</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of primary pulmonary carcinoid tumors using FDG PET</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>1998</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9574618</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wartski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy-Ladurie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Typical and atypical bronchopulmonary carcinoid tumors on FDG PET/CT imaging</article-title><source>Clin Nucl Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15483502</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Integrated PET/CT of pulmonary neuroendocrine tumors: diagnostic and prognostic implications</article-title><source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source><year>2007</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>1223</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17449764</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>MacManus</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rischin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of positron emission tomography on the management of patients with small-cell lung cancer: preliminary experience</article-title><source>Am J Clin Oncol</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15057156</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of [<sup>18</sup>F]FDG-PET imaging in small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><year>2003</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12483413</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Colby</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimosato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><source>Histological typing of lung and pleural tumors, </source><year>1999</year><edition>3rd ed. </edition><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>98</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosado de Christenson</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirejczyk</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thoracic carcinoids: radiologic-pathologic correlation</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>1999</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10336200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwon</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroendocrine tumors of the lung: clinical, pathologic, and imaging findings</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2006</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>AJCC.</collab></person-group><source> Cancer staging manual, </source><year>2002</year><edition>6th ed. </edition><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mountain</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dresler</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regional lymph node classification for lung cancer staging</article-title><source>Chest</source><year>1997</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1718</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9187199</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zelen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Keynote address on biostatistics and data retrieval</article-title><source>Cancer Chemother Rep</source><year>1973</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>42</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buck</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumstein</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of integrated FDG PET/CT imaging in pulmonary carcinoid tumors</article-title><source>J Intern Med</source><year>2006</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>545</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116005</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>





