<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4448568</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">24</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1102/1470-7330.2002.0038</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>European Institute of Oncology project for lung cancer screening</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bellomi</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>University of Milan, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>European Institute of Oncology, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2002</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; International Cancer Imaging Society 2002</copyright-statement></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; International Cancer Imaging Society 2002</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The opportunity of a screening for lung cancer has been debated for years, since the value of low-dose spiral CT in detecting small parenchymal lesions was demonstrated by ELCAP and other reports. I would like to present to ICIS members the first results of a preliminary study performed in Milan, even though complete data cannot be divulged prior to publication. These results could help in planning further studies or new protocols.</p><p>The study started in May 2000. 1036 volunteers, over 50 years of age, were enrolled who were either heavy smokers or ex-smokers with a history of more than 1 packet/day for more than 20 years. They have all been submitted to two yearly consecutive low-dose spiral CT chest examination (140 kVp, 40 mA, 2 : 1 pitch, with a slice thickness of 10 mm. Effective dose equivalent to patient was estimated 0.7 mSv).</p><p>The examined population had a mean age of 58 (range 50&#x02013;70), 742 males and 297 females, smoking on average 26 cigarettes a day for a mean of 37 years. 14% of volunteers had stopped smoking for a mean of 9 years.</p><p>After the first low-dose CT, 5.91% of volunteers were recalled for further investigations, as a pulmonary lesion greater than 5 mm was detected. Nodules smaller than 5 mm were not considered for diagnostic work-up: at the second year CT only 1/151 of such nodules showed increased size (from 4.8 to 7.5 mm). This was an adenocarcinoma (T<sub>1</sub>N<sub>0</sub>).</p><p>Out of the 61 recalled subjects, 15 had non-nodular abnormalities and 46 a non-calcified nodular lesion. Diagnostic work-up was performed by HRCT, contrast enhancement evaluation (feasible in 65% of nodules, having positive basal density and homogeneous enhancement), PET (for lesions greater than 7 mm), 3 months&#x02019; follow-up with volumetric analysis and biopsy when necessary.</p><p>With regard to non-nodular lesions, HRCT, PET scan and follow-up (required in 5/15 cases) showed to be the most useful and accurate methods to reach the diagnosis. In one case only a VAT biopsy was performed on a benign lesion (a growing partially solid lesion, positive to PET scan, that proved to be due to post-inflammatory changes due to bronchiectasis).</p><p>The definitive diagnosis of non-calcified nodules was reached in 58% of cases on the basis of HRCT morphology and evaluation of nodular density (when lower than 0 H.U; considered benign): no benign case was biopsied or subjected to surgery; a false-negative diagnosis was due to a small apical nodule, diagnosed as a scar, but the lesion increased from 8 to 15 mm in diameter at the second year low-dose CT. This was a T1N0 adenocarcinoma.</p><p>The results of contrast enhancement and PET agreed in 22% of cases, leading to diagnosis: we had two false-positive diagnoses (an intraparenchymal inflammatory node and a MALT lymphoma) and one false-negative (an adenocarcinoma diagnosed 3 months later on the basis of its growth, evaluated at HRCT due to its irregular morphology).</p><p>Follow-up for evaluation of nodule growth was required to reach a diagnosis in 22% of recalled patients: all the diagnoses, but one, were confirmed by operation (in malignant cases) or by the 1 year follow-up. Only one case of a regular round and smooth 8 mm nodule, with indeterminate contrast enhancement and PET negative, grew from 3.42 to 5.25 mm<sup>3</sup> in 6 months and was submitted to VAT biopsy. This was a hamartoma.</p><p>Only 7% of the recalled patients with benign lesions were submitted to invasive procedures.</p><p>Preliminary results confirm the ability of low-dose CT to detect small parenchymal lesions. The recall rate is low, considering that only nodules greater than 5 mm are submitted to follow-up, and this seems to be justified by our results. The use of contrast enhancement and PET scan to characterize the lesions reduces the need of follow-up and of invasive procedures.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>This paper is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cancerimaging.org">http://www.cancerimaging.org</ext-link>. In the event of a change in the URL address, please use the DOI provided to locate the paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>