<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="abstract" xml:lang="en"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cancer Imaging</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cancer Imaging</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1740-5025</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1470-7330</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4242100</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1470-7330-14-S1-O25</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1470-7330-14-S1-O25</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oral Presentation</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Session: Evaluation of lung nodules: role of PET/CT</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Bellomi</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>massimo.bellomi@ieo.it</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Rampinelli</surname><given-names>Cristiano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Veronesi</surname><given-names>Giulia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Imaging and Radiological Sciences, European Institute of Oncology. Via Ripamonti 435, 20141 Milano, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Thoracic Surgery, European Institute of Oncology. Via Ripamonti 435, 20141 Milano, Italy</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><supplement><named-content content-type="supplement-title">Proceedings of the International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</named-content><named-content content-type="supplement-sponsor">Publication charges for this supplement were funded through the International Cancer Imaging Society by support received from Siemens AG, Healthcare Sector, Imaging and Therapy Division.</named-content></supplement><fpage>O25</fpage><lpage>O25</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Bellomi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bellomi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.cancerimagingjournal.com/content/14/S1/O25"/><conference><conf-date>9-11 October 2014</conf-date><conf-name>International Cancer Imaging Society (ICIS) 14th Annual Teaching Course</conf-name><conf-loc>Heidelberg, Germany</conf-loc></conference></article-meta></front><body><sec><title/><p>Computed Tomographic (CT) screening for lung cancer remains controversial, although the National Lung Screening Trial (NLST) found that low dose CT (LDCT) reduced lung cancer mortality by about 20% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>], the high rate of indeterminate and false positive lung nodules was worrying.</p><p>The diagnostic work-up of CT nodules considers size (diameter or volume), characteristics (density, morphology, homogeneity) and volume doubling time (VDT), but several studies have investigated the ability of positron emission tomography (PET) to characterize nodules, although its role in diagnostic algorithms for screening-detected nodules has not been defined.</p><p>The first PET study with [<sup>18</sup>F]fluorodeoxyglucose to characterize indeterminate nodules outside screening was published in 2001 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In a previous study on PET-CT at baseline screening, we found an overall sensitivity of 88% for diagnosing malignancy, while for solid nodules &#x0003e;10 mm, sensitivity was 100%, suggesting PET-CT as an alternative to invasive procedures in the screening setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. When assessing the ability of PET-CT to diagnose indeterminate nodules detected during the subsequent years of the screening and analyzing 383 PET-CT examinations performed over 6 study years of screening, the sensitivity, specificity and accuracy of visually evaluated PET-CT, in distinguishing benign from malignant nodules, were 64%, 89% and 76% respectively. PET performance varied with nodule diameter (accuracy increased from 70% for nodules &#x0003c;10 mm to 82% for nodules &#x02265;15 mm) and nodule type (accuracy ranged from 88% for solid nodules to 46% for non-solid nodules).</p><p>We do not use FNAB routinely in our screening protocol. Typically we proceed to surgery when nodule characteristics, including VDT, often backed up by PET-CT, indicate malignancy. The disadvantage is that a preoperative pathological diagnosis is not available and a wedge resection with frozen section examination is required before radical surgery.</p><p>Nodules on PET-CT are commonly evaluated by semi-quantitative SUVbw max, which is operator independent, as well as by visual assessment of uptake by the nuclear medicine physician, whose experience can markedly influence the result. In our study we evaluated both methods and found visual assessment afforded higher accuracy (76%) than any SUV threshold with a good compromise between sensitivity (64%) and specificity (89%); while increasing the threshold from 1.5 to 2.5 decreased sensitivity (67% to 51%) and increased specificity (80% to 91%).</p><p>To conclude, PET-CT has high NPV for solid nodules &#x02265;15 mm, and high PPV for sub-solid nodules &#x0003c;10 mm, justifying its inclusion in the diagnostic work-up of indeterminate nodules identified on LDCT screening. It is more useful for nodules detected at baseline, while sensitivity is low for sub-solid nodules and nodules discovered after baseline: for these other diagnostic modalities, particularly VDT, are more useful.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>National Lung Screening Trial Research Team</collab><name><surname>Aberle</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapp</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Reduced lung-cancer mortality with low-dose computed tomographic screening</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21714641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Maclean</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuschner</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rydzak</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><article-title>Accuracy of positron emission tomography for diagnosis of pulmonary nodules and mass lesions; a meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2001</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>914</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.285.7.914</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11180735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Veronesi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellomi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Veronesi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Paganelli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maisonneuve</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanagatta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/><article-title>Role of positron emission tomography scanning in the management of lung nodules detected at baseline computed tomography screening</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>959</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2007.04.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17720408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>