<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Drug Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Drug Investig</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Drug Investigation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1173-2563</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1918</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25471739</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4281365</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">251</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40261-014-0251-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Short Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Remifentanil, Fentanyl, or the Combination in Surgical Procedures in the United States: Predictors of Use in Patients with Organ Impairment or Obesity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Sclar</surname><given-names>David Alexander</given-names></name><address><phone>(623) 572-3521</phone><email>dsclar@midwestern.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">College of Pharmacy, Midwestern University, Glendale, AZ USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Remifentanil has a rapid onset and short duration of action, predictable pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic profile, and unlike fentanyl, does not accumulate with repeated or prolonged administration. This study evaluated predictors of remifentanil use in surgical patients with renal or hepatic impairment, or obesity in the United States who received remifentanil, fentanyl, or the combination.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Data (2010) from the US Healthcare National Inpatient Database, State Inpatient Database, State Ambulatory Surgery Database, and private hospital and Medicaid databases were used in this analysis. Patients included had presence of hepatic or renal disease, and/or obesity and were &#x0003e;5 and &#x02264;80&#x000a0;years of age.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In 2010, 9,274 patients with renal impairment, 1,896 with hepatic impairment, and 6,278 with obesity were identified. The percentage of surgical patients diagnosed with renal disease, hepatic disease, or obesity who received remifentanil was 41, 28, and 35&#x000a0;%, respectively; 29, 17, and 22&#x000a0;% received both remifentanil and fentanyl, and 30, 55, and 43&#x000a0;% received fentanyl alone, respectively. In patients with renal or hepatic disease the probability of remifentanil use was greater for persons aged &#x0003e;50&#x000a0;years, with Medicare as primary payer, or who were diagnosed with obesity (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 all comparisons). In obese patients, the probability of remifentanil use was greater for persons aged &#x0003e;50&#x000a0;years or female (both <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05). For all 3 disease states, the probability of remifentanil use was lower for those receiving epidural anesthesia or with Medicaid as primary payer (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05 all comparisons).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Remifentanil in combination with fentanyl is used less than fentanyl in surgical patients with hepatic impairment or obesity. This is inconsistent with the fact that the pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic features of remifentanil suggest it is the preferred intraoperative opioid in these patients. Predictors of remifentanil use in patients with renal or hepatic impairment, or obesity include older age, obesity, and Medicare as primary payer. Remifentanil in combination with fentanyl was significantly less utilized than fentanyl in persons with Medicaid as primary payer even though there was a disproportionate enrollment of beneficiaries with renal or hepatic disease, or obesity in state Medicaid programs.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer International Publishing Switzerland 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="d30e186"><title>Key Points</title><p><table-wrap id="Taba"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">The pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic features of remifentanil would suggest that it is the preferred intraoperative opioid versus fentanyl in patients with renal impairment, hepatic impairment, or obesity; however, remifentanil alone or in combination with fentanyl is, in general, used less frequently than fentanyl.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Predictors of remifentanil use in patients with renal impairment, hepatic impairment, or obesity include older age, obesity, and Medicare as primary payer.</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Remifentanil in combination with fentanyl was used significantly less than fentanyl in surgical patients with Medicaid as primary payer even though there was a disproportionate enrollment of beneficiaries with renal or hepatic disease, or obesity in state Medicaid programs.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Remifentanil is a 4-anilidopiperidine &#x000b5;-opioid analgesic approved for use as an analgesic agent during induction and maintenance of general anesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It is a fentanyl derivative and its pharmacodynamic effects are, in general, similar to fentanyl and the other fentanyl cogeners [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, the pharmacokinetic profile of remifentanil is unique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Its metabolism is independent of the liver and kidneys, unlike other opioids, and it is rapidly eliminated via blood and tissue nonspecific esterases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The primary metabolic pathway is de-esterification of remifentanil to remifentanil acid, a relatively inactive carboxylic acid metabolite with 300- to 4,600-fold less potency than the parent compound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Almost 90&#x000a0;% of the drug recovered in urine is remifentanil acid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Remifentanil is not metabolized by plasma cholinesterase (pseudocholinesterase) and is not appreciably metabolized by the liver or lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Remifentanil is rapidly absorbed and distributed throughout the body with a mean volume of distribution at steady state of 350&#x000a0;mL/kg and a clearance of approximately 40&#x000a0;mL/min/kg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p>Remifentanil is considered a true short-acting opioid, with a rapid onset of action of approximately 1&#x000a0;min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] and a short offset of action of approximately 5&#x02013;10&#x000a0;min [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Its offset of action is not affected by duration of drug infusion, and remifentanil does not accumulate with repeated and prolonged administration, unlike other opioids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The context-sensitive half-time of remifentanil is approximately 3&#x02013;4&#x000a0;min irrespective of infusion duration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>These features of remifentanil would be of benefit to certain populations of patients, especially at-risk patients where drug clearance may be substantially reduced due to illness, organ dysfunction, or concomitant therapy. The pharmacokinetics of remifentanil are not affected in any clinically significant way in several at-risk patient groups. No differences are seen in the pharmacokinetic profile of patients with or without renal impairment, or in patients with end-stage renal disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The pharmacokinetics of remifentanil and its major metabolite, remifentanil acid, are unchanged in patients with severe hepatic impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In obese patients, when dosing is adjusted to ideal body weight, no differences in pharmacokinetics are observed between obese and lean patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p>Remifentanil has been shown to be an effective and safe analgesic component in the anesthetic management of patients with renal impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], hepatic impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], and obesity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. For these patients, where rapid titration and precise control of analgesia in response to hemodynamic fluctuations is essential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], as well as rapid and predictable emergence from anesthesia regardless of duration of anesthesia, remifentanil may be better suited than fentanyl as an adjunct in their general anesthesia requirements.</p><p>Fentanyl is widely distributed in the body, with a volume of distribution at steady state of 4&#x000a0;L/kg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. It is extensively metabolized by the liver with a high hepatic clearance (approaching that of hepatic blood flow) and a high hepatic extraction ratio (0.8&#x02013;1.0) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Unlike remifentanil, the context-sensitive half-time of fentanyl is dependent on infusion duration, with accumulation and prolongation of effect increasing as infusion time increases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The time required for a 50&#x000a0;% reduction in the effect-site concentration of fentanyl is over 65 times greater than that of remifentanil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>The following study evaluated predictors of remifentanil use, fentanyl use, or the combination of the two drugs in surgical patients with renal impairment, hepatic impairment, and/or obesity in the United States.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Data Source</title><p>This study evaluated administrative claims data (January 1, 2010, to December 31, 2010) from the US Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project&#x02019;s National Inpatient Database, State Inpatient Database, and State Ambulatory Surgery Database (US Department of Health and Human Services, Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and from MarketScan<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Hospital Drug Database and MarketScan<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> State Medicaid Database.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study Population</title><p>Patients aged &#x0003e;5 and &#x02264;80&#x000a0;years with renal impairment, hepatic impairment, and/or obesity were identified by international classification of disease (ICD-9-CM) codes: 584.x-585.x (renal impairment), 570.x-573.x (hepatic impairment), and 278.x (body mass index &#x0003e;30&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup> for obesity) from 8 categories of surgical procedures identified by ICD-9-CM and/or current procedure terminology codes: cardiac, general, gynecology, orthopedic, otolaryngology, neurology, thoracic, and vascular [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Patients were included in the study if they received remifentanil hydrochloride, fentanyl, or a combination of remifentanil HCL and fentanyl for surgical procedures. Patients were excluded if they were transferred to another facility.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Assessments</title><p>Baseline characteristics and other factors that may be predictive of patients receiving remifentanil, fentanyl, or the combination of these two drugs were evaluated including age, sex, disease state (renal impairment, hepatic impairment, obesity), comorbidities (identified by ICD-9-CM codes), healthcare plan (Medicaid, Medicare, or private), use of epidural drugs, and facility characteristics (hospital or outpatient; bed size, location [urban; rural]; ownership).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Hierarchical mixed-effects logistic regression analysis was used to discern factors predictive of receipt of remifentanil, fentanyl, or the combination in patients with renal impairment, hepatic impairment, and/or obesity. The a priori significance level was <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05. Odds ratio (OR) and 95&#x000a0;% confidence intervals (CI) were adjusted for patient-level Charlson/Deyo score (index for predicting mortality by comorbid conditions) and facility characteristics (public/private, teaching/nonteaching, urban/rural). Analysis was conducted using SAS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (version 9.1.3; SAS Research Institute, Cary, NC, USA), and STATA<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (version 12; STATA Corporation, LP, College Station, TX, USA). Data on percentage of patients receiving remifentanil, fentanyl, or the combination are presented using descriptive statistics only.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 9,274 patients were identified in 2010 with renal impairment, 1,896 with hepatic impairment, and 6,278 with obesity (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). There were slightly more male than female patients in each of the disease groups, and the mean age of patients was highest in the renal-impairment patients and lowest in the obese patients.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Patient demographics and baseline characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Variable</th><th align="left">Renal disease<sup>a</sup> (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9,274)</th><th align="left">Hepatic disease<sup>a</sup> (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1,896)</th><th align="left">Obesity<sup>a</sup> (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6,278)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Age (years)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Mean &#x000b1;SD</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="left">53.5&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.5</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">49.2&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.8</td><td char="&#x000b1;" align="char">39.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;15.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Median</td><td char="." align="left">53.0</td><td char="." align="char">48.0</td><td char="." align="char">37.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Range</td><td align="left">32&#x02013;74</td><td align="left">21&#x02013;80</td><td align="left">16&#x02013;74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Sex (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Male</td><td char="." align="left">58</td><td char="." align="char">64</td><td char="." align="char">53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Payer (%)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Medicaid</td><td char="." align="left">76</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">51</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Medicare</td><td char="." align="left">17</td><td char="." align="char">19</td><td char="." align="char">22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Private</td><td char="." align="left">7</td><td char="." align="char">18</td><td char="." align="char">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Epidural anesthesia</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes (%)</td><td char="." align="left">31</td><td char="." align="char">28</td><td char="." align="char">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Obesity (278.x)<sup>a</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Yes (%)</td><td char="." align="left">24</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<sup>a</sup>Categorized by ICD-9-CM codes: 570.x-573.x for hepatic disease, 584.x-585.x for renal disease, 278.x (body mass index &#x0003e;30&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>) for obesity</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Of the patients identified with renal impairment, 41&#x000a0;% received remifentanil, 29&#x000a0;% received a combination of remifentanil and fentanyl, and 30&#x000a0;% received fentanyl alone (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Twenty-eight percent of the patients identified with hepatic impairment received remifentanil, while 17&#x000a0;% received the combination of the two drugs and 55&#x000a0;% received fentanyl alone. Among the obese patients, 35, 22, and 43&#x000a0;% received remifentanil, a combination of remifentanil and fentanyl, or fentanyl alone, respectively.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Percentage of renal-impaired, hepatic-impaired, or obese patients receiving remifentanil, fentanyl, or a combination of remifentanil and fentanyl</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40261_2014_251_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Predictors of Remifentanil Use in Surgical Patients with Renal Impairment, Hepatic Impairment, or Obesity</title><p>In patients with renal impairment or hepatic impairment, the probability of remifentanil or combination remifentanil and fentanyl use versus fentanyl alone was significantly greater for patients aged &#x0003e;50&#x000a0;years, diagnosed with obesity, or having Medicare as their primary payer (relative to private payer) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The probability of remifentanil or combination remifentanil and fentanyl use versus fentanyl in both groups of patients was significantly lower for those receiving epidural anesthesia and for those having Medicaid as the primary payer.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics predictive of remifentanil or combination of remifentanil and fentanyl use versus fentanyl alone in renal-impaired, hepatic-impaired, and obese patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Characteristic</th><th align="left" colspan="3">OR and 95&#x000a0;% CI<sup>a</sup>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Renal disease (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9,274)</th><th align="left">Hepatic disease (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1,896)</th><th align="left">Obesity BMI&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;30 (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6,278)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Age, years</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x0003c;50</td><td align="left">1.37 (1.13&#x02013;1.58)*</td><td align="left">1.21 (1.08&#x02013;1.46)*</td><td align="left">1.49 (1.28&#x02013;1.62)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02265;50</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Sex</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Women</td><td align="left">1.05 (0.93&#x02013;1.12)</td><td align="left">0.92 (0.85&#x02013;1.13)</td><td align="left">1.23 (1.07&#x02013;1.45)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Men</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Payer</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Medicaid</td><td align="left">0.78 (0.51&#x02013;0.88)*</td><td align="left">0.85 (0.63&#x02013;0.91)*</td><td align="left">0.81 (0.64&#x02013;0.93)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Medicare</td><td align="left">1.94 (1.56&#x02013;2.33)*</td><td align="left">1.69 (1.37&#x02013;1.85)*</td><td align="left">0.93 (0.78&#x02013;1.06)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;Private (reference)<sup>b</sup>
</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Epidural anesthesia</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">0.42 (0.27&#x02013;0.61)*</td><td align="left">0.64 (0.52&#x02013;0.79)*</td><td align="left">0.75 (0.61&#x02013;0.83)*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Obesity</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;1&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Yes</td><td align="left">1.19 (1.07&#x02013;1.35)*</td><td align="left">1.36 (1.18&#x02013;1.63)*</td><td align="left">N/A</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;0&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;No</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>
<italic>BMI</italic> body mass index, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval, <italic>OR</italic> odds ratio</p><p>*<italic>&#x000a0;p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>Adjusted for patient-level Charlson/Deyo score (index for predicting mortality by comorbid conditions); facility characteristics (public/private; teaching/nonteaching; urban/rural)</p><p>
<sup>b</sup>OR and 95&#x000a0;% CI relative to private payer (e.g., managed care; health maintenance organization)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>The probability of remifentanil or combination remifentanil and fentanyl use versus fentanyl alone was significantly greater for obese patients that were female and aged &#x0003e;50&#x000a0;years, (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and significantly lower for obese patients receiving epidural anesthesia or having Medicaid as their primary payer.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results of this study found that remifentanil, with or without fentanyl, was used in 70&#x000a0;% of the surgical patients with renal impairment, 45&#x000a0;% of those with hepatic impairment, and 57&#x000a0;% of those with obesity. The numbers for patients with hepatic impairment or obesity were lower than expected. In severe liver failure patients, single bolus or low-dose fentanyl can be used; however, accumulation of fentanyl is a concern with repeated or high doses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The metabolism of remifentanil is unchanged in severe liver disease patients as metabolism is via tissue and blood esterases, making it an attractive opioid component of the anesthetic regimen for patients with hepatic impairment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p>Obesity was found to be a positive predictor of remifentanil use. Obesity is associated with a number of comorbid conditions that affect the administration of anesthesia including restrictive lung disease, obstructive sleep apnea, diabetes, hypertension, pulmonary hypertension, cardiomegaly, liver disease, and delayed gastric emptying [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Obese patients also have a higher prevalence of cardiovascular disease, including hypertension, arrhythmias, stroke, heart failure, and coronary artery disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], which can contribute to difficulties in maintaining a stable circulatory status in these patients. Airway procedures may be more difficult in these patients and they may have more difficulty breathing during anesthesia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Operating time may be longer in an obese patient due to technical challenges faced by the surgeon when the anatomy is distorted or hidden behind excessive fat.&#x000a0;The longer exposure to general anesthesia may cause delayed awakening of the patient or lead to over-sedation and subsequent postoperative complications, including respiratory depression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Use of remifentanil has been shown to result in shorter extubation times, earlier mobilization of patients, and potential minimization of postoperative complications such as respiratory depression or hypoxemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p>These features are also important for patients with organ impairment, many of whom are advanced in age. Elderly patients have reduced organ functional reserves and reduced compensatory mechanisms in response to stress, and medications are cleared from the body at a slower rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. There is an increased risk for postoperative complications in the elderly that includes adverse drug reactions, postoperative cognitive dysfunction, and delirium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Use of drugs associated with delirium in the elderly such as long-acting opioids, benzodiazepines and anticholinergics should be limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. It is important that the anesthetic regimen used for elderly patients provides intraoperative stability combined with rapid emergence to minimize the incidence of postoperative cognitive impairment and side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Recovery time with remifentanil-nitrous oxide anesthesia has been shown to be shorter than with fentanyl-isoflurane-nitrous oxide anesthesia in a study of elderly patients aged 65&#x000a0;years and older undergoing spinal surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Patients receiving the remifentanil-based regimen had shorter time to eye opening, extubation, and spontaneous respiration versus the fentanyl-based regimen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Such results support the finding from this study that older age (&#x0003e;50&#x000a0;years) is a predictor of remifentanil use.</p><p>Remifentanil, alone or in combination with fentanyl, was used significantly less than fentanyl in patients for whom the primary payer was Medicaid, even though there was a disproportionate enrollment of beneficiaries with renal or hepatic disease and/or obesity in state Medicaid programs. These payor results would suggest that access to remifentanil may be an issue for low-income patients. Perceived differences in cost for remifentanil versus fentanyl may be a barrier to remifentanil use. The drug cost of remifentanil is higher than that of fentanyl; however, drug costs are only a small part of total healthcare costs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Synergistic effects of anesthetic drugs and use of concomitant drugs all affect total costs. In addition, differences in time the patient is in surgery and differences in recovery and postoperative side effects all affect hospital, surgical, and postoperative expenditures.</p><p>Unfortunately, hardly any studies published in the United States evaluate in a comprehensive manner overall hospital or all anesthesia-related cost comparisons between remifentanil and fentanyl. The few existing American studies that analyze other costs in addition to opioid drug costs do suggest that when other costs are taken into account, such as total hospital costs or total anesthesia-related drug costs, the two drugs are comparable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p>Engoren et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] evaluated the cost of fast-track cardiac surgery in 90 adult patients who received remifentanil-based, sufentanil-based, or fentanyl-based anesthesia. The investigators found that although the median opioid and anesthetic costs of remifentanil were higher than those of fentanyl, total hospital cost (sum of direct variable cost for each item and service used by the patient from preoperative period through to discharge or death) was comparable between the two groups. No significant differences were found in median ventilator times, intensive care unit (ICU) stays, and hospital stays between the anesthesia regimens.</p><p>Reddy et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] evaluated the cost of coronary artery bypass graft surgery with remifentanil-based anesthesia versus fentanyl-based anesthesia in 59 adult patients. Anesthetic costs were higher for remifentanil versus fentanyl; however, pulmonary function testing costs, recovery room costs, and ward costs were lower with remifentanil than with fentanyl. Length of stay and other costs such as medical and surgical supplies, operating room, ICU, laboratory, radiology, pharmacy, and transfusion costs were similar between the two treatments. Taken together, the total costs of remifentanil and fentanyl were comparable.</p><p>A retrospective cost analysis of a controlled multicenter clinical study evaluating patients (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;63) undergoing craniotomy found that total anesthesia drug-related costs were less with remifentanil than with fentanyl for all price considerations except at the lowest average wholesale price (AWP) of fentanyl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Total drug costs were based on a range of AWPs for the two opioids as well as all concomitant drugs used in the intraoperative and immediate postoperative periods that were related to the choice of opioid during surgery.</p><p>For certain short duration surgeries, anesthetic costs alone may be comparable between remifentanil and fentanyl. In a study by Jellish et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], the anesthetic cost of remifentanil-based total intravenous anesthesia (TIVA) anesthesia supplemented with low-dose propofol in patients undergoing otologic procedures (1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;h procedures) was $69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7 versus $66&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5 for propofol-based TIVA with supplemental fentanyl. Patients receiving the remifentanil-based anesthesia had better hemodynamic stability, less movement, and faster emergence from surgery. Postoperative pain scores were mild for both groups, but higher in the remifentanil group. All other variables examined were similar, including incidence and severity of postoperative nausea and vomiting, mean time to hospital discharge, ambulation without dizziness and other recovery parameters, and patient satisfaction with anesthesia.</p><p>More studies are needed that evaluate aggregate costs of pharmacotherapy with remifentanil versus fentanyl, not only in higher-risk patients such as those with renal and hepatic impairment and obese patients, but also in certain surgeries where the pharmacokinetic benefits of remifentanil over other opioids may prove advantageous.</p><p>A limitation of this study is the retrospective nature of the analysis. ICD-9-codes were used to identify patients with renal impairment, including those with acute renal failure. There is no differentiation between presurgical or postsurgical occurrence of acute renal failure. It is possible that some of the patients included in this analysis had this condition as a consequence of surgery. Due to the fast offset of effect of remifentanil, another analgesic is required prior to discontinuation of remifentanil general anesthesia if postoperative pain is anticipated and remifentanil infusion is not continued into the postoperative period. Fentanyl may have been used for postoperative pain and may be included in the fentanyl plus remifentanil group; however, no separate evaluation of this parameter was conducted.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The type of analgesic pharmacotherapy should be predicated on the clinical presentation of a given patient (e.g., hepatic disease, renal disease, obesity) and the pharmacokinetic and metabolic profile of an agent.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by Mylan Specialty L.P. (Canonsburg, PA). The author acknowledges Stem Scientific (Lyndhurst, NJ) for writing assistance funded by Mylan Specialty, L.P. Dr. Sclar has served as a consultant to Mylan Specialty, L.P.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics. A preliminary appraisal</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacokinet.</source><year>1995</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003088-199529020-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7586903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ultiva<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (remifentanil) [package insert]. Canonsburg, PA: Mylan Specialty L.P.; revised March 2009. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ultiva.com/files/Ultiva-Prescribing-Info.pdf">http://www.ultiva.com/files/Ultiva-Prescribing-Info.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 11 Nov 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>PSA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamiyama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preliminary pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of an ultra-short-acting opioids: Remifentanil (GI87084B)</article-title><source>Anesth Anal.</source><year>1993</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1040</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1213/00000539-199311000-00028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil. A review of its use during the induction and maintenance of general anaesthesia</article-title><source>Drugs.</source><year>2005</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1793</fpage><lpage>1823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003495-200565130-00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16114980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemmens</surname><given-names>HJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiset</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The pharmacokinetics of the new short-acting opioids remifentanil (GI87084B) in healthy adult male volunteers</article-title><source>Anesthesia.</source><year>1993</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199311000-00004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Westmoreland</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebel</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hug</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of remifentanil (GI87084B) and its major metabolite (GI90291) in patients undergoing elective inpatient surgery</article-title><source>Anesthesia.</source><year>1993</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199311000-00005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitsiu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bodenham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of remifentanil and its major metabolite, remifentanil acid, in ICU patients with renal impairment</article-title><source>Br J Anesth.</source><year>2004</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aeh086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shlugman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dershwitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of remifentanil in persons with renal failure compared with healthy volunteers</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther.</source><year>1997</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9103501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dershwitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoke</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosow</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of remifetnanil in volunteer subjects with severe liver disease</article-title><source>Anesthesiology.</source><year>1996</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199604000-00008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8638835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navapurkar</surname><given-names>VU</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Muir</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of remifentanil during liver transplantation</article-title><source>Br J Anaesthesia.</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>881</fpage><lpage>886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/81.6.881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Huizinga</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil pharmacokinetics in obese versus lean patients</article-title><source>Anesthesiology.</source><year>1998</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>573</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000542-199809000-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9743391</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahaba</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>von Klobucar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rehak</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Total intravenous anesthesia with remifentanil, propofol and cisatracurium in end-stage renal failure</article-title><source>Can J Anesth.</source><year>1999</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>696</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF03013962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10442969</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Picard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Marti</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tassonyi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of remifentanil in a patient with chronic hepatic failure</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth.</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/81.2.265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9813539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Baerdemaeker</surname><given-names>LEC</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pattyn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortier</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Struys</surname><given-names>MMRF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of intraoperative opioid on postoperative pain and pulmonary function after laparoscopic gastric banding: remifentanil TCI vs sufentanil TCI in morbid obesity</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth.</source><year>2007</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bja/aem164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17606479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaszynski</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strzelczyk</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaszynski</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Post-anesthesia recovery after infusion of propofol with remifentanil or alfentanil or fentanyl in morbidly obese patients</article-title><source>Obesity Surgery.</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1381/096089204323013488</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15130225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitten</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil infusion facilitates early recovery for obese outpatients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy</article-title><source>Anesth Analg.</source><year>2000</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1111</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000539-200005000-00020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10781462</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gislason</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Raeder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast-track surgery for bariatric laparoscopic gastric bypass with focus on anaesthesia and peri-operative care. Experience with 500 cases</article-title><source>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand.</source><year>2008</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>1394</fpage><lpage>1399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2008.01782.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19025533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bellamy MC, Margarson MP. Designing intelligent anesthesia for a changing patient demographic: a consensus statement to provide guidance for specialist and non-specialist anesthetists written by members of and endorsed by the Society for Obesity and Bariatric Anaesthesia (SOBA). Perioperative Medicine. 2013;2:12. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.perioperativemedicinejournal.com/content/2/1/12">http://www.perioperativemedicinejournal.com/content/2/1/12</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgery in the patient with liver disease</article-title><source>Mayo Clin Proc.</source><year>1999</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4065/74.6.593</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10377935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagener</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brentjens</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anesthetic concerns in patients presenting with renal failure</article-title><source>Anesthesiology Clin.</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anclin.2010.01.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sublimaze<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (fentanyl citrate) [package insert]. Macquarie Park, Australia: Janssen-Cilag Pty Ltd; revised January 31, 2013. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.janssen.com.au/files/Products/Sublimaze_PI.pdf?11260f5eae8a24dd0a2656da6393e664">http://www.janssen.com.au/files/Products/Sublimaze_PI.pdf?11260f5eae8a24dd0a2656da6393e664</ext-link>. Accessed 7 Nov 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">US Department of Health and Human Services, Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality. US Healthcare Cost and Utilization Project&#x02019;s National Inpatient database. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ahrq.gov/research/data/hcup/index.html">http://www.ahrq.gov/research/data/hcup/index.html</ext-link>. Accessed 3 June 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sclar DA. Predictors of remifentanil use in surgical patients with renal or hepatic insufficiency and/or obesity in the United States. In: Proceedings of the 67th Annual Post-Graduate Assembly in Anesthesiology. New York, New York. December 14, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaja</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McNicol</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisley</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anaesthesia for patients with liver disease</article-title><source>Contin Educ Anaesth Crit Care Pain.</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjaceaccp/mkp040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Anesthesia secrets</source><year>2011</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Mosby Elsevier</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sinha AC, Eckmann DM. Anesthesia for bariatric surgery. In: Miller RD, editor. Miller&#x02019;s anesthesia, 7th ed. Location: Philadelphia: Churchill Livingstone Elsevier; 2010. p. 2089.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sieber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauldine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geriatric anesthesia</article-title><source>Miller&#x02019;s anesthesia</source><year>2010</year><edition>7</edition><publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Churchill Livingstone Elsevier</publisher-name><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bekker</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Berklayd</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Osborn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yarmush</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Turndorf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The recovery of cognitive function after remifentanil-nitrous oxide anesthesia is faster than after an isoflurane-nitrous oxide-fentanyl combination in elderly patients</article-title><source>Anesth Analg.</source><year>2000</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10866897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hogue S, Reese PR, Munshi O, Young T. Cost analysis of remifentanil and fentanyl for neurosurgical aesthesia. Am J Health-Syst Pharm. 1999;56:55&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engoren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luther</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenn-Buderer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of fentanyl, sufentanil, and remifentanil for fast-track cardiac anesthesia</article-title><source>Anesth Analg.</source><year>2001</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>859</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000539-200110000-00011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11574346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Feret</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulicki</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Quercia</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cost analysis of fentanyl and remifentanil in coronary artery bypass graft surgery without cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title><source>J Clin Pharm Ther.</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2710.2002.00401.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11975697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jellish</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonetti</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluder</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdoch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Remifentanil-based anesthesia versus propofol technique for otologic surgical procedures</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg.</source><year>2000</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>222</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0194-5998(00)70243-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10652394</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>