<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Drug Investig</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Drug Investig</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Drug Investigation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1173-2563</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1179-1918</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24178236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3880470</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">146</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40261-013-0146-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetics of Mirabegron, a &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>-Adrenoceptor Agonist for Treatment of Overactive Bladder, in Healthy Japanese Male Subjects: Results from Single- and Multiple-Dose Studies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Iitsuka</surname><given-names>Hiromi</given-names></name><address><email>hiromi.iitsuka@astellas.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tokuno</surname><given-names>Tomoaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amada</surname><given-names>Yoko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matsushima</surname><given-names>Hiroshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katashima</surname><given-names>Masataka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sawamoto</surname><given-names>Taiji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takusagawa</surname><given-names>Shin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Gelderen</surname><given-names>Marcel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Takanori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miyahara</surname><given-names>Hideo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Astellas Pharma Inc., 3-17-1, Hasune, Itabashi-ku, Tokyo, 174-8612 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Astellas Pharma Inc., Osaka, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Astellas Pharma Europe BV, Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Nishikumamoto Hospital, Medical Co. LTA, Kumamoto, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Toyohashi SOZO University, Aichi, Japan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Global Project Management, Astellas Pharma Inc., 3-17-1, Hasune, Itabashi-ku, Tokyo, 174-8612 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2013</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Mirabegron is a human &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>-adrenoceptor agonist for the treatment of overactive bladder. The pharmacokinetic profile of mirabegron has been extensively characterized in healthy Caucasian subjects.</p></sec><sec><title>Objective</title><p>The objective of this study was to evaluate the pharmacokinetics, dose-proportionality, and tolerability of mirabegron following single and multiple oral doses in healthy Japanese male subjects. The results were compared with those reported in non-Japanese (primarily Caucasian) subjects.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Two studies were conducted. In a single-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, single- and multiple-ascending dose study (Study 1), mirabegron oral controlled absorption system (OCAS) tablets were administered at single doses of 50, 100, 200, 300, and 400&#x000a0;mg, with eight subjects (six active, two placebo) per dose group (Part I), and once daily for 7&#x000a0;days at 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg with 12 subjects (eight active, four placebo) per group (Part II). In an open-label, three-period, single-ascending dose study (Study 2), mirabegron OCAS was administered to 12 subjects at 25, 50, and 100&#x000a0;mg in an intra-subject dose-escalation design. Plasma and/or urine samples were collected up to 72&#x000a0;h after the first and last dose and analyzed for mirabegron. Pharmacokinetic parameters were determined using non-compartmental methods. Tolerability assessments included physical examinations, vital signs, 12-lead electrocardiogram, clinical laboratory tests (biochemistry, hematology, and urinalysis), and adverse event (AE) monitoring.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Forty and 24 young male subjects completed Part I and II, respectively, of Study 1. Twelve young males completed Study 2. After single oral doses (25&#x02013;400&#x000a0;mg), maximum plasma concentrations (<italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>) were reached at approximately 2.8&#x02013;4.0&#x000a0;h postdose. Plasma exposure (<italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve) of mirabegron increased more than dose proportionally at single doses of 25&#x02013;100&#x000a0;mg and approximately dose proportionally at high doses of 300 and 400&#x000a0;mg. A more than dose proportional increase in plasma exposure was noted in the body of the same individual. Mirabegron accumulated twofold upon once-daily dosing relative to single-dose data. Steady state was reached within 7&#x000a0;days. Mirabegron was generally well-tolerated at single doses up to 400&#x000a0;mg and multiple doses up to 200&#x000a0;mg. The AE with the highest incidence was increased pulse rate at 400&#x000a0;mg in Study 1.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Mirabegron OCAS exhibits similar single- and multiple-dose pharmacokinetic characteristics and deviations from dose proportionality in healthy Japanese male subjects compared with those observed in non-Japanese (primarily Caucasian) subjects in previous studies.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer International Publishing Switzerland 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Mirabegron is an agonist of the human &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>-adrenoceptor, discovered by Astellas Pharma Inc. in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>-Adrenoceptors have been shown to play a role in the relaxation of the urinary bladder detrusor smooth muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Mirabegron relaxes the detrusor smooth muscle during the storage phase of the urinary bladder fill-void cycle by activation of &#x003b2;<sub>3</sub>-adrenoceptor, which increases bladder capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Mirabegron has been approved in Japan, the USA, and the EU for the treatment of overactive bladder (OAB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and is the first of a new class of oral compounds with a different mode of action than antimuscarinic medications, the current mainstay treatment for patients with OAB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>The pharmacokinetic profile of mirabegron after single and multiple oral doses has been reported in cohorts of Western, primarily Caucasian, healthy adult subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Mirabegron demonstrated a greater than dose-proportional increase in maximum plasma concentration (<italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>) and area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve (AUC) after single and multiple oral doses, which was due to an increase in absolute bioavailability with increasing dose (from 25&#x000a0;% at 25&#x000a0;mg to 40&#x000a0;% at 100&#x000a0;mg) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Mirabegron was cleared by multiple mechanisms (renal and possibly biliary excretion of unchanged drug, and metabolism by multiple enzymes), with no single predominating clearance pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In vitro studies suggested a role for the polymorphic cytochrome P450 (CYP) 2D6 enzyme in the oxidative metabolism of mirabegron, in addition to CYP3A [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], although in vivo results indicated that these isozymes play a limited role in the overall elimination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In addition, body weight is an important consideration when comparing different ethnic populations, as body weight has been shown to affect mirabegron pharmacokinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p>As part of the clinical development program in Japan, we conducted two studies using single doses of mirabegron 25&#x02013;400&#x000a0;mg and multiple doses of 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg/day in healthy Japanese male subjects to evaluate the pharmacokinetics, dose-proportionality, and tolerability of mirabegron after single and multiple oral doses. The pharmacokinetic results obtained in Japanese subjects in these studies were subsequently compared with those previously reported for non-Japanese (primarily Caucasian) healthy male subjects.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Both studies were conducted in accordance with the ethical principles based on the Declaration of Helsinki [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and Good Clinical Practice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], as defined by the Ministerial Ordinance concerning the standards for the implementation of clinical studies on pharmaceutical products, and the regulations stipulated in the Japanese Pharmaceutical Affairs Law. The studies were conducted at two centers and approved by institutional review boards.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Subjects</title><p>Subjects were eligible for inclusion in the studies if they met the following criteria: for Study 1, males aged 20&#x02013;44 years inclusive, with a body weight of 50.0 to &#x0003c;80.0&#x000a0;kg and a body mass index (BMI) of 18.5 to &#x0003c;25.0 kg/m<sup>2</sup>; for Study 2, males aged 20&#x02013;44 years inclusive, with a body weight of 50.0 to &#x0003c;80.0&#x000a0;kg and a BMI of 17.6 to &#x0003c;26.4&#x000a0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. Major exclusion criteria for both studies were current or previous hepatic, renal, heart, respiratory, or gastrointestinal disease or cerebrovascular disorder; concurrent or previous malignant tumor; upper gastrointestinal disease within 7 days prior to the start of the study (Study 2 only); any clinically significant deviation from normal in physical examination, vital signs, electrocardiogram (ECG) or clinical laboratory determinations; history of drug allergy; history of hypersensitivity to &#x003b2;-adrenoceptor agonists or exposure to study drug (Study 2 only); prior exposure to long-term medication (at least 28 days; Study 1 only), any investigational drug within 120&#x000a0;days, or prescription or over-the-counter medications within 1&#x000a0;week prior to the start of the study. In both studies, concomitant medication was not allowed throughout the duration of the study. All subjects provided written informed consent before screening.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study Designs</title><p>Study 1 was a single-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, parallel group, single- and multiple-dose escalation study in 64 healthy male subjects to assess the single- and multiple dose pharmacokinetics and tolerability of mirabegron, formulated as a sustained release tablet using the oral controlled absorption system (OCAS) technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The study consisted of two parts. In Part I, each subject received a single oral dose of mirabegron [50, 100, 200, 300 (as 100&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;200&#x000a0;mg tablet), or 400 mg (as 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;200&#x000a0;mg tablet)] or matching placebo (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6 active, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2 placebo) with 200&#x000a0;mL of water. Subjects were fasted overnight prior to dosing and remained fasted until 4&#x000a0;h postdose. In Part II, each subject received a single oral dose of mirabegron (100 or 200&#x000a0;mg) or matching placebo (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8 active, <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 placebo) with 200&#x000a0;mL of water, followed by a 2-day washout period and once-daily oral doses for 7&#x000a0;days (Days 4&#x02013;10). Dosing occurred within 30&#x000a0;min to 1&#x000a0;h after breakfast and no additional food was served until 4&#x000a0;h postdose. Subjects were admitted to the clinical site on the day before dosing (Day &#x02212;1) and were confined until discharge on Day 4 (Part I) or Day 13 (Part II). Subjects underwent a post-study visit 4 days after the last administration or after early discontinuation.</p><p>Study 2 was a single-dose, open-label, three-period, intra-subject dose-escalation study in 12 healthy male subjects to assess the dose proportionality of the mirabegron OCAS. Each subject received escalating single doses of mirabegron 25, 50 and 100 (as 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;50 mg tablet) mg with 150 mL of water in three separate treatment periods, with a washout period of at least 12 days between treatments. Subjects were fasted overnight prior to dosing and remained fasted until 4&#x000a0;h postdose. Subjects were admitted to the clinical site on the day before dosing (Day &#x02212;1) and were confined until discharge on Day 4 of each treatment period. Subjects underwent a post-study visit within 13&#x02013;17&#x000a0;days after the last administration or after early discontinuation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample Collection and Analysis</title><p>In Study 1, blood samples for plasma mirabegron concentrations were collected into tubes containing sodium-EDTA as anticoagulant and sodium fluoride as stabilizer at predose and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 24, 36, 48, and 72&#x000a0;h postdose in Part I, and at predose and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 24, 36, 48, and 72&#x000a0;h postdose on Days 1 and 10, and predose on Days 5, 6, 7, 8, and 9 of Part II. In Study 2, blood samples for plasma mirabegron concentrations were collected into tubes containing sodium-heparin as anticoagulant and sodium fluoride as stabilizer at predose and at 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 24, 36, 48, and 72&#x000a0;h postdose in all periods. In Part I and Part II (Days 1 and 10) of Study 1, urine samples for measurement of unchanged mirabegron were collected within 12&#x000a0;h prior to dosing (Part I and Day 1 of Part II) and from 0 to 12, 12 to 24, 24 to 36, 36 to 48, and 48 to 72&#x000a0;h postdose.</p><p>Plasma was collected by centrifugation and plasma and urine samples were stored at &#x02212;65&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C or below and &#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C or below, respectively, until analysis. Liquid&#x02013;liquid extraction was used to extract mirabegron from plasma constituents. Urine samples were diluted prior to analysis. Samples were assayed by validated liquid chromatography analytical methods coupled with tandem mass spectrometric detection (LC&#x02013;MS/MS) using an atmospheric pressure chemical ionization interface, as described previously with minor modifications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The calibration ranges were 1.0&#x02013;500&#x000a0;ng/mL in plasma and 2.0&#x02013;1,000 ng/mL in urine for Study 1, and 0.2&#x02013;100&#x000a0;ng/mL in plasma for Study 2. In the bioanalytical method validation studies, within-run precision of quality control (QC) standards was less than 5.8&#x000a0;% for plasma and less than 7.2&#x000a0;% for urine. The within-run accuracy (relative error) of the assays over the QC range ranged from &#x02212;5.0 to 10.0&#x000a0;% for plasma and from &#x02212;6.9 to 13.0&#x000a0;% for urine.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Pharmacokinetic Analysis</title><p>Concentration data of mirabegron in plasma and urine were analyzed by non-compartmental methods using SAS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> version 8.2 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA), or WinNonlin Professional<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> version 5.0.1 (Study 1) or 5.2.1 (Study 2) (CERTARA, St. Louis, MO, USA). The following pharmacokinetic parameters were obtained as applicable and as appropriate for each study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]: <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>; time to reach <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> (<italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>); AUC (obtained by the linear-logarithmic trapezoidal method) from time zero to 24&#x000a0;h (AUC<sub>24</sub>) and AUC from time zero to infinity (AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>) after single-dose administration, and AUC during a dosage interval (AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub>); terminal elimination half-life (<italic>t</italic><sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub>); apparent total body clearance from plasma after oral administration (CL/<italic>F</italic>); apparent volume of distribution during terminal phase after non-intravenous administration (<italic>V</italic><sub>z</sub>/<italic>F</italic>); cumulative percentage of unchanged drug excreted into the urine (Ae%) up to 72&#x000a0;h postdose; and renal clearance (CL<sub>R</sub>). Actual sampling times were used in all calculations involving sampling times, and nominal sampling times were used for the mean concentration&#x02013;time figures.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Tolerability Assessments</title><p>Tolerability was assessed based on physical examinations, vital signs (axillary body temperature, supine blood pressure, and supine pulse rate), resting 12-lead ECGs, standard clinical laboratory tests (hematology, blood biochemistry, urinalysis), and adverse event (AE) monitoring. Clinically significant adverse changes in any tolerability assessment, including symptoms and signs, vital signs, ECGs, and clinical laboratory tests, were considered AEs. AEs were collected from the time of dosing until the end of the study. The causal relationships for all AEs were categorized by the investigator as probable, possible, or not related.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical Methods</title><p>Tolerability data were evaluated descriptively, and AEs were described in their entirety. All randomized subjects who received at least one dose of study drug were included in the tolerability analyses. Summary statistics were calculated for all pharmacokinetic parameters by dose. All subjects who received at least one dose of study drug and had at least one mirabegron plasma concentration measured were included in the pharmacokinetic analysis.</p><p>In both studies, dose-proportionality was examined for natural log transformed <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> using a power model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The following model was used: ln(pharmacokinetic parameter)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x003b2;0&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;&#x003b2;1&#x000b7;ln(dose), where &#x003b2;0 is the intercept and &#x003b2;1 is the slope of the model. Dose proportionality was concluded if the 95&#x000a0;% confidence interval (CI) for &#x003b2;1 included 1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. To assess accumulation of mirabegron with multiple dosing (Study 1), 90&#x000a0;% CIs around the geometric mean ratio (GMR) of mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> on Day 10 versus <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>24</sub> on Day 1 were constructed. To evaluate if mirabegron demonstrates linear pharmacokinetics with time during repeated administration, 90&#x000a0;% CIs around the GMR for mirabegron AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> on Day 10 versus AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> on Day 1 were constructed. For linear pharmacokinetics with time, the AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> at steady state is equal to the AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> following a single dose (i.e., a ratio of 1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The MIXED procedure of SAS<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> version 8.2 was used for all statistical analyses, with subjects as a random effect in Study 2.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Study Population</title><p>The disposition of the subjects in Study 1 and their characteristics are summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. A total of 64 healthy male subjects (40 in Part I and 24 in Part II) were randomized to study treatment and all completed the study. In Study 2, 12 healthy male subjects were enrolled and all completed the study. Their mean age was 29.7 years (range 22&#x02013;37), with a mean body weight of 59.8 kg (range 54.9&#x02013;73.1) and a mean BMI of 21.1 kg/m<sup>2</sup> (range 19.2&#x02013;23.4). In both studies, none of the subjects received a concomitant medication during the treatment periods.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Subject demographics in the single- and multiple ascending dose study (Study 1)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Variable</th><th align="left" colspan="6">Single dose (Part I)</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Multiple dose (Part II)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Placebo</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">200&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">300&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">400&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">Placebo</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">200&#x000a0;mg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">24.5 (20&#x02013;29)</td><td align="left">22.5 (21&#x02013;25)</td><td align="left">23.3 (20&#x02013;31)</td><td align="left">23.2 (22&#x02013;26)</td><td align="left">23.2 (21&#x02013;29)</td><td align="left">23.8 (20&#x02013;27)</td><td align="left">24.0 (20&#x02013;31)</td><td align="left">23.3 (21&#x02013;29)</td><td align="left">23.6 (20&#x02013;27)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Body weight (kg)</td><td align="left">61.9 (53.7&#x02013;74.0)</td><td align="left">60.9 (57.5&#x02013;65.5)</td><td align="left">57.0 (51.7&#x02013;63.4)</td><td align="left">64.5 (57.2&#x02013;72.1)</td><td align="left">59.3 (51.6&#x02013;65.8)</td><td align="left">62.0 (52.8&#x02013;73.1)</td><td align="left">59.8 (54.5&#x02013;64.7)</td><td align="left">62.7 (55.7&#x02013;70.4)</td><td align="left">63.5 (56.2&#x02013;75.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</td><td align="left">20.8 (19.1&#x02013;22.7)</td><td align="left">20.8 (19.4&#x02013;22.1)</td><td align="left">20.0 (18.9&#x02013;22.4)</td><td align="left">21.6 (19.1&#x02013;23.5)</td><td align="left">20.2 (19.0&#x02013;22.8)</td><td align="left">20.9 (18.5&#x02013;24.0)</td><td align="left">20.8 (19.0&#x02013;22.9)</td><td align="left">21.3 (19.7&#x02013;23.9)</td><td align="left">21.0 (19.5&#x02013;22.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data for age, BMI, and body weight are presented as mean (range)</p><p>
<italic>BMI</italic> body mass index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Pharmacokinetics of Mirabegron</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Single Dose</title><p>The mean plasma concentrations of mirabegron for 72&#x000a0;h after single oral doses of 50&#x02013;400 mg in Study 1 Part I and 25&#x02013;100 mg mirabegron in Study 2 are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. A summary of the pharmacokinetic parameters is shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. Following single-dose administration of mirabegron 25&#x02013;400&#x000a0;mg in the fasting state, mean <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> values ranged from 2.8 to 4.0&#x000a0;h postdose across the tested dose range (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). After reaching <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>, mirabegron plasma concentrations exhibited an apparent biphasic decline, with a mean <italic>t</italic><sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub> ranging from 23.9 to 36.4&#x000a0;h in Study 1, and 28.6 to 32.9&#x000a0;h in Study 2. In both studies, mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> increased more than proportionally with dose (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). For Study 2 (25&#x02013;100 mg), the mean estimates of the parameter &#x003b2;1 in the power model were 1.501 for ln(<italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub>) (95&#x000a0;% CI 1.146&#x02013;1.856) and 1.342 for ln(AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>) (95&#x000a0;% CI 1.102&#x02013;1.583). Neither of the CIs included 1, indicating a non-proportional increase in exposure with increasing dose. These slope estimates result in a predicted 2.8-fold increase in <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and a 2.5-fold increase in AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> for every twofold increase in dose within the range of 25&#x02013;100&#x000a0;mg. Similar estimates for &#x003b2;1 were obtained in Study 1 Part I (50&#x02013;400 mg), with mean estimates for &#x003b2;1 of 1.501 (95&#x000a0;% CI 1.222&#x02013;1.781) for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and 1.260 (95&#x000a0;% CI 1.120&#x02013;1.400) for AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>. However, visual assessment of scatter plots of dose-adjusted <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) suggests a more than dose-proportional increase in mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> in the 50 and 100&#x000a0;mg doses, but a dose-dependent increase at high doses, i.e., in the 300 and 400&#x000a0;mg groups. In both studies, mean estimates of CL/<italic>F</italic> and <italic>V</italic><sub>z</sub>/<italic>F</italic> decreased with increasing dose, whereas <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub> and <italic>t</italic><sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub> were independent of dose across the tested dose range. In Study 1 Part I, Ae% was dose-dependent with mean values ranging from 7.20&#x000a0;% after 50&#x000a0;mg to 14.6&#x000a0;% after 300&#x000a0;mg. CL<sub>R</sub> appeared to show no dose dependency, with mean values ranging from 9.91 to 15.2&#x000a0;L/h.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Mean (&#x000b1;standard deviation) plasma concentrations of mirabegron after single oral administration of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system in healthy male subjects in <bold>a</bold> Study 1 Part I (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6/dose) and <bold>b</bold> Study 2 (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12/dose)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40261_2013_146_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Pharmacokinetic parameters of mirabegron after single oral doses of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system under fasting</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Study 1 Part I</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Study 2</th></tr><tr><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">200&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">300&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">400&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">25&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">50&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left">100&#x000a0;mg</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="left">31.0 (18.1)</td><td align="left">131 (43.8)</td><td align="left">165 (83.0)</td><td align="left">549 (92.5)</td><td align="left">720 (264)</td><td align="left">9.88 (3.91)</td><td align="left">30.1 (16.8)</td><td align="left">80.5 (31.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (h)</td><td align="left">3.5 (1.4)</td><td align="left">3.3 (0.8)</td><td align="left">2.8 (1.3)</td><td align="left">3.7 (1.0)</td><td align="left">4.0 (1.3)</td><td align="left">3.6 (1.0)</td><td align="left">3.5 (0.9)</td><td align="left">3.3 (1.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AUC<sub>last</sub> (ng&#x000b7;h/mL)</td><td align="left">224 (79.0)</td><td align="left">773 (216)</td><td align="left">1,252 (417)</td><td align="left">3,053 (300)</td><td align="left">3,917 (695)</td><td align="left">85.6 (34.1)</td><td align="left">230 (81.3)</td><td align="left">578 (193)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (ng&#x000b7;h/mL)</td><td align="left">292 (76.9)</td><td align="left">882 (235)</td><td align="left">1,383 (441)</td><td align="left">3,285 (334)</td><td align="left">4,143 (736)</td><td align="left">106 (40.7)</td><td align="left">275 (90.0)</td><td align="left">663 (214)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic>
<sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub> (h)</td><td align="left">36.4 (11.8)</td><td align="left">30.8 (3.4)</td><td align="left">26.4 (3.6)</td><td align="left">25.1 (4.3)</td><td align="left">23.9 (4.9)</td><td align="left">32.9 (7.8)</td><td align="left">31.9 (6.3)</td><td align="left">28.6 (5.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CL/<italic>F</italic> (L/h)</td><td align="left">183 (58.1)</td><td align="left">119 (28.1)</td><td align="left">158 (50.6)</td><td align="left">92.2 (10.9)</td><td align="left">99.8 (22.0)</td><td align="left">288 (159)</td><td align="left">202 (73.8)</td><td align="left">174 (89.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>V</italic>
<sub>z</sub>/<italic>F</italic> (L)</td><td align="left">9,818 (4,880)</td><td align="left">5,405 (1,742)</td><td align="left">5,934 (1,879)</td><td align="left">3,300 (373)</td><td align="left">3,347 (465)</td><td align="left">13,020 (5,892)</td><td align="left">9,325 (3,681)</td><td align="left">7,049 (3,406)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ae%</td><td align="left">7.20 (2.32)</td><td align="left">7.61 (3.62)</td><td align="left">9.01 (2.66)</td><td align="left">14.6 (2.48)</td><td align="left">11.8 (2.55)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CL<sub>R</sub> (L/h)</td><td align="left">15.2 (1.85)</td><td align="left">9.91 (4.45)</td><td align="left">14.6 (1.96)</td><td align="left">14.3 (1.80)</td><td align="left">12.1 (2.07)</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean (standard deviation)</p><p>
<italic>Ae</italic>% cumulative percentage of unchanged drug excreted into the urine, <italic>AUC</italic> area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve, <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>last</italic></sub> AUC from time zero to time of last measurable concentration, <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sub> AUC from time zero to infinity, <italic>CL/F</italic> apparent total body clearance from plasma after oral administration, <italic>CL</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic></sub> renal clearance, <italic>C</italic>
<sub><italic>max</italic></sub> maximum plasma concentration, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</italic></sub> terminal elimination half-life, <italic>t</italic>
<sub>max</sub> time to reach <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub>, <italic>V</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
<italic>/F</italic> apparent volume of distribution during terminal phase after non-intravenous administration, &#x02013; no data</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Dose-normalized AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (<bold>b</bold>) after single oral administration of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system 50, 100, 200, 300 and 400&#x000a0;mg in healthy male subjects in Study 1 Part I. Individual data are presented. <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sub> area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve from time zero to infinity, <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> maximum plasma concentration</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40261_2013_146_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Dose-normalized AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (<bold>b</bold>) after single oral administration of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system 25, 50, and 100&#x000a0;mg in healthy male subjects in Study 2. Individual data are presented. <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sub> area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve from time zero to infinity, <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> maximum plasma concentration</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40261_2013_146_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Multiple Dose</title><p>Mean plasma concentrations after single doses (Day 1) and multiple doses (Days 4&#x02013;10) of mirabegron 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg in Study 1 are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. A summary of the pharmacokinetic parameters of mirabegron on Days 1 and 10 in Study 1 is shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. After multiple doses of 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg, mirabegron plasma concentrations were visually assessed to be at steady state within 7&#x000a0;days (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The GMR of AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> on Day 10 to AUC<sub>24</sub> on Day 1 was 2.12 (90&#x000a0;% CI 1.74&#x02013;2.58) in the 100&#x000a0;mg group and 1.75 (90&#x000a0;% CI 1.44&#x02013;2.14) in the 200&#x000a0;mg group, indicating that mirabegron accumulates approximately twofold with once-daily dosing. The GMR for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> was 1.55 and 0.91 on Day 10 compared with Day 1 for the 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg dose, respectively. The GMR of AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> on Day 10 to AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> on Day 1 was 1.28 (90&#x000a0;% CI 1.08&#x02013;1.52) in the 100&#x000a0;mg group and 1.18 (90&#x000a0;% CI 0.99&#x02013;1.40) in the 200&#x000a0;mg group. The CI for the 100&#x000a0;mg dose did not include 1, suggesting that mirabegron exhibits non-linear pharmacokinetics over time at a 100&#x000a0;mg but not a 200&#x000a0;mg dose. Consistent with these results, the mean CL/<italic>F</italic> decreased with repeat dosing compared with single-dose administration. Mean values for <italic>t</italic><sub>max</sub>, <italic>t</italic><sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub>, and CL<sub>R</sub> were similar between Days 10 and 1, indicating that there were no obvious changes in the elimination and CL<sub>R</sub> of mirabegron.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Mean (&#x000b1;standard deviation) plasma concentrations of mirabegron after single (Day 1) and multiple oral administration (Days 4&#x02013;10) of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system in healthy male subjects in Study 1 Part II (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8/dose)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40261_2013_146_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Pharmacokinetic parameters of mirabegron after single and multiple oral doses of mirabegron oral controlled absorption system in Study 1 (Part II)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="2">100&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left" colspan="2">200&#x000a0;mg</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Day 1</th><th align="left">Day 10</th><th align="left">Day 1</th><th align="left">Day 10</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="left">91.2 (42.0)</td><td align="left">136 (52.5)</td><td align="left">313 (77.6)</td><td align="left">291 (90.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">t<sub>max</sub> (h)</td><td align="left">4.8 (0.5)</td><td align="left">5.0 (0.0)</td><td align="left">5.0 (0.0)</td><td align="left">5.0 (0.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AUC<sub>last</sub> (ng&#x000b7;h/mL)</td><td align="left">537 (112)</td><td align="left">1,198 (190)</td><td align="left">1,471 (365)</td><td align="left">2,663 (426)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AUC (ng&#x000b7;h/mL)<sup>a</sup>
</td><td align="left">616 (111)</td><td align="left">793 (157)</td><td align="left">1,632 (373)</td><td align="left">1,909 (366)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>t</italic>
<sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub> (h)</td><td align="left">28.8 (6.8)</td><td align="left">30.0 (4.4)</td><td align="left">27.4 (7.7)</td><td align="left">28.0 (1.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CL/F (L/h)</td><td align="left">167 (31.4)</td><td align="left">132 (33.4)</td><td align="left">128 (27.2)</td><td align="left">108 (19.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>V</italic>
<sub>z</sub>/<italic>F</italic> (L)</td><td align="left">7,088 (2,681)</td><td align="left">5,690 (1,502)</td><td align="left">5,063 (1,734)</td><td align="left">4,390 (943)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ae%</td><td align="left">7.91 (1.93)</td><td align="left">11.9 (2.17)</td><td align="left">10.1 (2.88)</td><td align="left">12.4 (2.79)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CL<sub>R</sub> (L/h)</td><td align="left">14.8 (2.00)</td><td align="left">15.2 (2.11)</td><td align="left">13.8 (2.78)</td><td align="left">13.0 (2.03)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean (standard deviation)</p><p>
<italic>Ae</italic>% cumulative percentage of unchanged drug excreted into the urine, <italic>AUC</italic> area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve, <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>last</italic></sub> AUC from time zero to time of last measurable concentration, <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sub> AUC from time zero to infinity, <italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x003c4;</italic></sub> AUC during a dosage interval, <italic>CL/F</italic> apparent total body clearance from plasma after oral administration, <italic>CL</italic>
<sub><italic>R</italic></sub> renal clearance, <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> maximum plasma concentration, <italic>t</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</italic></sub> terminal elimination half-life, <italic>t</italic>
<sub>max</sub> time to reach <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub>, <italic>V</italic>
<sub><italic>z</italic></sub>
<italic>/F</italic> apparent volume of distribution during terminal phase after non-intravenous administration</p><p>
<sup>a</sup>AUC reported as AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> for Day 1 and AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> for Day 10</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Tolerability</title><p>In Study 1 Part I, 12 AEs were reported by eight (20&#x000a0;%) of the 40 subjects, and nine of these were considered by the investigator to be related to study drug. The AEs were all mild in intensity and occurred in one (17&#x000a0;%), three (50&#x000a0;%), and four (67&#x000a0;%) subjects in the 100, 300, and 400&#x000a0;mg groups, respectively. No AEs were observed in the placebo, 50 or 200&#x000a0;mg groups. The most common AEs (reported by &#x02265;2 subjects) were increased pulse rate and increased blood amylase. Pulse rates exceeding 100&#x000a0;beats/min at 4&#x02013;6&#x000a0;h after dosing occurred in three of six subjects in the 400&#x000a0;mg group. One of these three subjects with increased heart rate also developed palpitations at 3&#x000a0;h after dosing. There were no episodes of clinically significant increases in pulse rate or palpitations in other dose groups. Pulse rate tended to increase in a dose-dependent manner at 6&#x000a0;h postdose in the 200&#x000a0;mg and higher dose groups compared with the placebo group. Increases in blood amylase that were considered AEs by the investigator, occurred in two of six subjects in the 300&#x000a0;mg group and one of six subjects in the 100&#x000a0;mg group. In Part II, eight AEs were reported by five (21&#x000a0;%) of the 24 subjects, and two of these were considered by the investigator to be related to study drug. The AEs occurred in two (25&#x000a0;%), two (25&#x000a0;%), and one (12.5&#x000a0;%) subjects in the placebo, 100, and 200&#x000a0;mg groups, respectively. All AEs were mild in intensity and reported by one subject each. Increases in pulse rate were observed at 6&#x000a0;h after the first administration in the 200&#x000a0;mg group and at 6&#x000a0;h after the last administration in the 100 and 200&#x000a0;mg groups as compared with the placebo group. None of the pulse rate increases were judged clinically significant by the investigator. There were no clinically significant changes in blood pressure, body temperature, 12-lead ECG, or physical examination results.</p><p>In Study 2, there were six AEs reported by four (33&#x000a0;%) of the 12 subjects, and five of these were considered by the investigator to be related to study drug. Of the six AEs, two and four events occurred in two and three subjects receiving a 25 and 50&#x000a0;mg dose, respectively. All were mild in intensity and reported by one subject each. Mean supine pulse rate at 6&#x000a0;h postdose appeared to show a dose-dependent increase. Mean systolic blood pressure tended to increase at 3&#x02013;6&#x000a0;h postdose; however, it was considered to be due to circadian rhythm. There were no apparent changes in mean diastolic blood pressures and no clinically significant findings in ECG data. No deaths, serious AEs, or AEs requiring symptomatic therapy occurred in either study. All AEs resolved spontaneously.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>In these studies in healthy Japanese male subjects, mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> were reached on average within 2.8&#x02013;4.0&#x000a0;h following single-dose oral administration and at 5.0&#x000a0;h following multiple-dose administration. Steady-state conditions were reached by 7&#x000a0;days of once-daily administration with mirabegron, and accumulation of mirabegron was about twofold. These findings are in accordance with previously published single- and multiple-dose studies in healthy non-Japanese individuals, which mainly comprised Caucasians (60&#x02013;100&#x000a0;%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The mean <italic>t</italic><sub>&#x000bd;&#x003b2;</sub> of mirabegron (25.1&#x02013;36.4&#x000a0;h) was consistent with the range observed in non-Japanese males following single- (27.9&#x02013;40.6&#x000a0;h) and multiple-dose administration (29.2&#x02013;36.8&#x000a0;h) in those previous studies that used a similar sampling duration (up to 72 or 96&#x000a0;h postdose) as the present studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p>A greater than dose-proportional increase in exposure was observed following single-dose administration across the 25&#x02013;100&#x000a0;mg dose range, resulting in a predicted 2.8- and 2.5-fold increase in mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>, respectively, with each doubling of the dose within this dose range. Similar deviations from dose proportionality (approximately 3.0-fold for <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and 2.7-fold for AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>) were observed in a single-dose pharmacokinetics study in healthy non-Japanese male subjects using the same dose range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Above 100&#x000a0;mg, the dose non-proportionality was much less marked as the normalized AUC&#x02013;dose relationship began to reach a maximum. A postulated mechanism for the non-proportionality of mirabegron pharmacokinetics after oral administration is the decrease in the action of gut efflux transporters (predominantly P-glycoprotein) with increasing doses that reduce the bioavailability of mirabegron [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The efflux ability of these transporters may be saturated at higher doses (above 100&#x000a0;mg), resulting in a return to dose proportionality.</p><p>A small increase (28&#x000a0;% at 100&#x000a0;mg and 18&#x000a0;% at 200&#x000a0;mg) in AUC<sub>&#x003c4;</sub> at steady state compared with first-dose AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> was observed, suggesting that mirabegron may exhibit non-linear pharmacokinetics over time (i.e., an increase in bioavailability and/or a decrease in clearance with time) at these doses. Similar deviations from linear pharmacokinetics (ranging from a 6&#x000a0;% increase at 100&#x000a0;mg to 38&#x000a0;% increase at 300&#x000a0;mg) were observed in a multiple-dose pharmacokinetics study in healthy non-Japanese individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. As mirabegron exhibited linear pharmacokinetics with time at a clinically relevant dose of 50&#x000a0;mg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], the clinical meaningfulness of the finding is likely to be limited.</p><p>A retrospective comparison of mirabegron exposure in Japanese and non-Japanese (primarily Caucasian) healthy men was conducted. Only single-dose data at 25, 50, 100, and 200&#x000a0;mg from Study 1 Part I and Study 2 were used for the comparison, as these were generated under similar food conditions (i.e., after an overnight fast) as those obtained in the non-Japanese subjects. The comparison revealed that mean <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> values for mirabegron in Japanese male subjects at the lower dose levels (25, 50, and 100&#x000a0;mg) were higher than those observed in previous studies at the same dose level in non-Japanese male individuals (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Differences ranged from approximately 32&#x000a0;% at 25&#x000a0;mg to 58&#x000a0;% at 100&#x000a0;mg. For mean <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> at 200&#x000a0;mg and mean AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> at all evaluated dose levels, values were generally comparable or only slightly higher in Japanese subjects. The apparent differences in mean mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and, to a lesser extent, AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> between Japanese and non-Japanese individuals most likely reflect the variability in <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> and AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> observed within and across studies of mirabegron pharmacokinetics, and the small sample size in the present and previous studies. In addition, the differences are attributable in part to differences in body weight (mean weight ranging from 58.8 to 64.5&#x000a0;kg in Japanese subjects vs. 80.0 to 83.5 kg in non-Japanese subjects) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The differences in mirabegron <italic>C</italic><sub>max</sub> were smaller when values were normalized for body weight (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Such weight-based trends have been observed in previous studies with mirabegron. Correction for body weight nearly completely eliminated differences in mirabegron exposure between healthy men and women after intravenous administration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], and markedly reduced sex differences in exposure after single- and multiple-dose oral administration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Comparison of single-dose mean plasma exposure of mirabegron in healthy Japanese and Western (non-Japanese) male subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th align="left" colspan="2">25&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left" colspan="2">50&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left" colspan="2">100&#x000a0;mg</th><th align="left" colspan="2">200&#x000a0;mg</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Japanese</th><th align="left">Western [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</th><th align="left">Japanese</th><th align="left">Western [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</th><th align="left">Japanese</th><th align="left">Western [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</th><th align="left">Japanese</th><th align="left">Western [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">
<italic>n</italic>
</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">17</td><td char="." align="char">18</td><td char="." align="char">26</td><td char="." align="char">18</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Body weight (kg)</td><td align="left">59.8 (4.90)</td><td align="left">83.5 (15.4)</td><td align="left">60.2 (4.4)</td><td align="left">82.9 (12.4)</td><td align="left">58.8 (4.8)</td><td align="left">80.5 (12.2)</td><td align="left">64.5 (5.27)</td><td align="left">80.0 (9.5)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">
<italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL)</td><td align="left">9.88 (3.91)</td><td align="left">7.51 (4.21)</td><td align="left">30.4 (16.7)</td><td align="left">21.8 (8.61)</td><td align="left">97.2 (42.5)</td><td align="left">61.4 (27.1)</td><td align="left">165 (83.0)</td><td align="left">158 (75.7)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weight-corrected <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL&#x000b7;kg)</td><td align="left">591 (234)</td><td align="left">626 (354)</td><td align="left">1,832 (1,020)</td><td align="left">1,820 (786)</td><td align="left">5,670 (2,357)</td><td align="left">4,860 (2,090)</td><td align="left">10,422 (4,846)</td><td align="left">12,050 (4,500)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (ng&#x000b7;h/mL)</td><td align="left">106 (40.7)</td><td align="left">96.8 (39.1)</td><td align="left">281 (84.0)</td><td align="left">278 (70.5)</td><td align="left">736 (239)</td><td align="left">658 (152)</td><td align="left">1,383 (441)</td><td align="left">1,195 (501)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Weight-corrected AUC<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> (ng&#x000b7;h/mL&#x000b7;kg)</td><td align="left">6,347 (2,471)</td><td align="left">8,080 (3,330)</td><td align="left">16,870 (4,952)</td><td align="left">22,930 (6,250)</td><td align="left">43,032 (13,354)</td><td align="left">52,780 (13,820)</td><td align="left">88,272 (25,476)</td><td align="left">92,750 (30,760)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Data are presented as mean (standard deviation). Japanese data were obtained in Study 1 Part I and Study 2; Western data were taken from Eltink et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and Krauwinkel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</p><p>
<italic>AUC</italic>
<sub><italic>&#x0221e;</italic></sub> area under the plasma concentration&#x02013;time curve from time zero to infinity, <italic>C</italic>
<sub>max</sub> maximum plasma concentration</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Mirabegron was well-tolerated in healthy Japanese subjects. No serious AEs or discontinuations as a result of AEs were reported at any dose of mirabegron administered in either study. These tolerability findings are consistent with single- and multiple-dose studies conducted in non-Japanese, predominantly Caucasian, healthy subjects at single doses of mirabegron up to 300&#x000a0;mg or multiple daily doses of up to 300&#x000a0;mg [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The most common AEs were increased pulse rate in Study 1, and the pulse rate tended to increase dose dependently. These trends are reported by Krauwinkel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Mirabegron exhibited a greater than dose-proportional increase in exposure after single and multiple oral doses of mirabegron OCAS in healthy Japanese male subjects. Steady-state conditions were reached by 7 days of once-daily administration, and accumulation of mirabegron was about twofold. The single- and multiple-dose pharmacokinetic characteristics and deviations from dose proportionality in healthy Japanese male subjects were similar to those observed in non-Japanese (primarily Caucasian) subjects in previous studies.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The studies were sponsored by Astellas Pharma Inc. The authors thank Virginie Kerbusch, PhD (PharmAspire Consulting) for scientific writing support, for which she received financial compensation from Astellas. Drs. Tokuno, Matsushima, Katashima, Sawamoto, Takusagawa, and Van Gelderen, and Ms. Iitsuka and Amada played a substantial role in the design and overall management of the study, and the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data. Drs. Tanaka and Miyahara were involved in data collection. All authors listed were involved in the critical review and revision of the manuscript, and all provided final approval of the content.</p><sec id="d30e2256"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>Drs. Tokuno, Matsushima, Katashima, Sawamoto, Takusagawa, and Van Gelderen, and Ms. Iitsuka and Amada are paid employees of Astellas Pharma. Drs. Tanaka and Miyahara were the primary study investigators, for which they received financial compensation from Astellas. The authors have indicated that they have no other conflicts of interest with regard to the content of this article.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takasu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ukai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of (R)-2-(2-aminothiazol-4-yl)-4&#x02019;-{2-[(2-hydroxy-2-phenylethyl)amino]ethyl} acetanilide (YM178), a novel selective &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist, on bladder function</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther.</source><year>2007</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>642</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.106.115840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17293563</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b2;3-adrenoceptors in human detrusor muscle</article-title><source>Urology.</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0090-4295(01)01635-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007519</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapple</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x003b2;3-adrenoceptors in urinary bladder</article-title><source>Neurourol Urodyn.</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>752</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nau.20420</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600372</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Astellas Pharma. Betanis tablets Japanese prescribing information. July 2011.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.info.pmda.go.jp/shinyaku/P201100119/80012600_22300AMX00592_A100_1.pdf">http://www.info.pmda.go.jp/shinyaku/P201100119/80012600_22300AMX00592_A100_1.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Oct 2013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Astellas Pharma US Inc. Myrbetriq United States prescribing information. June 2012. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/drugsatfda/index.cfm?fuseaction=Search.Set_Current_Drug&#x00026;ApplNo=202611&#x00026;DrugName=MYRBETRIQ&#x00026;ActiveIngred=MIRABEGRON&#x00026;SponsorApplicant=APGDI&#x00026;ProductMktStatus=1&#x00026;goto=Search.Label_ApprovalHistory">http://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cder/drugsatfda/index.cfm?fuseaction=Search.Set_Current_Drug&#x00026;ApplNo=202611&#x00026;DrugName=MYRBETRIQ&#x00026;ActiveIngred=MIRABEGRON&#x00026;SponsorApplicant=APGDI&#x00026;ProductMktStatus=1&#x00026;goto=Search.Label_ApprovalHistory</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Oct 2013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Athanasopoulos A, Giannitsas K. An overview of the clinical use of antimuscarinics in the treatment of overactive bladder. Adv Urol. 2011;2011:820816</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eltink</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaddelee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single dose pharmacokinetics and absolute bioavailability of mirabegron, &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist for treatment of overactive bladder</article-title><source>Int J Clin Pharm Ther.</source><year>2012</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>838</fpage><lpage>849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5414/CP201782</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krauwinkel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dijk</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaddelee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pharmacokinetic properties of mirabegron, a &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist: results from two phase I, randomized, multiple-dose studies in healthy young and elderly men and women</article-title><source>Clin Ther.</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>2144</fpage><lpage>2160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2012.09.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takusagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Lier</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Absorption, metabolism and excretion of [14C]mirabegron (YM178), a potent and selective &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist, after oral administration to healthy male volunteers</article-title><source>Drug Metab Dispos.</source><year>2012</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/dmd.111.043588</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takusagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of human cytochrome P450 isoforms and esterases involved in the metabolism of mirabegron, a potent and selective &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist</article-title><source>Xenobiotica.</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>957</fpage><lpage>967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00498254.2012.675095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22509825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Gelderen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An exploratory comparison of the single dose pharmacokinetics of the &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist mirabegron in healthy CYP2D6 poor and extensive metabolizers</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther.</source><year>2009</year><volume>85</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>S88</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sawamoto T, Lee J, Alak A, et al. Phase I, open-label, drug interaction study to evaluate the effect of multiple doses of ketoconazole on single dose mirabegron (YM178) oral controlled absorption system (OCAS) in healthy adult subjects. Clin Pharmacol Ther 2011; 89(Suppl. 1):S21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Medical Association Declaration of Helsinki. Ethical principles for medical research involving human subjects. Adopted by the 18th WMA General assembly and amended by 48th WMA General Assembly, Somerset West, South Africa, October 1996. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wma.net/en/30publications/10policies/b3/">http://www.wma.net/en/30publications/10policies/b3/</ext-link>. Accessed 29 Oct 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Registration of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use. Guideline for good clinical practice E6(R1). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ich.org/fileadmin/Public_Web_Site/ICH_Products/Guidelines/Efficacy/E6_R1/Step4/E6_R1__Guideline.pdf">http://www.ich.org/fileadmin/Public_Web_Site/ICH_Products/Guidelines/Efficacy/E6_R1/Step4/E6_R1__Guideline.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 31 July 2013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapple</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The development of the oral controlled absorption system (Ocas&#x000ae;): a new improved formulation of tamsulosin</article-title><source>Eur Urol Suppl</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eursup.2005.07.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Teijlingen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Meijer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Takusagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of LC-MS/MS methods for the determination of mirabegron and its metabolites in human plasma and their application to a clinical pharmacokinetic study</article-title><source>J Chromatogr B Analyt Technol Biomed Life Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>887&#x02013;888</volume><fpage>102</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jchromb.2012.01.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22317789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabrielsson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic data analysis: concepts and applications</source><year>2007</year><edition>4</edition><publisher-loc>Stockholm</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Swedish Pharmaceutical Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gough</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutchison</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keene</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Assessment of dose proportionality: report from the statisticians in the pharmaceutical industry/pharmacokinetics UK joint working party</article-title><source>Drug Inf J</source><year>1995</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1048</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenhende</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSante</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Confidence interval criteria for assessment of dose proportionality</article-title><source>Pharm Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1278</fpage><lpage>1283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1026451721686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11145235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rowland</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tozer</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><source>Clinical pharmacokinetics: concepts and application</source><year>1995</year><edition>3</edition><publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &#x00026; Wilkins</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takusagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushigome</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nemoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intestinal absorption mechanism of mirabegron, a potent and selective &#x003b2;3-adrenoceptor agonist: involvement of human efflux and/or influx transport systems</article-title><source>Mol Pharm.</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1783</fpage><lpage>1794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/mp300582s</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23560393</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>