<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIPS</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-682X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6838</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25478273</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4247943</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/215732</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Supersensitivity Psychosis and Its Response to Asenapine in a Patient with Delusional Disorder</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rajkumar</surname><given-names>Ravi Philip</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Psychiatry, Jawaharlal Institute of Postgraduate Medical Education and Research (JIPMER), Pondicherry 605 006, India</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Ravi Philip Rajkumar: <email>ravi.psych@gmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: Shusuke Numata</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>2014</volume><elocation-id>215732</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2014 Ravi Philip Rajkumar.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Supersensitivity psychosis is a recognized complication of long-term antipsychotic treatment, in which patients develop new or reemergent psychotic symptoms, generally accompanied by dyskinetic movements, due to prolonged dopamine receptor blockade and resultant supersensitivity. Though it is most closely associated with schizophrenia and the use of typical antipsychotic agents, it has also been documented in patients with other diagnoses, and in those receiving atypical antipsychotics. There is no established treatment for this condition. In this paper, we describe a patient with persistent delusional disorder, jealous type, who developed a supersensitivity psychosis characterized by persecutory delusions, auditory hallucinations, and thought insertion in association with mild tardive dyskinesia. These symptoms resolved completely following six weeks of treatment with the second-generation antipsychotic asenapine, 20&#x02009;mg/day. The mechanisms and implications of the patient's symptomatology and response are discussed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>The term &#x0201c;supersensitivity psychosis&#x0201d; was first introduced into the psychiatric literature by Chouinard and Jones to refer to the emergence of psychotic symptoms in patients on long-term antipsychotic therapy [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Such symptoms are thought to result from dopamine receptor supersensitivity consequent to chronic blockade of D<sub>2</sub> dopamine receptors in the mesolimbic pathway, a mechanism analogous to that of tardive dyskinesia [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], though other processes such as cholinergic neuronal loss have been proposed [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Supersensitivity psychoses have been most commonly reported in patients with schizophrenia [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], though documented cases have also been reported in schizoaffective disorder [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], in bipolar disorder [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], in intellectual disability [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and even in subjects with no past history of mental illness [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Though its existence has been disputed by some authors [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], there has been a renewed interest in this condition with the realization that even newer &#x0201c;atypical&#x0201d; antipsychotics may be implicated in its causation [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Criteria for its diagnosis have been developed by Fallon et al. [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], based on both Chouinard's descriptions and further research. These include that though there is no approved treatment for supersensitivity psychosis, various approaches have been suggested, including risperidone [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], clozapine [<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], and anticonvulsants [<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. We report the case of a woman with delusional disorder who developed supersensitivity psychosis following ziprasidone therapy and who remitted when treated with the atypical antipsychotic asenapine.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case Report</title><p>Mrs. D, a married woman aged 44, first presented to our clinic three years ago with seven years' continuous illness characterized by a single, well-systematized delusion of infidelity. This belief would lead to frequent quarrels with her husband, which sometimes escalated to physical violence. At presentation, she had never received any prior antipsychotic therapy, though she had received intermittent treatment with divalproex for &#x0201c;aggression.&#x0201d; A diagnostic evaluation revealed no medical or neurological causes of psychosis and no evidence of substance abuse or dependence. She was diagnosed to have persistent delusional disorder, jealous type (ICD code F22.0). As she was distressed about weight gain while on divalproex, she was offered treatment with aripiprazole, 15&#x02009;mg/day, along with supportive couples therapy. However, she showed an inadequate response to this drug even after two months of continuous treatment. Her medication was changed to ziprasidone, which was initiated at 80&#x02009;mg/day, which led to some improvement in her delusional belief over the next ten months. Due to a slight worsening of her symptoms in the context of a family dispute, this was increased to 100&#x02009;mg/day. Within two weeks of the dose increase, she developed perioral and lingual dyskinetic movements. Her Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale score was 4. As the movements were slight and were not causing significant distress, she agreed to continue ziprasidone at the same dose. This resulted in good symptomatic improvement for a month, after which she developed fresh symptoms which were quite unlike her initial presentation. Delusions of infidelity were absent; instead, she reported persecutory delusions towards her brother-in-law, second person auditory hallucinations of a male voice with derogatory content, and thought insertion. There were no pervasive mood changes associated with these symptoms, though she was distressed by the experience of thought insertion. A provisional diagnosis of paranoid schizophrenia was made, but given the relationship of her symptoms to her orolingual dyskinesias and the late age of onset, this was revised to supersensitivity psychosis as per Fallon and Dursun's criteria.</p><p>Ziprasidone was tapered and stopped, and she was treated with asenapine, initiated at 10&#x02009;mg/day and slowly increased to 20&#x02009;mg/day over the next month. After 6 weeks of treatment with 20&#x02009;mg/day of asenapine, she reported a complete resolution of her new psychotic symptoms and had no dyskinetic movements. Her former delusion of infidelity did not return. She has been followed up for 18 months thereafter and has remained in remission, even after asenapine was decreased to 15&#x02009;mg/day due to a complaint of daytime sedation. Her relationship with her husband remains satisfactory, and she has been able to return to work as a high school teacher.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>Our patient fulfilled all the revised diagnostic criteria for a supersensitivity psychosis proposed by Fallon et al. [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These criteria are as follows.<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Emergence of psychotic symptoms&#x02014;delusions, hallucinations, and thought alienation phenomena&#x02014;when on treatment with antipsychotics other than clozapine or quetiapine for over 1 year.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Presence of abnormal involuntary movements.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Compliance with antipsychotic treatment.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of any significant life events or stressors.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Absence of any organic brain injury or substance abuse, including alcohol.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Significant interference in social and occupational functioning due to these symptoms.</p></list-item></list></p><p>In our patient, the likely offending agent was ziprasidone. Ziprasidone-induced supersensitivity psychosis has been reported earlier in an adolescent, though the time course of symptoms differed from that seen in our case [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Certain aspects of our patient's phenomenology are strikingly similar to earlier reports; for example, both thought alienation [<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] and persecutory delusions [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] have been documented in earlier cases of supersensitivity psychosis. As many patients with delusional disorder receive long-term antipsychotics, it is possible that at least some cases of apparent diagnostic transition from delusional disorder to schizophrenia&#x02014;a phenomenon reported in as many as 42% of patients in one study [<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]&#x02014;may actually represent supersensitivity psychoses.</p><p>The choice of asenapine as a treatment modality in this patient was based on the fact that, like ziprasidone and aripiprazole, it is associated with lower rates of weight gain. However, there are theoretical reasons to believe that this drug may be useful in supersensitivity psychoses<italic> per se,</italic> because asenapine is a potent antagonist of serotonin 5-HT2A receptors [<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and 5-HT2A blockade may reduce the D2 receptor supersensitivity responsible for these patients' symptoms [<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>In conclusion, this case suggests that supersensitivity psychoses can occur in patients with delusional disorder and should be considered in patients whose psychotic symptoms apparently change while receiving antipsychotic therapy. Antipsychotics with strong 5-HT2A antagonism, such as asenapine, may be a safe and effective treatment option in such patients.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The author declares that there is no conflict of interests regarding the publication of this paper.</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B. D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis: clinical and pharmacologic characteristics</article-title><source><italic>The American Journal of Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1980</year><volume>137</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0018835477</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6101522</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Severe cases of neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis. Diagnostic criteris for the disorder and its treatment</article-title><source><italic>Schizophrenia Research</italic></source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0920-9964(91)90050-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0025772098</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1677263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of striatal cholinergic neurons as a basis for tardive and L-dopa-induced dyskinesias, neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis and refractory schizophrenia</article-title><source><italic>Biological Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1993</year><volume>34</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3223(93)90044-E</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0027363506</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7904833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigelow</surname><given-names>L. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug withdrawal in chronic schizophrenic patients: in search of neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology</italic></source><year>1981</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004714-198105000-00002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0019795186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6117582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis: retrospective study of schizophrenic inpatients</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1988</year><volume>49</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0023746720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2899071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dursun</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A naturalistic controlled study of relapsing schizophrenic patients with tardive dyskinesia and supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Psychopharmacology</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>755</fpage><lpage>762</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79960484808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881109359097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20147573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanahara</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishige</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muneoka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamanaka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiina</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sekine</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiraishi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A prospective comparative study of risperidone long-acting injectable for treatment-resistant schizophrenia with dopamine supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Schizophrenia Research</italic></source><year>2014</year><volume>155</volume><issue>1&#x02013;3</issue><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2014.02.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84899491639</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24667073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margolese</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauclair</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;langer</surname><given-names>M.-C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic tolerance and rebound psychosis during quetiapine maintenance monotherapy in patients with schizophrenia and schizoaffective disorder</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004714-200208000-00003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036323747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12172332</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laporta</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis in patients with bipolar affective disorder</article-title><source><italic>Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>81</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>437</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0025371994</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0447.1990.tb05477.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1972608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witschy</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychosis after neuroleptic withdrawal in a manic-depressive patient</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1984</year><volume>141</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0021328871</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6691422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sovner</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioridazine withdrawal-induced behavioral deterioration treated with clonidine: two case reports</article-title><source><italic>Mental Retardation</italic></source><year>1995</year><volume>33</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0029131291</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>J.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teng</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>K.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>W. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e0;lez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demers</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metoclopramide-induced supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Annals of Pharmacotherapy</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>36</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1387</fpage><lpage>1390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1345/aph.1A440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036707917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12196057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>J. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitiello</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroleptic withdrawal in patients meeting criteria for supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>51</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0025158353</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1974249</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ash</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Craighead</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adolescent female with withdrawal psychosis following abrupt termination of ziprasidone</article-title><source><italic>European Child and Adolescent Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00787-012-0239-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-84862861722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22249643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fallon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dursun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deakin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug-induced supersensitivity psychosis revisited: characteristics of relapse in treatment-compliant patients</article-title><source><italic>Therapeutic Advances in Psychopharmacology</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23983951</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vainer</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;langer</surname><given-names>M.-C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnier</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaudry</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>J.-Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risperidone and clozapine in the treatment of drug-resistant schizophrenia and neuroleptic-induced supersensitivity psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Progress in Neuropsychopharmacology and Biological Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1994</year><volume>18</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1129</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0278-5846(94)90116-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0028109927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chouinard</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of supersensitivity psychosis with antiepileptic drugs: report of a series of 43 cases</article-title><source><italic>Psychopharmacology Bulletin</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0025064971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2274634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malcolm</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supersensitivity psychosis with concurrent episodic vomiting</article-title><source><italic>British Journal of Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1992</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.161.3.407</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0026646311</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1356574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitty</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McTigue</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamali</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Callaghan</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnostic stability four years after a first episode of psychosis</article-title><source><italic>Psychiatric Services</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>56</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1084</fpage><lpage>1088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ps.56.9.1084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-24644457574</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16148321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minassian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the clinical efficacy of asenapine in schizophrenia</article-title><source><italic>Expert Opinion on Pharmacotherapy</italic></source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2107</fpage><lpage>2115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14656566.2010.506188</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-77954787424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20642375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessmer</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serotonin 5-HT2A receptors underlie increased motor behaviors induced in dopamine-depleted rats by intrastriatal 5-HT2A/2C agonism</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Therapeutics</italic></source><year>2004</year><volume>310</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>694</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.104.066365</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-3042760666</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15044557</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>