<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIM.PSYCHIATRY</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-682X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6838</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23984153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3747447</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/761567</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Venlafaxine-Induced Orthostatic Hypotension in a Geriatric Patient</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chikkaramanjegowda</surname><given-names>Vidyashree</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Leon</surname><given-names>Jose</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Psychiatry, College of Medicine, University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY 40509, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>University of Kentucky Mental Health Research Center, Eastern State Hospital, Lexington, KY 40508, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Jose de Leon: <email>jdeleon@uky.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editors: I. G. Anghelescu, M. Kellner, and J. Saiz-Ruiz</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>31</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><elocation-id>761567</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 V. Chikkaramanjegowda and J. de Leon.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Venlafaxine is not usually associated with risk of orthostatic hypotension. A 65-year-old US Caucasian female taking 225&#x02009;mg/day of venlafaxine extended-release developed symptomatic orthostatic hypotension. The systolic and diastolic blood pressure dropped by 25 and 18&#x02009;mm Hg, respectively, from supine position to standing position within 3 minutes. The patient was otherwise healthy and the orthostatic hypotension resolved with venlafaxine discontinuation. This was a probable venlafaxine adverse drug reaction according to the Naranjo scale. This case contributes to the scarce literature that indicates that clinicians need to be aware that occasionally venlafaxine can induce clinically significant orthostatic hypotension, particularly in geriatric patients. Our patient did not have orthostatic hypotension when she was taking venlafaxine at 60 years of age in higher venlafaxine doses (300&#x02009;mg/day) but developed this adverse drug reaction when venlafaxine was restarted at the geriatric age. This case indicates that a history of prior tolerance to venlafaxine does not guarantee tolerance after 65 years of age. If a clinician decides to use venlafaxine in geriatric patients, the clinician should warn the patient about the risk of orthostatic hypotension and consider very slow titration and low doses.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>The Consensus Committee of the American Autonomic Society and the American Academy of Neurology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] defined orthostatic hypotension as &#x0201c;a reduction of systolic blood pressure (BP) of at least 20&#x02009;mm Hg or diastolic BP of at least 10&#x02009;mm Hg within 3 minutes of standing.&#x0201d; This consensus definition has recently been updated with minor changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p> Orthostatic hypotension can be an adverse drug reaction (ADR) to several antidepressants and antipsychotics. These drugs can cause orthostatic hypotension during the first few weeks of treatment but usually tolerance develops. Thus, the risk for hypotension is one of the reasons that slow titration is recommended for some of these drugs. Orthostatic hypotension is usually explained by the alpha-<sub>1</sub> antagonistic properties of some antidepressants and antipsychotics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Among antidepressants, several of the tricyclic antidepressants (TCAs) are potent alpha-<sub>1</sub> antagonists, but venlafaxine is usually considered to be lacking in antagonist properties at these receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Articles focused on venlafaxine cardiovascular ADRs describe venlafaxine as being prone to cause hypertension, but it is not considered to cause orthostatic hypotension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. The blockade of the noradrenergic reuptake transporter explains why venlafaxine can frequently cause hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>].</p><p> We described one case of venlafaxine-induced orthostatic hypotension that was carefully assessed using the Naranjo scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], one of the most frequently used ADR scales. This case contributes to the scarce literature that indicates that clinicians need to be aware that occasionally venlafaxine can induce clinically relevant orthostatic hypotension, particularly in geriatric patients. Moreover, our patient did not have orthostatic hypotension with prior venlafaxine treatment but developed this ADR when she reached geriatric age.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case Presentation</title><p> A 65-year-old US Caucasian female had a history of<italic> DSM-IV-TR</italic> major depressive disorder and anxiety disorder NOS. She had no significant medical problems. For three years (from 57 to 60 years of age), she was treated with 300&#x02009;mg/day of venlafaxine extended-release (150&#x02009;mg twice a day) and 10&#x02009;mg of zolpidem at night. She had no ADRs, but, due to a change in the coverage of her medical insurance, she was switched from venlafaxine to citalopram (20&#x02009;mg/day). After 6 months, she asked her psychiatrist to switch her antidepressant due to uncontrolled anxiety. For the next 2 years (from 60 to 62 years of age), she tried duloxetine (60&#x02009;mg/day), but, after observing a worsening of tics, she was switched back to citalopram (20&#x02009;mg/day) and she was stable for 3 years. At age 65, after worsening of her tics, the patient requested her psychiatrist (VC) to switch her to venlafaxine extended-release.</p><p> The psychiatrist started venlafaxine extended-release 75&#x02009;mg/day and recommended gradual titration to the target dose of 300&#x02009;mg/day (150&#x02009;mg administered twice a day) over 5-week duration. Citalopram was tapered off in 7 days. At 5-week followup, when the patient had been on venlafaxine for 4 weeks, including a dose of 225&#x02009;mg/day for 14 days, the patient complained of &#x0201c;lightheadedness&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;blacking out,&#x0201d; particularly when rising from supine to standing position. This worsened with the increased dose of venlafaxine. The patient had no other medical problems; her only other medication was zolpidem at the same dose (10&#x02009;mg at night) for the last 2 years. The psychiatrist established that the patient met criteria for orthostatic hypotension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] since the systolic and diastolic BP dropped by 25 and 18&#x02009;mm Hg, respectively, from supine position to standing position within 3 minutes. The systolic BP dropped from 135 to 110&#x02009;mm Hg while the diastolic dropped from 94 to 76&#x02009;mm Hg. She was tapered off venlafaxine in 7 days and restarted on citalopram. One week later (3 days after the complete discontinuation of venlafaxine), the patient reported a complete resolution of the symptoms. In a follow-up visit (3 weeks after the complete resolution of symptoms), she did not have any significant change in her orthostatic blood pressure; her systolic BP dropped by 8&#x02009;mm Hg (from 118 to 110&#x02009;mm Hg) while the diastolic dropped by 7&#x02009;mm Hg (from 69 to 62&#x02009;mm Hg) from supine position to standing position within 3 minutes. The BP drop no longer met the criteria for orthostatic hypotension.</p><p> The patient's psychiatrist (VC) scored the probability that this ADR was explained by venlafaxine treatment using the Naranjo scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. She obtained a score of 8 (range up to 9) that indicated that the ADR was probably associated with venlafaxine treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p> The Naranjo scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] indicated that the ADR was probably associated with venlafaxine treatment. A PubMed search using the terms &#x0201c;venlafaxine and orthostatic hypotension&#x0201d; provided a case report by Duggal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] and a geriatric study by Johnson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Duggal et al. described a clinically relevant orthostatic hypotension case in a 46-year-old Indian male with two episodes of falls on 225&#x02009;mg/day of venlafaxine extended-release [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. They did not provide a score using the Naranjo scale. With the available published information, one of us (VC) obtained a score of 7 indicating a probable venlafaxine ADR. Johnson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] described an open-label 12-week study on 72 geriatric patients taking venlafaxine. They measured orthostatic changes in 47 of their patients weekly. There were 38 patients who had no orthostatic changes at baseline before starting venlafaxine; 50% of them had orthostatic changes at least twice during the 12 weeks. More importantly, of the 30 patients who did not endorse dizziness at baseline, 8 developed mild dizziness during venlafaxine treatment. Although other cardiovascular ADRs were associated with venlafaxine discontinuation, no patient discontinued venlafaxine due to orthostatic changes and/or dizziness. It was recommended that patients with orthostatic changes drink more fluids and go from supine to standing position slowly. Thus, this recommendation appeared sufficient to avoid symptomatic orthostatic changes.</p><p>Duggal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] provided a reference for a relevant Australian venlafaxine study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] not included in PubMed. Alderman and Wiese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] described a retrospective review of 13 of 18 (72%) mainly geriatric patients who unexpectedly had orthostatic hypotension during titration. Contributing factors included (1) history of hypertension, or ischaemic heart disease, and (2) intake of antihypertensives, or nitrate vasodilators.</p><p> As antidepressants typically cause orthostatic hypotension by blocking alpha-<sub>1</sub> adrenergic receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], it is not unreasonable to suspect that this case may be also explained by venlafaxine blockade of these receptors. <italic>In vitro</italic> studies usually state that venlafaxine has no affinity for alpha-<sub>1</sub> adrenergic receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], but the affinity of venlafaxine metabolites for these receptors has never been studied, to the best of our knowledge. Some cases of lethal venlafaxine overdoses were associated with refractory hypotension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], indicating that something associated with venlafaxine treatment may cause, in special circumstances, clinically relevant alpha-<sub>1</sub> adrenergic blockade.</p><p> Our case is interesting in the sense that our patient did not develop orthostatic hypotension when she previously took venlafaxine (from 57 to 60 years of age), but she developed it when she reached 65 years of age. Geriatric age is frequently associated with clinically relevant changes in pharmacokinetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] and pharmacodynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The decrease in renal drug clearance may be the most important factor related to venlafaxine, since geriatric patients tend to have 50% higher plasma venlafaxine concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Geriatric age is associated with pharmacodynamic changes that are not well understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. According to Trifir&#x000f3; and Spina [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], one of the most evident pharmacodynamic geriatric changes is the selective dysfunction of the homeostatic systems that control the alpha-<sub>1</sub> adrenergic receptor system, which mediates acute changes in vasoconstriction. Thus, it can be postulated that during the last 5 years, our patient progressively developed a decrease in renal clearance and dysfunction of the alpha<sub>1</sub>-adrenergic receptor vascular system, which explained her orthostatic changes on venlafaxine at 65 years of age, despite no symptoms when she was younger.</p><p> In spite of the fact that venlafaxine is not expected to cause orthostatic hypotension, in some patients orthostatic hypotension may not only be clinically relevant but can be associated with substantial risks, particularly of falls. Our case is unique since the patient did not have orthostatic hypotension with prior venlafaxine treatment. However, when the patient was restarted on venlafaxine at 65 years of age, she was no longer able to tolerate lower venlafaxine doses than those she had taken 5 years earlier. Our case contributes to the literature that indicates the substantial risk of orthostatic hypotension in geriatric patients treated with venlafaxine. If a clinician decides to use venlafaxine in geriatric patients, the clinician should warn the patient about the risk of orthostatic hypotension and consider very slow titration and low doses. A history of prior tolerance to venlafaxine does not imply tolerance after 65 years of age.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Disclosure </title><p>No commercial organizations had any role in the writing of this paper for publication. In the last 3 years, Jose de Leon was a coinvestigator in an NIH Small Business Innovation Research Grant awarded to Genomas, Inc. In the last 3 years, Vidyashree Chikkaramanjegowda had no conflict of interests.</p></ack><ack><title>Acknowledgments </title><p>The authors acknowledge Lorraine Maw, M. A., at the Mental Health Research Center at Eastern State Hospital, Lexington, KY, USA, who helped in editing this paper.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Consensus Committee of the American Autonomic Society and the American Academy of Neurology</collab><article-title>Consensus statement on the definition of orthostatic hypotension, pure autonomic failure, and multiple system atrophy</article-title><source><italic>Neurology</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>46</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>p. 1470</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0029904204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wieling</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Axelrod</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Consensus statement on the definition of orthostatic hypotension, neurally mediated syncope and the postural tachycardia syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Clinical Autonomic Research</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>21</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79958702577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21431947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richelson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions of antidepressants with neurotransmitter transporters and receptors and their clinical relevance</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>64</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0142011218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14552650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feighner</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular safety in depressed patients: focus on venlafaxine</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1995</year><volume>56</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>579</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0029562267</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8530334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thase</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of venlafaxine on blood pressure: a meta-analysis of original data from 3744 depressed patients</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1998</year><volume>59</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>502</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0031755709</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9818630</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naranjo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Busto</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellers</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A method for estimating the probability of adverse drug reactions</article-title><source><italic>Clinical Pharmacology and Therapeutics</italic></source><year>1981</year><volume>30</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>245</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0019799332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7249508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duggal</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jagadheesan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nizamie</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Venlafaxine&#x02014;induced orthostatic hypotension</article-title><source><italic>Indian Journal of Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>371</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21407896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whyte</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulsant</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular changes associated with venlafaxine in the treatment of late-life depression</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Geriatric Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>14</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33748589476</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16943176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alderman</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiese</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unexpected orthostatic hypotension with venlafaxine</article-title><source><italic>Australian Journal of Hospital Pharmacy</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0032845767</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Doty</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Krygiel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fatality related to a 30-g venlafaxine overdose</article-title><source><italic>Pharmacotherapy</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>23</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1668</fpage><lpage>1672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0344011132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14695048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klotz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related changes in pharmacokinetics</article-title><source><italic>Current Drug Metabolism</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>601</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79961084008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21495970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trifir&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-related changes in pharmacodynamics: focus on drugs acting on central nervous and cardiovascular systems</article-title><source><italic>Current Drug Metabolism</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-79961039191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21495972</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unterecker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiemke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Greiner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of age, sex, smoking and co-medication on serum levels of venlafaxine and O-desmethylvenlafaxine under naturalistic conditions</article-title><source><italic>Pharmacopsychiatry</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22426847</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>