<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Reports Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Reports Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRII</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6609</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6617</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25954552</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4412090</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/236079</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>An IgG4-Related Salivary Gland Disorder: A Case Series Presenting with a Different Clinical Setting</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>Masayuki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fushiki</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>Yukio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Otolaryngology, Head &#x00026; Neck Surgery, University of Toyama, Toyama 930-0194, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Hiroaki Fushiki: <email>hfushiki@med.u-toyama.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editors: Francisco Blanco-Favela, Alessandro Plebani, Ming-Yuh Shiau, and Peter Szodoray</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>2011</volume><elocation-id>236079</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2011 Masayuki Ishida et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>K&#x000fc;ttner tumor is a chronic inflammatory disease that presents with a firm swelling of the submandibular gland and often mimics a neoplasm. Recently evidence suggests that K&#x000fc;ttner tumor may be a type of disorder characterized by IgG4-related inflammations. Herein, we report 3 cases of submandibular gland swellings with severe fibrosis, inflammation with marked lymphoplasmacytic infiltration; this pathology mimics clinical manifestation of a malignant tumor in 18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) findings.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>K&#x000fc;ttner tumor, commonly known as chronic sclerosing sialadenitis, is a chronic inflammatory disease that presents with firm swelling of the submandibular gland and often mimics a malignant tumor clinically [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that the pathogenesis of K&#x000fc;ttner tumor can be characterized by IgG4-related multifocal inflammations [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In the present study, we report 3 cases of an IgG4-related salivary gland disorder that cause bilateral or unilateral swelling of the submandibular gland, each presenting with a different clinical setting. Diagnostic features of the disorder will be discussed together with a literature review.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case Report</title><p>
<statement id="casee1"><title>Case 1 . </title><p>A 77-year-old male visited our university hospital because of a 2-month history of bilateral swelling of the submandibular region. Bilateral diffused enlargement of the submandibular glands was elastic hard and had good mobility on palpation. A computed tomography (CT) scan showed that the submandibular gland was bilaterally enlarged to approximately 30&#x02009;mm (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>). There was no significant swelling of lymph nodes in the neck. Laboratory tests were negative for SS-A and SS-B antibodies, with no increase in amylase activity. The swelling could not be resolved by treatment with antibiotics and antiphlogistic agents. A biopsy sample of the left submandibular gland was taken under local anesthesia. The biopsied tissue was white and hard. Histopathological examination revealed extensive fibrosis and diffuse lymphocyte infiltration, with scattering of a small number of eosinophilic leucocytes and lymphoid follicles. The salivary gland tissue was highly atrophied.</p></statement>
</p><p>
<statement id="casee2"><title>Case 2 . </title><p>A 59-year-old female was admitted to our university hospital because of a swelling in the right submandibular gland region for the third time. Swellings in the right submandibular gland region had occurred twice in the previous 2 years, and the biopsy samples showed &#x0201c;reactive lymph node&#x0201d; both times. CT showed that the right submandibular gland was enlarged to 40&#x02009;mm &#x000d7; 20&#x02009;mm, with several lymph nodes measuring up to 15&#x02009;mm in the periphery of the parotid gland and the right upper deep cervical region. </p><p>18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) showed a high and slightly heterogeneous increase in accumulations of FDG in the right submandibular region (standardized uptake value, SUV: 6.24), with a slight increase in accumulations in the upper dorsal to the right submandibular region, the right cervical regions, and the supraclavicular fossa (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figure 2</xref>). Laboratory tests were negative for SS-A and SS-B antibodies, with no increase in amylase activity. In order to rule out a possible right submandibular gland cancer with lymph node metastases or malignant lymphoma, the right submandibular gland was extirpated under general anesthesia. Histopathological examination revealed diffused, double-layered, small-sized gland ducts accompanied by lymphoid follicles forming a high-degree lymphocyte infiltration. Plasma cell and eosinophilic leukocyte infiltrations, relatively high-degree fibrosis, and many IgG4-positive plasma cells were also observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figure 3</xref>). Subsequent swelling occurred in the unaffected submandibular gland after a period, which was resolved by steroid treatment.</p></statement>
</p><p>
<statement id="casee3"><title>Case 3 . </title><p>A 61-year-old male was admitted to our university hospital because of a 1-year history of swelling of the right submandibular region. He reported that the swelling enlarged gradually over the year. CT showed a slightly contrast-enhanced mass, measuring 32&#x02009;mm &#x000d7; 22&#x02009;mm in the right submandibular region. Salivary gland scintigraphy (Tc-99&#x02009;m) showed a decrease in accumulations in the right posterior submandibular gland in early images. Laboratory tests were negative for SS-A and SS-B antibodies, with no increase in amylase activity. The right submandibular gland was extirpated under general anesthesia. Histopathological examination revealed that the submandibular glands were enlarged because of marked lymphocyte infiltration and only a few normal submandibular glands were present. There was a remarkably high degree of plasma cell infiltration in the fibroid portion of the glands.</p></statement>
</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>In 1896, K&#x000fc;ttner identified a disorder that causes tumor-like swelling of the submandibular glands, which was named after him [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It differs from nonspecific chronic sialadenitis in that the submandibular gland is commonly affected, hard tumor-like mass is present in clinical manifestation, and pathology shows florid lymphoplasmacytic infiltrate accompanied by prominent and progressive fibrosis. In 108 cases described by Isacsson and Lundquist, the mean age at diagnosis was 42&#x02013;45 years, with no gender difference [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The chief complaint is recurrent pain and/or swelling in one side of the neck [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Recent studies have shown that K&#x000fc;ttner tumor and Mikulicz's disease are serologically similar disorders that cause IgG4-related inflammations of the salivary gland and they both may produce similar lesions in organs other than the salivary gland [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Lesions of IgG4-related inflammations include the lacrimal glands, autoimmune pancreatitis, sclerosing cholangitis, interstitial nephritis, and retroperitoneal fibrosis [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>The 3 cases reported in this study are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1">Table 1</xref>. A definite diagnosis of the disorders in this study was made by histopathological examination of the salivary glands; all cases were diagnosed with IgG4-related chronic sclerosing sialadenitis, on the basis of the presence of high-degree infiltration of IgG4-positive plasma cells in the swollen submandibular gland tissues. </p><p>All 3 cases showed swelling of the submandibular region, but each presented with a different clinical manifestation. If the disease affects both sides, as in <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee1">Case 1</xref>, systemic autoimmune disorders such as K&#x000fc;ttner tumor, Mikulicz's disease, or Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome should be considered initially in the differential diagnosis. Mikulicz's disease, first reported by Mikulicz in 1892, is a disorder of unknown cause, showing sustained left-right symmetric swellings of the lacrimal gland as well as the salivary gland [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. In contrast, Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome is manifested by xerostomia and keratoconjunctivitis sicca accompanied by the swelling of the salivary glands. K&#x000fc;ttner tumor and Mikulicz's disease are serologically characterized by high levels of serum IgG and its subtype IgG4, and it is mostly negative for the antinuclear antibodies (ANA) and anti-SS-A and -SS-B, which are often positive in Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Histological examination showed the presence of IgG4-positive plasma cell infiltration in Mikulicz's disease but not in Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Chronic sclerosing sialadenitis with widespread involvement of the major and minor salivary glands has been reported as a usual presentation [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Mikulicz's disease and K&#x000fc;ttner tumor may be subtypes of an identical clinical entity with IgG4-related inflammations, with the extent and severity of the lesions within the salivary gland presenting with different clinical manifestations.</p><p>In unilateral cases similar to our tumor-like Cases <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee2">2</xref> and <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee3">3</xref>, it may not be easy to diagnose this disorder. If the submandibular swelling occurs unilaterally with abnormal accumulations on FDG-PET (<xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee2">Case 2</xref>), malignancy such as a cancer or lymphoma is more likely to be suspected. Measurement of serum IgG4 concentrations is useful for diagnosing Mikulicz's disease: it was significantly greater in Mikulicz's disease than in other salivary gland diseases (a cutoff value of 135&#x02009;mg/dL) [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It may be also useful in differentiating clinically K&#x000fc;ttner tumor from neoplasm. If serum IgG4 concentration is within normal range, biopsy sample should be taken for a definite diagnosis (<xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee3">Case 3</xref>). Once a definite diagnosis of IgG 4-related chronic sclerosing sialadenitis is made on the basis of pathology, FDG-PET may be useful for characterizing multifocal lesions other than the salivary gland and/or assessing the therapeutic effects of corticosteroids [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Kitagawa et al. [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] found that 5 out of 12 patients with K&#x000fc;ttner tumor were associated with sclerosing lesions in the extrasalivary gland tissues. Treatment with steroids shows a good response in K&#x000fc;ttner tumor and Mikulicz's disease [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>In clinical practice, we recommend that K&#x000fc;ttner tumor should be treated as a systemic disorder rather than a salivary gland disorder, by otolaryngologists. Clinical whole-body examination and followup is necessary to find simultaneous and/or emerging IgG4-related inflammations of other sites when they did it.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;ttner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000dc;ber entz&#x000fc;ndliche tumoren der submaxillarspeicheldr&#x000fc;se</article-title><source><italic>Beitr Klin Chir</italic></source><year>1896</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34447587966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Abundant IgG4-positive plasma cell infiltration characterizes chronic sclerosing sialadenitis (K&#x000fc;ttner's tumor)</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Surgical Pathology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-21144435786</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.pas.0000164031.59940.fc</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897744</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamisawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hishima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Close correlation between chronic sclerosing sialadenitis and immunoglobulin G4</article-title><source><italic>Internal Medicine Journal</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33745600364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1445-5994.2006.01119.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16866659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isacsson</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahlner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundquist</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic sialadenitis of the submandibular gland. A retrospective study of 108 cases</article-title><source><italic>Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology</italic></source><year>1981</year><volume>232</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0019420678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7271582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naishiro</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinomura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title xml:lang="jp">The significance of disease-independence in Mikulicz's disease&#x02014;revival interests in Mikulicz's disease</article-title><source><italic>Nihon Rinsh&#x0014d; Men'eki Gakkai Kaishi</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33645455756</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2177/jsci.29.1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505597</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamano</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ochi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hydronephrosis associated with retroperitoneal fibrosis and sclerosing pancreatitis</article-title><source><italic>Lancet</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><issue>9315</issue><fpage>1403</fpage><lpage>1404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037140159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08359-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11978339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsushima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasuo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IgG4-associated multifocal systemic fibrosis complicating sclerosing sialadenitis, hypophysitis, and retroperitoneal fibrosis, but lacking pancreatic involvement</article-title><source><italic>Internal Medicine</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>1243</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-33845220790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2169/internalmedicine.45.1759</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17139126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mikulicz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000dc;ber eine eigenartige symmetrische Erkrankung der Tr&#x000e4;nen und Mundspeicheldr&#x000fc;sen</article-title><source><italic>Beitr&#x000e4;ge zur Chirurgie : Festschrift gewidmet Theodor Billroth</italic></source><year>1892</year><fpage>610</fpage><lpage>630</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabello-Inchausti</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic sclerosing sialadenitis (Kuttner's tumor): unusual presentation with bilateral involvement of major and minor salivary glands</article-title><source><italic>Annals of Diagnostic Pathology</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037293633</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/adpa.2003.50004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12616471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabata</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamisawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takuma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum IgG4 concentrations and IgG4-related sclerosing disease</article-title><source><italic>Clinica Chimica Acta</italic></source><year>2009</year><volume>408</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-69849104274</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cca.2009.06.036</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beneficial effects of steroid therapy for Mikulicz's disease</article-title><source><italic>Rheumatology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>44</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1322</fpage><lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-27144492958</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/rheumatology/kei026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16105910</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Cervical CT images of <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee1">Case 1</xref>. Bilateral swelling of the submandibular glands (arrows).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRII2011-236079.001"/></fig><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>FDG-PET images of <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee2">Case 2</xref>. (a) Intense uptake (SUV: 6.24) in the right submandibular gland (arrows). (b) Intense uptake in the right submandibular gland (thick arrows) and the deep interior cervical area (thin arrows).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRII2011-236079.002"/></fig><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Histopathological examination of <xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee2">Case 2</xref>. (a) Small-sized gland ducts with plasma cell and eosinophilic leukocyte infiltrations (H&#x00026;E stain&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x000d7;40). (b) IgG4-positive plasma cells (stained with IgG4 monoclonal antibody&#x02009;&#x02009;&#x000d7;40). Mouse monoclonal antibody to human IgG4 (clone, HP6025; dilution, 1&#x02009;:&#x02009;100; Zymed Laboratories Inc., Calif, USA).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRII2011-236079.003"/></fig><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of three case reports.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee1">Case 1</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee2">Case 2</xref>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref ref-type="statement" rid="casee3">Case 3</xref>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, gender</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 years old, male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59 years old, female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 years old, male</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swelling of the submandibular gland</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both sides</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initially, on the right side; after a period of time, on the left side</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right side</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum amylase</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within normal range</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within normal range</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within normal range</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum SS-A antibody</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum SS-B antibody</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum IgG<break/>(863&#x02013;1589&#x02009;mg/dL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2441</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1313</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1196</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Serum IgG4<break/>(4&#x02013;108&#x02009;mg/dL)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">451</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IgG4-positive plasma cells in salivary gland tissue</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histopathological<break/> diagnosis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic sclerosing sialadenitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic sclerosing sialadenitis</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic sclerosing sialadenitis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other organ lesions</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other image findings</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intense uptake on PET</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Decrease in accumulations on salivary gland scintigraphy</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></floats-group></article>