<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIM.PSYCHIATRY</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-682X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6838</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22937409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3420492</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2011/797658</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Stable Bipolar Patient Switched to Mania following Clinical Doses of Prednisone</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panwar</surname><given-names>Vikram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lassi</surname><given-names>Krishan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">Department of Psychiatry, Pawnee Mental Health Services, 2001 Claflin Road, Manhattan, KS 66502, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Krishan Lassi: <email>panwar15@hotmail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editor: D. De Leo</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>2011</volume><elocation-id>797658</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2011 V. Panwar and K. Lassi.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>We describe a stable bipolar female patient on medications that got switched into mania due to higher doses of prednisone prescribed for her severe sinusitis.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Steroids have been prescribed for a long time for variety of clinical conditions (Immunological diseases, cancers, respiratory conditions, and musculoskeletal conditions). Approximately, ten million steroid prescriptions are issued every year in USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Studies have reported three types of psychiatric adverse effects in patient on steroid therapy: (1) mild, nonpathological euphoria, (2) clinically significant psychiatric symptoms, (3) bipolar disorder induced by course of steroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Various reports have shown that incidence of steroid psychosis is between 5%&#x02013;20%. Most patients develop symptoms within days to weeks of starting treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]; but symptoms can occur any time after stopping the steroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. We present a case of 44-year-old female with a history of stable bipolar disorder who developed manic symptoms when started on prednisone for her severe sinusitis. She was stable on medicines for bipolar disorder for quite some time.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case</title><p>A 44-year-old, unemployed, married woman, living with her husband and 2 daughters was presented to the clinic with a history of mood swings and psychosis. She reported of having depressed mood, decreased energy, and a feeling of guilt and hopelessness for the last one week. She denied having any suicidal or homicidal ideations. The patient stated that she was diagnosed with bipolar II disorder at the age of 22 years; her symptoms were always mild and did not interfere with her activities. During her hypomanic phase she endorsed decrease in sleep, increased involvement in activities, high energy level, and impulsive activities (shopping spree). According to her in last few years her symptoms have increased in intensity and progressed into mania (delusions, illusions, auditory hallucinations, and obsessions). During manic period she did a lot of impulsive acts. During her most recent episode, she got obsessed with a person whom she felt she was in love with. She sent him text messages and followed him home; this continued for weeks. She was also involved in high-speed chase with cops and got into lot of trouble with law and family and had to be hospitalized. Three weeks prior to her hospitalization she was treated for her sinusitis with 60&#x02009;mg oral prednisone. She reported of having a similar switch from hypomania to mania in past on using prednisone for her sinusitis. In the hospital, her steroids were tapered 5&#x02009;mg every 4 days, and her symptoms were resolved.</p><p>She did not report any drug allergy or any kind of abuse during her childhood. Her family history was not known as she was adopted and did not know her biological parents. She used to work full time but was currently unemployed and was also in the process of divorce. She denied smoking, abusing, alcohol, or use of any recreational drugs. Her current medications are Trazodone (150&#x02009;mg QHS), Risperidone (1&#x02009;mg&#x02009;QAM), Zyprexa (15&#x02009;mg&#x02009;QHS), and Lithium (300&#x02009;mg&#x02009;TID).</p><p>On examination, the patient appeared her stated age and was clean with appropriate clothing. Her posture was appropriate and had normal body movement and speech. Her behavior was cooperative and had intact cognitive functions. She denied any perceptual disturbances currently, and her thought process was normal. She had a good insight about her mental illness but poor judgment as she had poor personal relationships.</p><p>Laboratory workup failed to reveal any significant abnormalities.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>Steroids have been widely prescribed for a long time for a variety of clinical conditions. Since 1950s, side effects of steroids have been well documented. Early side effects include insomnia, excitation, and distractibility followed by depression, mania, hypomania, and in some cases psychosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Studies have reported that majority of patients develop these symptoms within 3-4 days; but symptoms can occur as late as 3 weeks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Most of the patients recover within 5-6 weeks after tapering of steroids but it may take longer in some cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The cause of steroids side effects is not clearly understood, but it is believed to be due to cholinergic and dopaminergic stimulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Research has shown that steroids can alter sodium potassium pump and ion flux across membrane effecting norepinephrine metabolism particularly in reticular activating system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Various case reports show that there is linear dose response relationship; higher the dose (&#x0003e;40&#x02009;mg/day) the more the chances of developing psychotic episodes, but the dose does not seem to affect the rate of onset, duration, or severity of the symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Patient's past psychiatric history or age also appears to be unrelated to development of neurological symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Treatment for these side effects includes tapering of steroids and adding mood stabilizers (lithium, Valproic acid) or adding low doses of neuroleptics (haloperidol) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>It is important to distinguish primary mania from corticosteroid-induced mania in a patient with history of mental disorder who is on steroids. As incidence of type 1 bipolar disorder is 1.8%, many people with this disorder are on steroids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. A number of published reports describe mood disorder as a more prominent feature of steroid psychosis than psychosis and also higher incidence of psychotic features in corticosteroid-induced mania than in primary mania [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. When someone gets the diagnosis of steroid-induced psychosis it is easy to overlook bipolar disorder. Psychiatrists have long struggled with patients who do not fit clearly into diagnostic criteria.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>4. Conclusion</title><p>In our case a patient with history of bipolar II disorder stable on medications switched into mania when started on 60&#x02009;mg/day of prednisone. Her manic symptoms resolved after discontinuation of prednisone. So this proves a stable patient on medications switched to mania because of steroids. In our paper we did not find many cases in which stable bipolar patient switched to mania on clinical doses of prednisone.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sirois</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid psychosis: a review</article-title><source><italic>General Hospital Psychiatry</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>25</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>33</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12583925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary observations on mental disturbances occurring in patients under therapy with cortisone, and ACTH</article-title><source><italic>New England Journal of Medicine</italic></source><year>1952</year><volume>246</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14890837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid-induced psychotic and mood disorders</article-title><source><italic>Psychosomatics</italic></source><year>2001</year><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11815680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Psychiatric Adverse Drug Reactions: Steroid Psychosis</italic></source><year>1991</year><publisher-name>Clinical Advances Treatment Psychiatric disorder</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Manic-Depressive Illness</italic></source><year>1990</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppes</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of corticosteroid-induced mood changes with olanzapine</article-title><source><italic>American Journal of Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1999</year><volume>156</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>p. 968</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolkowitz</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinow</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Doran</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prednisone effects on neurochemistry and behavior. Preliminary findings</article-title><source><italic>Archives of General Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>47</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>968</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1977371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagliardi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>When steroids cause psychosis</article-title><source><italic>The Rheumatologist</italic></source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benyamin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafeyan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteroid induced psychosis in the pain management setting</article-title><source><italic>Pain Physician</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19057637</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerullo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corticosteriod induced mania: prepare for the unpredictable</article-title><source><italic>The Journal of Family Practice</italic></source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><issue>6</issue></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frances</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Docherty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The expert consensus guideline series: treatment of bipolar disorder</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>57, supplement 12</volume></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>