<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Reports Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Reports Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRII</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6609</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6617</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25383230</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4207592</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2012/186320</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intravenous Immunoglobulin and Mycophenolate Mofetil for Long-Standing Sensory Neuronopathy in Sj&#x000f6;gren's Syndrome</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Danieli</surname><given-names>Maria Giovanna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pettinari</surname><given-names>Lucia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morariu</surname><given-names>Ramona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Monteforte</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Logullo</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Clinica Medica, Dipartimento di Scienze Cliniche e Molecolari, Universit&#x000e0; Politecnica delle Marche &#x00026; Ospedali Riuniti, Via Tronto 10, 60126 Ancona, Italy</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>U.O. di Medicina-LPA, Presidio di Loreto, 66025 Loreto, Italy</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>U.O. di Radiodiagnostica, Ospedale di Casarano, 73042 Lecce, Italy</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Clinica Neurologica, Dipartimento di Medicina Sperimentale e Clinica, Polo Didattico Scientifico, Universit&#x000e0; Politecnica delle Marche &#x00026; Azienda Ospedali Riuniti, Via Tronto 10, 60126 Ancona, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Maria Giovanna Danieli: <email>mgdanieli@mail.com</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Academic Editors: N. Kutukculer, Y. Nozaki, B. Sarov, and A. Vojdani</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>2012</volume><elocation-id>186320</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>9</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2012 Maria Giovanna Danieli et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Sensory neuronopathy is described in association with the Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome (SS). We studied a 55-year-old woman with a 4-year history of progressive asymmetric numbness, distal tingling, and burning sensation in upper and lower limbs. In a few months, she developed ataxia with increased hypoanaesthesia. Electrodiagnostic tests revealed undetectable distal and proximal sensory nerve action potential in upper and lower limbs. Cervical spine magnetic resonance showed a signal hyperintensity of posterior columns. Previous treatment with high-dose glucocorticoids and azathioprine was ineffective. A combined treatment with intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil was followed by a progressive and persistent improvement. This case documented the efficacy and the safety of the coadministration of intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil in sensory neuronopathy associated with SS refractory to conventional immunosuppressive therapy.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Central nervous system involvement in Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome (SS) is rarely reported and may be severe and varied [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Sensory neuronopathy (or sensory ganglionopathy, SN) is a distinctive neuropathy of SS, accounting for 15&#x02013;20% of all neuropathies seen in this condition [<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. A sensory neuropathy is often the presenting feature of SS, and, therefore, a high index of suspicion is required, particularly in female patients with non-length-dependent, painful, or ataxic sensory neuropathy or those with trigeminal sensory and autonomic involvement [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. At the onset of SN, numbness, tingling, burning, and pain sensations are reported in all limbs, usually with asymmetric distribution. With the disease progression, the sensory disturbances can involve the trunk, the face or they develop into a symmetric way. On examination, degeneration of large sensory neurons leads to gait ataxia, proprioceptive sensory loss, and widespread deep tendon areflexia [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. When smaller sensory neurons are affected, deficits are those of hypoesthesia to pain and thermal stimuli with hyperacute pain. Autonomic nervous system involvement may cause fixed tachycardia, orthostatic hypotension, and gastrointestinal pseudo-obstruction. The response to treatment is usually poor, even with glucocorticoids, immunosuppressants, and plasmapheresis [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Here we report the case of a woman with primary SS who presented with SN that was successfully managed with intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil coadministration.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>2. Case Report</title><p>In 2001, a 55-year-old woman presented with progressive asymmetric numbness distal tingling and burning sensation in upper limbs associated with xerostomia and xerophtalmia. Antibodies to SS-A/Ro and anti-SS-B/La were positive. A minor salivary gland biopsy showed mononuclear cells with prominent lymphocyte infiltration with glandular cell atrophy. Nerve conduction studies showed a &#x0201c;sensory axonal neuropathy.&#x0201d; The diagnosis of SS was made according to the criteria of American-European Community [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and she was treated with anti-inflammatory drugs. In 2003, distal sensory deficits aggravated and extended to the lower limbs with increased hypo-anaesthesia and unsteady gait. In spite of treatment with oral prednisone (1&#x02009;mg/kg/day) and azathioprine (2&#x02009;mg/kg/day), distal sensory deficits progressed. Thus, she was admitted to our hospital in June, 2005.</p><p>On admission she was bedridden and she could not ambulate independently. A global impairment of sensation was detected as a profound loss in all lower limbs and, as moderate reduction, in the upper limbs. Deep tendon reflexes were absent. No autonomic symptoms were detected. Neurological examination of the cranial nerves was normal. Muscle strength was normal in all of the four limbs. Severe sensory ataxia was present in assisted gait. Romberg's sign was positive.</p><p>We documented a mild normocytic anaemia with lymphopenia with high erythrocyte sedimentation rate. The antinuclear antibody titre was elevated with positive anti-SS-A/Ro and anti-SS-B/La by fluorescence enzyme immunoassay. Levels of immunoglobulins (IgG, IgM, and IgA) and serum concentrations of complement levels (C3 and C4) measured by nephelometry were normal. As for serological autoimmune markers, immunofixation did not detect monoclonal immunoglobulins; cryoglobulins were negative, as ANA and rheumatoid factors (IgM-RF) and anti-CCP antibodies. HBV and HCV markers were negative. Electrodiagnostic studies revealed undetectable distal and proximal sensory nerve action potential (SNPAs) in upper and lower limbs. Nerve conduction studies were normal. Concentric needle examination of distal and proximal muscles was normal. Somatosensory-evoked potentials were absent with distal stimulation, both in upper and lower limbs. Spinal cord magnetic resonance disclosed high signal intensity without gadolinium enhancement in posterior columns of the cervical spinal cord (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>), findings consisting with the diagnosis of neuronopathy.</p><p>We started a combined treatment with intravenous immunoglobulin and oral mycophenolate mofetil. Intravenous immunoglobulin was infused at 1&#x02009;g/kg/day (5&#x02009;g/hour) on two consecutive days each month for six months, followed by further cycles every other month for six months. Oral mycophenolate mofetil was started at 500&#x02009;mg/day and then titrated to the definite dosage of 30&#x02009;mg/kg/day. Oral prednisone was slowly tapered from the initial dose of 1&#x02009;mg/kg/day to an average of 0.25&#x02009;mg/kg every other day.</p><p>Within three months, the patient presented a marked improvement in sensory symptoms, in gait and in the functional status. No modification of <italic>sicca syndrome</italic> was reported. She continued with MMF for one year more and with IVIg with decreased doses and longer intervals between courses for two years. At last followup she was ataxic but she can ambulate without support, and the sensory loss in upper and lower limbs was notably reduced. Magnetic resonance features were unchanged.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>3. Discussion</title><p>We report a case of a long-standing severe ganglionopathy in the context of SS for which the combined treatment with intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil was remarkably and persistently successful. The pathogenic mechanism responsible for the neuronopathy is still debated. Some authors have postulated that the dorsal root ganglion damage is associated with loss of neurons and mononuclear inflammatory infiltrates without vasculitis [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In the literature, few studies, mainly case reports or small series, investigated the therapeutic options for neuronopathy. More studies are available for nonvasculitic neuropathies associated with SS. For both forms, the response to traditional glucocorticoids and immunosuppressants is generally poor [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Cyclophosphamide, used preferentially in vasculitic neuropathies, is linked to a certain degree of toxicity. In sensory neuropathy associated with SS, positive results have been reported following the use of IVIg, with long-term sustained improvement and a reduction in the rate and severity of glucocorticoids-related adverse effects [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In a retrospective national multicentric study, Rist et al. [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] documented the benefit of IVIg in 19 patients with SS-related neuropathy without any necrotizing vasculitis. The clinical response was observed after two courses of IVIg administration, thus underlying the necessity to evaluate the treatment response only after two courses.</p><p>As for MMF in SS, we found in the literature only a small pilot trial in patients refractory to other immunosuppressants. The authors documented an improvement in xerophthalmia as well in some laboratory parameters (reduction of gamma globulins and IgM-RF titre, increase of C3 and C4 complement levels and white blood cell count) [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>No data are available on the use of coadministration of intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil in SS. In neuronopathy, the rationale of using intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil involves the cell-mediated [<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and humoral [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] immunological mechanisms underlying the ganglionopathy. Immunoglobulin is widely used in autoimmune diseases, intravenously and subcutaneously [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Among other mechanisms, intravenous immunoglobulin can affect T regulatory cells by increasing their suppressive function [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and accelerate the rate of the pathogenic IgG catabolism [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Mycophenolate mofetil affects the <italic>de novo</italic> synthesis of guanosine nucleotides thus inhibiting a crucial pathway for DNA synthesis in lymphocytes. The synergism between the action of intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil in suppressing the activation and the proliferation of lymphocytes could explain the favourable response and the long-term remission we observed.</p><p>We choose to continue the IVIg administration at monthly intervals, since in previous reports only repeated doses of IVIg permitted the maintenance of the clinical response [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Moreover, the use of IVIg enables a reduction of the infective risk in subjects treated with immunosuppressant. This point is of particular interest since immunodeficiency states are increasingly recognised in patients with immune-mediated diseases and they are due to intrinsic defect linked to the disease itself and/or to the immunosuppressant employed throughout the disease management.</p><p>In conclusion, we documented a distinct improvement of the disability linked to ganglionopathy within the first three months of intravenous immunoglobulin coadministered with mycophenolate mofetil treatment. The better neurological condition was maintained over a period of more than 4 years. The coadministration of intravenous immunoglobulin and mycophenolate mofetil was demonstrated to be beneficial and safe in a case of sensory neuronopathy associated with SS refractory to conventional immunosuppressive therapy.</p><p>
<statement id="head1"><title>Take Home Messages</title><p>
<list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>Intravenous immunoglobulin has been widely used in the treatment of immune-mediated diseases. </p></list-item><list-item><p>Not many reports described the intravenous immunoglobulin application in Sj&#x000f6;gren's syndrome, and even fewer are related to mycophenolate mofetil.</p></list-item><list-item><p> The use of intravenous immunoglobulin co-administered with mycophenolate mofetil permitted to attain a complete remission with a relevant functional recovery in a subject with long-standing refractory neuronopathy. </p></list-item><list-item><p> No side effects were linked to this combined treatment.</p></list-item></list>
</p></statement>
</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tob&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pers</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Devauchelle-Pensec</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Neurological disorders in primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Autoimmune Diseases</italic></source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>11 pages</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">645967</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mellgren</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000f6;ransson</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Omdal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome associated neuropathy</article-title><source><italic>Canadian Journal of Neurological Sciences</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>34</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-34548447034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17803024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sghirlanzoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pareyson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sensory neuron diseases</article-title><source><italic>Lancet Neurology</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-19344370192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vitali</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bombardieri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonsson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Classification criteria for Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome: a revised version of the European criteria proposed by the American-European Consensus Group</article-title><source><italic>Annals of the Rheumatic Diseases</italic></source><year>2002</year><volume>61</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>558</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0036092482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12006334</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cornblath</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ataxic sensory neuropathy and dorsal root ganglionitis associated with Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Annals of Neurology</italic></source><year>1990</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>304</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0025268531</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2327738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Benito-Leon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bermejo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez-Jimenez</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous immunoglobulin therapy in sensory neuropathy associated with Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Neurology Neurosurgery and Psychiatry</italic></source><year>1996</year><volume>60</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>p. 699</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0029934806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Benefit of IVIG for long-standing ataxic sensory neuronopathy with Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source><italic>Neurology</italic></source><year>2003</year><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-0037431997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12578938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hachulla</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Experience of intravenous immunoglobulin therapy in neuropathy associated with primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome: a national multicentric retrospective study</article-title><source><italic>Arthritis Care &#x00026; Research</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21584943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willeke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Schl&#x000fc;ter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Schotte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Domschke</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaubitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycophenolate sodium treatment in patients with primary Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome: a pilot trial</article-title><source><italic>Arthritis Research and Therapy</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-36949026702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antiganglion neuron antibodies correlate with neuropathy in Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome</article-title><source><italic>NeuroReport</italic></source><year>2005</year><volume>16</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-20044388943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15858405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seite</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoenfeld</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Youinou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillion</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What is the contents of the magic draft IVIg?</article-title><source><italic>Autoimmunity Reviews</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>439</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-51749088581</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18558358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Danieli</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettinari</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Logullo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabrielli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subcutaneous immunoglobulin in polymyositis and dermatomyositis: a novel application</article-title><source><italic>Autoimmunity Reviews</italic></source><year>2011</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>149</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-78751635995</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20858553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kessel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammuri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intravenous immunoglobulin therapy affects t regulatory cells by increasing their suppressive function</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Immunology</italic></source><year>2007</year><volume>179</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>5571</fpage><lpage>5575</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-38349137792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Elluru</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Negi</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of natural antibodies in immune homeostasis: IVIg perspective</article-title><source><italic>Autoimmunity Reviews</italic></source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>440</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2-s2.0-51749109351</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18558359</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>MRI 1.5T Axial section obtained with sequence GRE-T2 at C4 level showing a signal hyperintensity of posterior columns.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRII2012-186320.001"/></fig></floats-group></article>